<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ct on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ct/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (ct)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 17:54:21 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ct/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Thinking  in Primary Grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 17:54:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last week I spent a couple of days as part of a team running
professional development for a
group of pre and in service elementary school teachers. Two days
talking about computational thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wait a minute - elementary school teachers? I&amp;#39;m a high school guy
pretending to be a college guy. My extensive experience with
elementary school education is that I raised two kids and I don&amp;#39;t
think I messed them up too much. I don&amp;#39;t know anything about
elementary education!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How&amp;#39;d I ever get myself into this???
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
About a year ago my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt&#34;&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt; was encouraging me to apply for a grant to
explore computational thinking in elementary schools with the Robin Hood Foundation. I was
hesitant since elementary school is not my bag but since I also knew some
of the Robin Hood players I figured let&amp;#39;s see where things go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, coincidentally, I started talking to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yadavaman&#34;&gt;Aman Yadav&lt;/a&gt;. I had followed Aman
online for a number of years and was hoping to find an opportunity to
meet him somewhere down the line. Long story short, the two of us
decide to apply to for the Robin Hood Foundation grant together. I
felt much more comfortable than going solo since Aman had already done
some great CT work with Detroit teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, in spite of my insistence of not knowing primary ed,
Robin Hood decided to support our efforts. Last week, Aman and I,
joined by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/saraevogel&#34;&gt;Sarah Vogel&lt;/a&gt; who has also done some good work with CT in
primary grades and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CSEdPhil&#34;&gt;Phil Sands&lt;/a&gt; who is currently doing grad work with
Aman we ran two days of PD for 10 pre service and 10 in service
teachers. It was a mix of activities to explore concepts such as
debugging, decomposition, abstraction, and brainstorming on how the
teachers could bring these concepts to their classrooms in support of
core academic areas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Towards the end, I was sitting in on one group of teachers
energetically discussing how they could share what they learned with
their school. I then moved to another group where they were discussing
how core ideas from our exercises could be adapted to support teaching
writing. Really inspiring.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aman and I will be getting together with the pre and in service
teachers again in late August with the plan of developing concrete lessons
that both draw out CT concepts and support core subjects. I&amp;#39;m not
sure if Phil will be able to come out to join us but he&amp;#39;ll be involved
in the project for the long haul. We&amp;#39;re hoping Sara can also be as
involved moving forward but Sara&amp;#39;s very much in demand and very
busy so here&amp;#39;s hoping that her schedule permits it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the end the plan is to make everything the teachers develop
available to the greater CS Education community but we&amp;#39;re going for a
bigger win. If all of this works, the plan is to get some of these
practices into Hunter&amp;#39;s required pre-service classes. Given the number
of teachers we prepare at Hunter, that could really move the needle.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Working with elementary school teachers is new to me and I&amp;#39;m having
fun with all of this. Super appreciative to have partners like the
Robin Hood Foundation, Aman, Sara, and Phil as well as the teachers
who took time out of their summers to come down to Hunter and work on
this with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts On Code And Beyond - Computational Thinking</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 17:48:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/thoughts-on-code-and-beyond-ct/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The theme of this year&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/i/moments/1084877641285541889&#34;&gt;To Code and Beyond&lt;/a&gt; was Computational
Thinking. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial&#34;&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; gave the keynote. While the talk isn&amp;#39;t
currently online, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N3uCb-95fFE&amp;amp;t=5s&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt; that Mark gave last March. It&amp;#39;s
not the same but the second halves are and well worth a look.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the first half, Mark talked about other types of &amp;#34;thinking.&amp;#34;
Scientific thinking, engineering thinking and even historical
thinking. All had a good amount of overlap with both each other and
with computational thinking even as we haven&amp;#39;t yet settled on what
computational thinking actually is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This overlap is why I think that bringing CS into the primary grades
gives us an opportunity to reduce the achievement gap between rich and
poor. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve already said that I&amp;#39;m not sold on hardcore CS and programming in
the early grades but rather it&amp;#39;s CT - the problem solving and
methodologies of CS that can effectively be part of the earlier
grades.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, that&amp;#39;s easier said than done. While there has been some
pushback recently we still have far too much emphasis on standardized
tests and elementary school teachers are way overworked. Trying to get
already overburdened teachers to add in a whole new subject area is a
big ask. The opportunity is that we might be able to develop aspects
of CT in a way that supports what elementary teachers are already
doing, possibly under the unlabeled guise of scientific thinking,
historical thinking, engineering thinking or some other thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is already going on to a certain extent with individual teachers
at individual schools. Logic games and problem solving techniques have
always been explored by elementary school teachers who have freedom
from tightly packed test based curricula. These could be considered CT
and you could also add data collection and processing and I&amp;#39;m sure
many other things as well. This is where CS/CT can fit in the
elementary schools without adding to the teacher&amp;#39;s current
load. What&amp;#39;s more, if we can figure out how to incorporate these CT
concepts to support the subject matter already being studied we could
help close the gap between the haves and the have nots.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve said many times before that I&amp;#39;m not an elementary school
specialist but I still suspect this is the approach for CS in the
primary grades at least for the near term. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve already got a pretty full plate between my work with Hunters
Daedalus CS honors program along with our pre-service programs being
very close to going live but I&amp;#39;m also hoping to do some work in
relating to this in the near future.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is There a First Grade Machine Learning Achievement Gap?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-there-a-first-grade-ml-achievement-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 15:24:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-there-a-first-grade-ml-achievement-gap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today was the fifth &amp;#34;To Code and Beyond&amp;#34; - a one day conference
hosted at Cornell Technion and once again Diane Levitt put together
a great show. The theme was Computational Thinking and the day
consisted of a variety of talks, panels, and activities. I plan on
writing about one panel in particular but for today I wanted to
address something that came up as a question. One attendee asked a
panel about the achievement gap - the fact that when the CS movement got
started in NY some of the more innovative and interesting work was
being done with some of our most vulnerable students. Recently, he
heard about a student who was doing Machine Learning in early
elementary school - first grade. The concern
he had was that when we started the less affluent populations might
have even been pulling ahead but now he&amp;#39;s concerned that the gap
between have and have nots will continue to grow even in this new
field.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not so concerned about the ML gap in the early grades and I
still think that we still have an opportunity to lessen the gap
between the haves and have nots with CS and more specifically CT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded about when I started fencing. I first picked up a foil
in 11th grade. Stuy had a senior heavy team that year. I was the only
new junior and there were a bunch of new sophomores. The following
year, we were the starting lineup. We were raw but we still managed
second place in the city. Most of us continued on to fence in USFA
events and then in college. I remember one of the first events we went
to. It was the under 20 qualifiers for the Junior Olympics National
Championships. There were a couple of superstars who recently came
over from eastern bloc countries there. Also a bunch of
fencers we didn&amp;#39;t know but we knew that they&amp;#39;d been fencing for
years - since they were 8, 9, 10. &amp;#34;They&amp;#39;ve been fencing for
years. We&amp;#39;ve only been doing it for one. How can we ever compete?&amp;#34;
I remember Jordan saying &amp;#34;Yeah, they&amp;#39;ve fenced for years but probably
a day or two a week, we&amp;#39;ve been doing it intensely every day for a
year and a half.&amp;#34; He also noted that when they were in their early
years their bodies probably weren&amp;#39;t coordinated enough to really
develop so much. He was right. The superstars dominated but then we
were very much in the mix and in fact took most of the qualifying
spots. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also thought about teaching CS at Stuy. There were always kid who
came in to class with prior experience. That was clear on day one and
for the first few weeks. By the end of the first semester you woudn&amp;#39;t
know it based on overall class performance. The newcomers caught up
pretty quickly. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is why I&amp;#39; not really concerned when I hear about a school doing
Machine Learning in first grade. How much can they really do and how
deep is it? Is the kid even really ready for it or are they just going
through the motions? Or, are they just doing something they&amp;#39;ve always
done in first grade and are just labelling it ML.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that last option is fairly likely. It&amp;#39;s also why I think we
still have an opportunity to close the achievement gap as part of the
CS / CT movement. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When people ask me about CS in the early grades I first tell them that
I&amp;#39;m not an early grade specialist. I follow this by stating that I
think that well resourced schools have been doing thing that we now
consider CT for years - logic, problem solving, puzzles, etc.When a
group of students solve a problem and describe a solution that
includes repetition it used to be just problem solving. Now it&amp;#39;s
computation thinking. Sure, we can tease it out, formalize it and
expand on it but the schools and teachers with the resources and
freedom have already been doing this. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the CS For All movement, we have an opportunity to bring this to
all our students not just the well to do ones.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course this is easier said than done. We have to prepare them to
identify these CT practices and actively develop these skills in their
students. This means giving teachers the time, resources, and training
and not shorten the already tight tether to standardized multiple
choice tests. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At times I&amp;#39;ve been disappointed with the overall K12 CS Ed
movement. We&amp;#39;ve made great strides coming from nowhere to where we are
but as a community we missed the opportunity to bypass the mistakes
and bad ideas that teachers of other disciplines are plagued with. 
We still have this chance with Computational Thinking and the early
grades.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I hope we do it right.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>