<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>languages on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/languages/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (languages)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 17:33:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/languages/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Different languages, different techniques, different solutions</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/different-languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 17:33:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/different-languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent this weekend diving back into Clojure or more specifically,
Clojurescript. For those who don&amp;#39;t know, Clojure is a Lisp that runs
on the JVM. The solution it particularly seeks to &amp;#34;solve&amp;#34; is
immutability. Clojurescript is Clojure that compiles to Javascript for
web applications. Tooling aside, it&amp;#39;s all pretty neat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t do anything earth shaking, just a quick implementation of
Conway&amp;#39;s game of life and Snake. While the code isn&amp;#39;t particularly
good, you can check them out here (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-snake&#34;&gt;Snake&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life&#34;&gt;Life&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Life implementation got me thinking about the value of studying
different languages or more specifically, different paradigms. A
student who implements the game of life in Java will likely implement
something very similar in C++ as both languages are Object Oriented /
imperative. An implementation in Clojure or Haskell will likely look
very different.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look a little deeper.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%2527s_Game_of_Life&#34;&gt;Conway&amp;#39;s Game of LIfe&lt;/a&gt; is a Cellular Automaton and when teaching a CS
class in Java or C++ it&amp;#39;s a really nice application of 2D arrays. On
each turn, for each cell in the world, you calculate its living
neighbors. If the cell is alive and it has 2 or 3 living neighbors, it
stays alive to the next turn. If the cell isn&amp;#39;t alive but has 3 living
neighbors it will become alive. Otherwise the cell dies (or remains
dead).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a Java type language, given a 2D array &lt;code&gt;this_turn&lt;/code&gt; with the current
world and you might get something like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a really nice application of 2D arrays and I&amp;#39;ve done it with my
classes frequently over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another language I&amp;#39;ve done &lt;strong&gt;life&lt;/strong&gt; in is NetLogo. In NetLogo, you have
a world represented by an x,y grid with each cell in the grid known as
a patch. You write a program and all the patches run it
independently. A life solution might look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-text&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-netlogo&#34; data-lang=&#34;netlogo&#34;&gt;ask patches [ 
  set n count nieghbors with [color =  red] ;; red cells will be alive
  ifelse color = red 
    [ ifelse n=2 or n = 3
        [set nextcolor red]
        [set nextcolor black]
    ] 
    [
      ifelse n=3
        [ set nextcolor red ]
        [ set nextcolor black ]  
    ]
ask patches [set color nextcolor]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My NetLogo is a little rusty so my syntax might be off but the idea is
to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
have each patch count it&amp;#39;s living neighbors and figure out it&amp;#39;s
next state - alive (red) or dead (black)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
have each patch set its color to the new state
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a very different solution. In NetLogo you never think about
looping over the cells. It&amp;#39;s much higher level. You think about each
location as it&amp;#39;s own entity whereas in the Java solution you&amp;#39;re
getting much more into the nitty gritty. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NetLogo and Java are very different languages and using them
encourages you to solve problems in different ways. you&amp;#39;d likely
never create a 2D array in NetLogo - you&amp;#39;d exploit the word as your
array. Likewise you&amp;#39;d exploit the patches to distribute the work. In
Java you&amp;#39;d probably wouldn&amp;#39;t create a class to represent each patch in
the array and then run each in a thread. That would be overkill for
the problem at hand.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, what about Clojure?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Clojure isn&amp;#39;t set up for 2D arrays, at least not as cleanly as a
language like C++ or Java. One could use Java Interop - that is, the
ability of Clojure to directly use Java but that would defeat the
purpose of using Clojure. Clojure is all about lists, vectors, and
maps. Instead of a 2D array of the world, I made a list (vector) where
each element contained the location of a living cell. This is
certainly more space efficient. It also let me operate on the world as
a sequence of transformations to the data:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Calculate all the possible next cells (the cells in the list plus
all their neighbors
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For each possible next cell, count it&amp;#39;s living neighbors and
determine if the cell is alive in the next iteration
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Replace the list of cells with these new cells. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;generate [state]
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Generate and return the next state&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[potential-cells (for [[x y] state [dx dy] cell-bloc-3x3]
                          [(+ x dx) (+ y dy)])
        next-state (for [cell potential-cells]
                     (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;alive?&lt;/span&gt; cell state) cell))]
    (into &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;{} (remove nil?(into &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;{} next-state)))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can see the complete code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life/blob/master/src/life.cljs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This again is a very different way of thinking about the problem. In
Java we looped over the world and made adjustments. Here we
transformed the current set of cells into the next generations set of
cells in a pipeline like fashion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another feature of Clojure that results from its focus on immutability
is that in programs like these the computational part of the program
and the presentation part (the graphics) are totally separate. We
first transform the data and then the UI displays the current
data. Clojure does this very nicely and maybe I&amp;#39;ll write a post on
it but for now, I just want to point out that this is very different
from NetLogo. In fact, I completely finished the program for life
before I even thought about the interface. In NetLogo the interface is
an integral part of the language.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The point of all of this is that languages designed around different
paradigms are worth exploring even if you never do real work in
them. Even if you don&amp;#39;t like or use Clojure you can take lessons from
it&amp;#39;s functional side and how it handles immutability and you can add
those techniques to your toolkit when using C++ or Java. It doesn&amp;#39;t
mean you should write Java to look like Clojure but having a complete
toolkit of paradigms to draw from and apply when appropriate can only
be good for us and for our students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selecting a starting language - why not Javascript</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was catching up with the team at Stuy the other day and they
mentioned that they were periodically getting pushback on their choice
of languages, particularly in the intro class. The pushback was mostly
in the form of &amp;#34;why don&amp;#39;t you start them with Javascript?&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in the day, when I created our intro class where we use Scheme,
NetLogo and then later Python, I&amp;#39;d get similar pushback but then it
was &amp;#34;why not Java?&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;why not C?&amp;#34;, or &amp;#34;whu not C++?&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had a good discussion on this and I shared my thoughts as to why I
don&amp;#39;t like Javascript as a first language and I thought I&amp;#39;d share some
of them here. I&amp;#39;ll try to get around to the rationale behind Scheme
and NetLogo in a later post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, let me say that I &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Javascript -
particularly when approaching it as a functional language. I also
think every school and situation is different so there are likely
times when Javascript is the right beginner language for the job.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s dive in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why are some of the pluses for Javascript as an intro language.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ubiquity and availability:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you have a browser, you have Javascript - it&amp;#39;s also available
through online IDEs and online lightweight sites like &lt;a href=&#34;https://jsfiddle.net/&#34;&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Interactivity:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can tweak websites almost live, use the HTML5 canvas pretty
interactively and mode
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s mainstream
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s quick to get up and running
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is all true, but there are also downsides.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my big problems with Javascript is the lack of simple solid
educational tooling. I love to use tools like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drjava.org/&#34;&gt;DrJava&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://drpython.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;DrPython&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://racket-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt; (formerly DrScheme) with beginners. All simple learning
IDEs. True, you can use a simple online IDE but I haven&amp;#39;t found them
to have as strong a learning interface. They also, generally, keep you
in an oversimplified programming sandbox. There&amp;#39;s no clean transition
from the sandbox to the real deal - particularly given the non-trivial
state of js build tools and environments. These simple learning IDEs
set the stage and then we can transition to more powerful development environments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also prefer, where possible, to have kids learn locally so that they
can learn something about the underlying operating system even if
only at a user level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A problem relating to the lack of tooling is the fact that a JS
program can fail to run and not give you any meaningful feedback at
all - this is a problem for a beginner.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Javascript also has all sorts of wonkiness. We have &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;
which is pretty conventional, but then there&amp;#39;s also &lt;code&gt;===&lt;/code&gt;. We have
potentially confusing scoping issues and also some other real
weirdness:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-js&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34; data-lang=&#34;js&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For more, check out the this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;. Start watching at about 1:20 -
it&amp;#39;s a riot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this weirdness actually makes sense - just not to a beginner.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Javascript also gives plenty of freedom - there are many ways to do
things. This can be great for the developer but not necessarily ideal
for the learner. Loops, recursion, mapping functions - you name it,
Javascript&amp;#39;s got it. I like simpler languages for beginners because
it&amp;#39;s easier to get them thinking and problem solving in certain ways
when there tool set is somewhat restricted (more on that when I write
about Scheme).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the fact that Javascript&amp;#39;s a mainstream language can be a
minus. Given its popularity, a beginner class could have at  least a
few kid who&amp;#39;ve at least played with the language. This can lead them
to think they know more than they do and more importantly, this can
be intimidating to the real newbies who develop the impression that
&amp;#34;everyone knows this but me.&amp;#34; A less mainstream language puts everyone
on a level playing field.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let me say again that I love javascript as a language and before a
student graduates Stuy they can learn all about Javascript, front end
development, some functional programming, and more. It&amp;#39;s just not the
right language to start with - at least not at Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>