<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>community on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/community/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (community)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 15:43:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/community/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Class Legends</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 15:43:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s talk about something other than distance learning and COVID-19.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You know you&amp;#39;ve been doing something a long time when you&amp;#39;ve got
legends.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over on my alumni mailing list JonAlf shared a web site showing off
what his current students were doing in their computer graphics
class. Somewhere in the thread, Con replied:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;
Someone should put up a video of the fabulous and fantastically famous
hand animation called FINGER.MDL. It dates from a little before my
time, but stories elevated it to legendary status.
&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Indeed it had reached legendary status. Other projects over the years
including Larry&amp;#39;s anatomically correct robot had also risen to
infamy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A little later in the thread the project&amp;#39;s author Josh chimed in and
shared his original source code. He still had it from May 1995. I&amp;#39;m
not entirely surprised - I had a copy of the code as well. The trouble
is it was written in Turbo-C on a DOS machine. Good luck compiling it
on a modern system. Fortunately, Josh was able to build and run the
project using an emulator. Check out the  marginally NSFW video at the
end of the post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the legend? Well, in addition to being a pretty terrific
project - particularly when you remember the horsepower it was running
on and that it was written by a student who was concurrently finishing
APCS, there&amp;#39;s a story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It starts in one of my APCS classes. Students were working on final
projects. Tom was working on Tetris - an impressive project for APCS
done in Turbo Pascal. Tom wanted to add music to the project and had a
clever way of doing it. Back then you could get basic sounds by
turning on and off the speaker at certain frequencies. Tom had two
arrays, one with frequencies and one with durations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Something like: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;notes&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;440&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;523&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;440&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;659&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;]
durations&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then for the game loop
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#+begin_src python&lt;/span&gt;

  current_note&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
  note &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; notes[current_note]
  duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; durations[current_note]
  play(note) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# starts the note playing until you change or stop it&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; game_not_over:
      duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:
          current_note &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (current_note&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;length(notes)
          note &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; notes[current_note]
          duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; durations[current_note]
          play(note) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# starts the note playing until you change or stop it&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# the rest of the game loop&lt;/span&gt;
  stop_playing() &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# stop the speaker&lt;/span&gt;

    

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#+end_src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, he had to figure out all the frequencies and durations for
&amp;#34;Korobeiniki,&amp;#34; the tetris song. The class was more than happy to help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everyone&amp;#39;s working to help figure this out for Tom. It&amp;#39;s all pretty
cool when in walks Jinx Perullo - Stuy&amp;#39;s new principal along with the
President of the New York City Board of Education. The President&amp;#39;s jaw
drops as she hears a cacophony of Tetris music and screen after screen
of Tetris being played!!!!! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jinx makes an abrupt about face and drags the dignitary out of the
room. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward a week or so. We&amp;#39;re in the graphics class at the end of
the day - it was held during an non-existent after school period so
that the students could attend. Josh&amp;#39;s working on his graphics program
at a computer by the door.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jinx walked in again. This time with the school&amp;#39;s chancelor to be
greeted by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ca_8q3ct6J4&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ca_8q3ct6J4&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again, a quick about face.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For some reason Jinx never brought important people to my classes
again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those were indeed the good old days.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Focus To Feel Normal</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:46:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Austin Cory Bart tweeted this a little while ago.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I don&amp;#39;t
always consider how much power I have as a faculty. Right now, I&amp;#39;d
really like to expend that power to make my students understand that I
don&amp;#39;t want them focused on my course during a global pandemic. Not
right now. Later, but not right now.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart
(@AustinCorgiBart) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AustinCorgiBart/status/1238565390575456262?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March
13, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While Cory&amp;#39;s right about this it&amp;#39;s also good to remember that as
we&amp;#39;re all going remote, focusing on our courses can be important for
our students not merely due to content but in this time of uncertainty
to have something to focus on to remind us of community and remind us
of normal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While all our students are now home or being sent home they&amp;#39;re going
to be in semi isolation. Most will be with families but many will be
isolated from friends and classmates and without our courses, in a
limbo state left to obsess and stress over the current state of
affairs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Focusing on our class  - through synchronous onlinen classes and
mailing lists, working on assignments, and otherwise engaging in this
approximation of our students regular weeks we&amp;#39;re providing a valuable
distraction in addition to whatever actual course material we can
cover.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve seen it before. After 9/11 and to a lesser extent after
Sandy. After 9/11 we were closed for about a a week. Based on the
email list I was able to put together and the back and forths I had
between parents and students stress was high, information and outlets
low. We managed to set up one event that got a bunch of students
together and it was really needed. We restarted classes at Brooklyn
Tech and stayed for close to a month. Classes were half length
starting in the afteroon. I was teaching CS without any real computer
access, some classes shared rooms and in general it&amp;#39;s debatable how
much learning happened. What it did do though, is it gave the kids
something to focus on other than the 9/11 attacks and their
aftermath. It wasn&amp;#39;t normal but it was &amp;#34;normaler.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the years that followed, I&amp;#39;d hear from both parents and students -
a number of whom I never taught about how important it was giving them
something to do other than obsess about the events of the day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same thing after Sandy. Some students weren&amp;#39;t all that affected but
others suffered tremendous losses. We set up virtual classes for a
couple of days while school wasn&amp;#39;t in session. Again, it gave them
something to focus on that wasn&amp;#39;t the superstorm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same thing this time around. We all should be aware and alert to
everything happening but we also need community and things to focus
on. Our classes can be one of those things.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remote Classes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/remote-classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 09:34:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/remote-classes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Over at &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com&#34;&gt;AVC&lt;/a&gt; Fred Wilson just posted about &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2020/03/outschool-can-help-your-school-prepare-for-unexpected-closures/&#34;&gt;Outschool&amp;#39;s efforts&lt;/a&gt;
to support students and teachers in the event of school closures due
to the Coronavirus. All the details and relevant links are in the
post. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I looked a bit into Outschool when Fred first &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2019/05/outschooling/&#34;&gt;wrote about them&lt;/a&gt; but
never had a chance to do a deep dive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, internet based teaching is not going to be as effective as in
person teaching but I was thinking about how far things have come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After superstorm Sandy, Stuy was closed for about a week. Instead of
losing all the time my classes and I decided to try to do us some
internet schooling. We used Google tools and things went pretty well. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wrote about what we did and some concluding thoughts &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-10-31-sandy-bridge.html/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back then - 2012 - the technology was close but not quite there. Now,
with tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us&#34;&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;#39;m guessing &lt;a href=&#34;https://outschool.com/&#34;&gt;Outschool&lt;/a&gt;, which is probably
more fine tuned for education rather than meetings you have some nice
all in one or at least most in one solutions. I had to use a YouTube
broadcast and separate documents and chats. Today&amp;#39;s tools tie all of
those together along with screen sharing. Maybe Outschool even has a
shared virtual blackboard - that would be pretty cool. Add in
something like Trello and GitHub and we&amp;#39;re really cooking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It really reminds me that &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apache_Wave&#34;&gt;Google Wave&lt;/a&gt; was really a product ahead of
it&amp;#39;s time. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said above, internet teaching will not be as effective as
live. It&amp;#39;s more of a show and do rather than an interactive class and
I go through some of the other issues in the my two posts linked above
but we&amp;#39;re getting better. Certainly way better than closing a school
and doing nothing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hats off to Outschool for providing their services to the community. I
hope few have to use them but am thankful they&amp;#39;re there.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSEvents.nyc</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 18:52:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A couple of weeks ago, a handful of CS Ed folks got together. One
issue we discussed was that of finding CS related events both for
students and teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of our conveners, Dan Fenjves of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.upperlinecode.com/&#34;&gt;UPPERLINE CODE&lt;/a&gt; talked about
possibly hosting a central site. Today, Dan announced
&lt;a href=&#34;http://csevents.nyc/.&#34;&gt;http://csevents.nyc/.&lt;/a&gt; A site where organizers can submit and students
and teachers can find upcoming events. Right now it&amp;#39;s NY centric but
it does list some events beyond the city.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re planning an event or CS Educational opportunity, submit it,
if you&amp;#39;re looking for one, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CS Education Subreddit</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 07:37:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amyjko?ref_src=twsrc%255Etfw%257Ctwcamp%255Etweetembed%257Ctwterm%255E1230982366706860032&amp;amp;ref_url=https%253A%252F%252Fpublish.twitter.com%252F%253Fquery%253Dhttps%25253A%25252F%25252Ftwitter.com%25252Famyjko%25252Fstatus%25252F1230982366706860032%2526widget%253DTweet&#34;&gt;Amy Ko&lt;/a&gt; posted this yesterday:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;CSEd people:
many have struggled to use Twitter for discussion. How about Twitter
for broadcasting, but when replies turn to discussion, we use &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/2oivuriOoU&#34;&gt;https://t.co/2oivuriOoU&lt;/a&gt;? It&amp;#39;s a
better (albeit imperfect) platform for civil discourse. Subreddit mods
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AustinCorgiBart?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@AustinCorgiBart&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Amy J. Ko (@amyjko) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amyjko/status/1230982366706860032?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February
21, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d love to see more traffic &lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/CSEducation&#34;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;. For full disclosure, I&amp;#39;m one of
the moderators but in my defense, I&amp;#39;m not much of a moderator and as
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AustinCorgiBart/status/1230992957467168768&#34;&gt;Cory&lt;/a&gt; said, I too am happy to either keep moderating or to step aside.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Twitter is nice for broadcasting but not great for
meaty discussions. The character limit does make you think out what
you&amp;#39;re saying but it&amp;#39;s also a headache and tweet storms are an
inelegant solution at best. Once you start mixing in replies threads
become hard to follow. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An interesting case study of Twitter conversation is over at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/home&#34;&gt;Fred
Wilson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s blog  &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com&#34;&gt;AVC&lt;/a&gt;. Fred recently rebooted his long standing blog and
is now using Twitter for comments whereas he previously used &lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;.
I haven&amp;#39;t done an in depth analysis but there appears to be far fewer
comments and less in depth conversation than in his blogs past
incarnations. This could just be my perceptions but given the large
readership, it might be an interesting thing to analyze.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to other communication tools, I&amp;#39;ve written about them with respect
to classroom communications &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/class-communications/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Many of the same issues
exist for using these tools as a professional community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Facebook groups are private, undiscoverable, hard to search, and
scattered. They also exist in the Facebook silo. Data goes in but it
never comes out. I also can&amp;#39;t access those Facebook groups using
anything other than Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Email is a great default. Nowhere else to go - things just show up in
your inbox. I&amp;#39;m on the APCS mailing list as well as SIGCSE. One
problem is the no quoting policy which makes threads hard to follow
and discoverability and long term searchability are a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Slack? Just no.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So let&amp;#39;s think about reddit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can go to the site to read it but you can also subscribe using an
RSS/Atom reader like Feedly. If you post a comment you get replies via
email and an alert in reddit. It&amp;#39;s discoverable, public, and
searchable. It even appears to support chats and a wiki.  Hits all the
buttons for me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We could do a better job with the subreddit - add resource links to
the sidebar for instance - I just started to do that now. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cscheerleader/status/1231177418708267008&#34;&gt;Ria&lt;/a&gt; commented on how she wasn&amp;#39;t happy that people could post
anonymously. I tend to agree with her - I&amp;#39;ve always used my real
identity in forums and would prefer others do the same but that&amp;#39;s not
a dealbreaker to me. I&amp;#39;d rather an open community with anonymous
posting allowed than Zuck&amp;#39;s world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another issue that is sure to be raised is openness. Some teachers
don&amp;#39;t want their discussions public where students can find
them. Sometimes this is to separate class from life and sometimes
because class related issues are being discussed. I&amp;#39;ve never had an
issue with this. Having spent close to 30 years in the classroom I&amp;#39;ve
always been pretty open and public. Sure, sometimes a student can find
an old assignment or blog post going over something but so what, maybe
they&amp;#39;ll learn something. The only time I see this as really being an
issue is that you don&amp;#39;t want to talk about specific student issues in
a public forum to protect the students privacy. It&amp;#39;s harder to ask
your colleagues for help with some specific student related problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, much of what I&amp;#39;m guessing Amy was talking about was the CS
Educator type discourse that doesn&amp;#39;t get into those weeds but I see
these communities as for all educators (which I&amp;#39;m sure Amy does as
well, just separating my read on her specific tweet).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, please do join us over in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/CSEducation/&#34;&gt;CSEducation&lt;/a&gt; over on Reddit. If you want
to subscribe via an rss or atom reader just use this link:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/CSEducation.rss&#34;&gt;https://reddit.com/r/CSEducation.rss&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presenting At CSTA 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 13:05:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Presenting at CSTA 2020
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I noticed a few tweets and posts from people announcing that they&amp;#39;d be
presenting at CSTA2020 - the big computer science teachers conference
held every July.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A common thread in a few of these were trepidation&amp;#39;s
presenters. Excited to be doing this but nervous.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s interesting that teachers, myself included, sometimes get nervous
before presentations even though we present every day as part of our
jobs. I know it&amp;#39;s different as we have the same kids every day but
even day 1 jitters each semester aren&amp;#39;t the same as the presentation
anxiety that some of us face.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m certainly not a super master seasoned presenter. I&amp;#39;ve done it a
few times at CSTA and other venues and this year JonAlf and I will be
running a GitHub workshop but I thought I&amp;#39;d share some words of
encouragement anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
You&amp;#39;re really just talking shop.
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Basically, you&amp;#39;re a teacher talking about teaching and I think we all
love to do that. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
It&amp;#39;s an audience of friends
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CSTA is a conference primarily of teachers - our colleague.s Everyone
coming to your session is already interested in your opinion and going
in as a supportive audience. They &lt;strong&gt;want&lt;/strong&gt; to hear from you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll go back to the previous point - you&amp;#39;re basically talking shop
with friends. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
CSTA still feels intimate
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of its rapid growth, the CSTA conference still feels
intimate. It&amp;#39;s not a huge conference where you can attend a talk or
meet someone at breakfast and never find them again. It&amp;#39;s big enough
so that you &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; avoid anyone you want to dodge but you can pretty
much find time to spend with anyone you want to as well. This can turn
your talk more into a starting point for a longer convesation - how
cool is that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t forget to enjoy it
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I used  to get really nervous when giving LARGE talks - we&amp;#39;re talking
to an audience of one or two thousand. I&amp;#39;ve only done that a few
times. A couple of times at the New York Tech Meetup and once when I
was the faculty graduation speaker at Stuy when my best friend was the
guest speaker and my daughter was in the graduating class. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was pretty nervous before I hit the stage at Stuy when a colleague
gave me some great advice - &amp;#34;take the time to enjoy the moment.&amp;#34; I
remembered that just as I said above - I was about to talk to
friends. Two thousand of them, but friends nonetheless. I was reminded
to slow down and take it in. Enjoy the moment. I&amp;#39;ve tried to do that
with any presentation I&amp;#39;ve given since. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Final thoughts
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As  a final thought I&amp;#39;ll leave you by paraphrasing something that I
think was said by Pinchas Zuckerman - the world class violist and
violinist (who I think also used to wear a shirt proclaiming &amp;#34;I
vibrato when I play baroque - Deal with it!!!!!).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He said that you should always be smiling when you&amp;#39;re
performing. Either your performance is going well and you&amp;#39;re creating
beautiful music or it&amp;#39;s going horribly but it will be over soon. :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already looking forward to July.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the side benefits of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/&#34;&gt;visiting high schools&lt;/a&gt; is that I end up
going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I
normally wouldn&amp;#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk
that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at
the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of
weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
James Madison
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goddard High School
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
FDR HS
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Midwood HS
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goddard was interesting because it was founded in 2008 and grew out of
the middle school in the same building. FDR was also interesting. It
was founded in 1965 which makes the building fairly young or at least
early middle aged for a New York City school building. When you
approach it, you see this small short modern looking one story structure:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://proxy.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=http%3A%2F%2Fassets.nydailynews.com%2Fpolopoly_fs%2F1.1408243.1374717210!%2Fimg%2FhttpImage%2Fimage.jpg_gen%2Fderivatives%2Flandscape_635%2Fteacher25n-1-web.jpg&amp;amp;f=1&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hidden from view is the big rectangular tower that the entrance
connects to via a tunnel. I had an interesting conversation with the
school&amp;#39;s principal about how that came to be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
James Madison and Midwood also have their own buildings and they are
both partially screened - that is, they have selective admissions for
at least a portion of their student population. FDR is particularly
interesting becuase it is frankly an &amp;#34;old school&amp;#34; neighborhood
school that survived the destructive years of Bloomberg/Klein.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other schools I visited in that span were all housed in schools
that had been closed during the Bloomberg/Klein years and new small
schools created in their place. The original buildings were:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thomas Jefferson
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Franklin K Lane
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Christopher Columbus
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Andrew Jackson
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the coolest parts about visiting the older buildings is that
they were built in a different time. You have elaborate lobbies of
marble and polished granite. Beautiful murals and ornate
auditoriums. Unique architectural features like the ramps on the first
floor in Thomas Jefferson or the foyer in Brooklyn Tech (a school I
visited earlier in the year).  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also have school history. In many of the buildings the walls are
still adorned with names of notable alumni.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Christopher Columbus boasts Sal Mineo,  (Anne Bancroft), and, well,
David Berkowitz. Andrew Jackson does pretty well for basketball with
Bob Cousy, Lly Daniels, Boo Harvey, and recent Knick Kyle
O&amp;#39;Quinn. Woody Allen and Mimi Sheraton among others went to
Midwood. James Madison has a political bent with Bernie Sander, Ruth
Bader Ginsburg, and Chuck Schumer. Finally, Thomas Jefferson was home
to Sylvia Fine, David Daniel Kaminsky (that&amp;#39;s Danny Kaye to you), Paul
Mazrusky, Al Lewis, and others. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another tidbit I learned was about the history of Franklin K
Lane. Lane&amp;#39;s built in the Brooklyn Queens border. You can see the
hills of Forrest Park left from the last Ice Age rising up behind it
as you approach the building. Apparently there used to be a line of
paint denoting the border. Lane also saw a good deal of race related
turmoil throughout it&amp;#39;s history. I was talking to an alum during my
visit and he was telling me how that in his day, you either left the
building via the north entrance or the south one depending on your
crew and woe is he who got caught on the wrong side. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, many of the older buildings were part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_Progress_Administration&#34;&gt;WPA&lt;/a&gt; from the New
Deal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you do get a chance to go into an old school, take some time to
check out the architecture and the ghosts of the past.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll leave you with a couple of pictures from Brooklyn Tech - mostly
because they were easy to find.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.khomarch.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/kevin-hom-architect-university-college-architect-brooklyn-tech-1.jpg&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/59aec48e9f7456bae98b8609/5ad7b923575d1f7d69412830/5ad7b93d88251b1250984d58/1524087471280/mural-image-bths-2.JPG&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bthsalumni.org/view.image?Id=812&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;#ZgotmplZ&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Thanksgiving weekend is also reunion weekend. I&amp;#39;ve been on and off
invited to Stuy reunions over the years. Not as often it seems as some
teachers but more often than others. I always do my best to attend. I
have very fond memories of many students and many classes over many
years and think a lot about them so feel very honored whenever I&amp;#39;m
invited to one of these.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the past each class due a reunion did its own thing - some club or
bar usually in Manhattan. This year, things were a little
different. Stuy held some &amp;#34;all class&amp;#34; reunion activities at the school
during the day and then multiple reunions were held at the school
during the evening. They hosted three classes - 2008, 2004, and 1998
in different parts of the school. The class of 2013 also had a reunion
off site - that&amp;#39;s my daughter Batya&amp;#39;s graduating class so she got to
catch up with her class wherever they held their shindig. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think the format worked well. Two classes were in the cafeteria
separated by a curtain and the third in one of the gyms. There was
self serve beer, wine, and water along with assorted snacks and finger
foods. Each area also had a DJ playing music though not too
loudly. Everyone knew the location, costs were kept low and for the
most part it wasn&amp;#39;t so loud that you couldn&amp;#39;t talk to each other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual it was great to see some former students that I hadn&amp;#39;t seen
in years and also chatting with non-cs students that I really didn&amp;#39;t
know but there were a few highlights.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spend a good amount of time with some of my 1998 crew. As I told
them, I really honestly missed them. We had some really good
times. Some of them had moved out of the city but talking to the NY
contingent we all left feeling that we should do a better job of
seeing each other in person.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also enjoyed my time with the other groups but I&amp;#39;ve manged to see
more of them more recently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a couple of weeks, I&amp;#39;m actually going to have a reunion of my own
alumni community. I&amp;#39;ve put together a loose association of my former
students and other Stuy students involved in tech. We&amp;#39;re having a
meetup in early December and right now it looks like around 100 people
are going to attend. I love those meetups because they bring together
people across the generations. The downside for me is that it&amp;#39;s
like a big family event. As the host I never get to really catch up
with anyone since I&amp;#39;m running from person to person.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One final nice takeaway from the evening. After I exited Stuy I
started to gear up in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cleverhood.com/&#34;&gt;Cleverhood&lt;/a&gt; for the rainy ride home and
started chatting with a group of &amp;#39;98 grads one of whom was my
student. He said to the group &amp;#34;you might not remember this guy and
probably have no idea what he did for all of you.&amp;#34; He went on to
explain how I got Stuy on the internet in 1994/1995 and set up email
accounts for everyone. I remembered that I ran the internet stuff at
Stuy for years but never really thought about the fact that we got
online and got those facilities to the kids that early. Working with
Bruce, a student at the time we &lt;del&gt;stole&lt;/del&gt; requisitioned one of the IBM
RS/6000 machines that were supposed to be used in the cad classes, got
it onto the net, and set up email accounts for everyone. It&amp;#39;s funny
that I just always thought of that as something we did but to some of
the students it was a pretty big deal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goes to show that you never know what makes a mark on your students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a
feeling of community. Students aren&amp;#39;t on campus every day and come
from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&amp;#39;t have
a CS &amp;#34;hang out&amp;#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&amp;#39;re
scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my
honors students. The first two cohorts were a single class in
size. Even though some dormed and some commuted, they were all
together in my class twice a week. This year, we&amp;#39;ve close to doubled
in size and about half of my students came in with a good deal of
prior CS knowledge. The result is that I have two different classes of
honors students and we are never all together unless it&amp;#39;s for a
special event.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, we&amp;#39;ve got one of my favorites coming up. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In two weeks, I&amp;#39;ll be taking about half my students up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;Catskills
Conf&lt;/a&gt;. An event that I describe as light tech conference with a focus
on creativity and diversity meets summer camp. I&amp;#39;ve written about the
event in in each of the past three years (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/%0A&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/%0A&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskills-2017/%0A&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;) and also
about the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/%0A&#34;&gt;knitting for charity&lt;/a&gt; event that Devorah runs during the
conference weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event and if you&amp;#39;re anywhere near the Hudson Valley
region you should &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, it&amp;#39;s a great first conference for the students. It only has
one track so no choices and the talks look really interesting this
year. Some of the ones I&amp;#39;m looking forward to are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Designing for Access first
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Behind the Tech: Emoji
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Leaning into uncertainty
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The full schedule is &lt;a href=&#34;https://catskillsconf.com/schedule/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But also mixed in are activities like blacksmithing
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/blacksmith.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and a live bird of prey show
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/BOP.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also hikes that show off the beauty of Fall in the Hudson
Valley
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature1.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature2.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature3.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rather than having the kids spread out in random hotel rooms we&amp;#39;re all
in a camp style bunkhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/bunkhouse.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The weekend is spent  living together along with technologists and
other creative types from NYC, the Hudson Valley and everywhere else. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my favorite parts is at the end of each evening when we all
hang out by the campfire. Hunter CS students, company founders,
software engineers, designers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/campfire.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event overall and a great event to build community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said before, if you&amp;#39;re in the area, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>