<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Advent of Code on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/advent-of-code/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (Advent of Code)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 17:19:27 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/advent-of-code/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi Stage Assignments - the good and the bad - Advent of Code</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/multi-stage-assignments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 17:19:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/multi-stage-assignments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
In the real world you&amp;#39;re usually not building your own projects from
scratch. Much more frequently you&amp;#39;re working on a team and you and
other players come and go over time. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is in stark contrast to most CS educational experiences where
students typically complete relatively small assignments from
beginning to end. One of my biggest fears way back when as I was about
to graduate college was when I woke up one night in a cold sweath &amp;#34;oh
crap - in a couple of weeks I&amp;#39;m going to have to actually produce good
code. Not just code good enough to get by the grader.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, as a general rule,  having students build a project and then later
extend it or, even better, having them extend another student&amp;#39;s project
can be a very good experience. On the other hand, it can also be a
very bad one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great feeling when you leverage a previous project to create
something new. On the other hand, there can be tremendous frustration
if the original project forms a faulty foundation and you have to go
back and rebuild and even then you&amp;#39;re never 100% sure that you&amp;#39;re
building on a solid base.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Building on a previous project has been big in this years &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of
Code&lt;/a&gt;. It started with &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/2&#34;&gt;day 2&lt;/a&gt; when we were asked to write a simple
computer that ran &amp;#34;intcode programs.&amp;#34; Not a bad little challenge. It
then returned in &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/5&#34;&gt;day 5&lt;/a&gt; where we had to add a number of features to our
intcode machines. This too was a nice assignment. It had to be built
on a correct and complete day 2 solution but as far as I could tell,
regardless of how you completed day 2 there was a straightforward way
to extend it to integrate the requirements for day 5.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Things got interesting in &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/7&#34;&gt;day 7&lt;/a&gt; and this is where a teacher, or
competition designer for that matter has to start being careful. Day 5
had us modify and build on day 2 but day 7 had us &lt;strong&gt;use&lt;/strong&gt; what we
created in days 2 and 5. From a teacher who&amp;#39;s building assignments
point of view, this changes the equation. Day 2 and 5 had you build
something that took some input and produced some output. Now, in day 7
you had to do something on top of your intcode machine, feed it into
it (or them as it turned out) and get an output. Depending on the
assumptions you made in building your intcode machine you would either
have an easy time with day 7 or you&amp;#39;d have to go back and redo day 2
and/or 5 - much less fun. As part 2 of day 7 had us running multiple
intcode machines &amp;#34;simultaneously,&amp;#34; my set up didn&amp;#39;t work. I still have
to go back and finish that problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Herein lies a big problem with multi part assignments. Unless you
really lay out the parameters of the early assignment students can,
and frequently will make assumptions you never dreamed of. Those
assumptions can make their lives easier in parts 2 and beyond but it
can also leave them with an impossible task. This on top of any
student that doesn&amp;#39;t finish the early version to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moving on, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/9&#34;&gt;day 9&lt;/a&gt; added some more features to the intcode machine and
since then, days &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt; have all used our intcode
machine. I&amp;#39;ve had issues with my machine for days 11 and 13 and have
to fix my intcode machine&amp;#39;s input/output handling to finish those
challenges but my machine worked well enough to complete days 15, 17,
and 19.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, at the end of the day building on a previous project can be very
cool and for a student very rewarding but it can also be really
challenging. On top of the issue I&amp;#39;ve already talked about this can
also leave students in a very uneasy state when extending a project by
using it rather than building on it. Did they write the early parts
fully correctly or just enough to get by the early test cases? It can
be very unsettling to work on an uncertain foundation. What&amp;#39;s more,
while a teacher can even provide base code, this might only be useful
to help check results as now having a student use provided code adds
yet another challenge (albeit one that provides many useful lesosns).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to doing this in Advent of Code? I doubt &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ericwastl&#34;&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt; and the other
organizers will read this but in case they do, this isn&amp;#39;t a complaint
about Advent of Code. I love the event and we can all quibble about
details we like or don&amp;#39;t like. Advent of Code also isn&amp;#39;t a class with
a grade and if I never finish, let&amp;#39;s say, day 11, there are no
consequences - unlike if a student doesn&amp;#39;t finish part 2 of a graded
project. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing this because I think there are some interesting parallels
between creating an event like Advent of Code and designing projects
and lessons for students and more interestingly , where those //s
diverge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now to get to grading. Hoping to get done to spend at least a few
minutes on &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/20&#34;&gt;day 20&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 8 - addendum - generating inputs</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 17:04:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
As I sad in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/8&#34;&gt;day 8&lt;/a&gt; would be a nice project or lesson in
an APCS-A or college CS1 class. Another nice problem would be to
write a program to generate an image in the format required by the
question. Alternatively, a teacher doing day 8 with their classes
might want to generate a bunch of images for the students to test
their decoders on. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I&amp;#39;d write one to see how appropriate it would be for the
students. I tried to do it without anything fancy or advanced.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, you&amp;#39;ll need a way to generate the block text for the
images. I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.patorjk.com/software/taag/#p=display&amp;amp;f=Banner3&amp;amp;t=Hello&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; site and used the &lt;strong&gt;Banner3&lt;/strong&gt; font. I generated
some text and saved it in a file. The important thing for our purposes
is that any space will count as white and any character as black.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The encoded image is a N * Width * Height sequence of digits  where
each Width * Height sequence of digits represents one layer. See the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/8&#34;&gt;problem text&lt;/a&gt; for details.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can follow along with the code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day08-generator.py&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, here&amp;#39;s how the program works:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The top 51 lines of the program consist of a routine which I&amp;#39;ll
describe later and code to handle command line argument (to set the
number of layers).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, on line 55 I erad  in the file with the source image (from stdin). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In line 57 through 63, I loop over the data and changed each non space
or newline to a star character. I really don&amp;#39;t have to do this but I
wanted to see what the image looked like in just &amp;#34;black and white.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Line 65 through 67 is where I split on the newlines. Now I could take
the length of any line to get the image width and the number of lines
the height.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
70 through 79 creates a long list for the image. At each location, I
generate a list of values. Each list has one entry per layer. The
actual pixel value (1 or 0) is stored at a random location. Everything
before that is a random choice between the real color and transparent
and everything after is just random. Details for that step are in the
&lt;code&gt;genpixel&lt;/code&gt; routine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, in 83 through 89 I loop over each layer and for each layer
the image and and output all the values into a single string. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is then output to stdout while the dimensions go to stderr.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I had a source image in a file named &amp;#34;hello.dat&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;d convert it to
source input for day 8 by typing &lt;code&gt;cat hello.dat | python3 day08-generator.py
-l 10 &amp;gt; day08-input.dat&lt;/code&gt;. This would create a 10 layer input.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s it. Once again, the code is all &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day08-generator.py&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It would make for another
nice student assignment or for a teacher to prepare inputs for the
class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day - 8</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 08:42:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent most of last week up in Albany working on the NY State K12 CS
Standards so fell a bit behind. I had to go back to complete &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/5&#34;&gt;day 5&lt;/a&gt; but
still haven&amp;#39;t finished &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/7&#34;&gt;day 7&lt;/a&gt; which builds on day 5 which in turn
builds on &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/2&#34;&gt;day 2&lt;/a&gt;. I might not get to finishing 7 for a while but it
looks like a good chance to play with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.braveclojure.com/core-async/&#34;&gt;core.async&lt;/a&gt; - Clojure&amp;#39;s
facilities for concurrency. I also want to write up &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/6&#34;&gt;day 6&lt;/a&gt; but today
let&amp;#39;s look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/8&#34;&gt;day 8&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Day 8 is image processing problem so it fits nicely into an APCS-A
type class. You&amp;#39;re given the height and width of the image and you&amp;#39;re
told that the image comes in layers. The input is a long string of
digits. So, if you&amp;#39;re told that the width is 5 and height is 3 you
might get this as your input representing an image with 3 layers:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;100210120100120001102020112100000121002110102&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Adding commas and spaces:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;10021,01201,00120   00110,20201,12100   00012,10021,10102&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first part of the task is to find the layer with the most 0s and
return the number of 1s multiplied with the number of 2s.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is just a nice little data parsing problem. You have to break the
input into &lt;code&gt;width*height&lt;/code&gt; chunks, see which has the most zeros, count
the ones and the twos and return the result. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 is where the image stuff comes in. We&amp;#39;re told that a color
value of 0 is black, 1 is white, and 2 is transparent. We&amp;#39;re also told
that the image&amp;#39;s actual color is the first color it sees (black or
white) when going through the layers. Depending on how you read in
your data, this could be easy or hard. You have to scan down the
layers and keep the first non-transparent color. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1, I read my data into a list of lists where each item was a
layer. I did this in Clojure, but the Python representation of the
sample image above might look something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;[ [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;],
  [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;],
  [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was no reason to subdivide each layer into rows and columns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1, I wanted to have lists where each list was all the values
of each pixel across the layers. This meant &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transpose&#34;&gt;transposing&lt;/a&gt; the matrix -
tat is, if you look at the above list of lists as a matrix, switching
the rows and columns. This was pretty easy to do in Clojure using
&lt;code&gt;(apply mapv vector matrix)&lt;/code&gt; but it shouldn&amp;#39;t be too hard in other
languages.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, we have to keep the first non-transparent color we see in each
list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final fun part is then taking the colors and printing out the
final image.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s what I got:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;XXX  XXXX  XX   XX  X  X 
X  X X    X  X X  X X X  
X  X XXX  X    X  X XX   
XXX  X    X    XXXX X X  
X    X    X  X X  X X X  
X    X     XX  X  X X  X &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s nice about this problem from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view? First,
it&amp;#39;s the puzzle aspect of finding the hidden text. Second, it&amp;#39;s an
image problem which in APCS-A usually means 2D arrays but you can also
solve it without any 2D matrices. My solution involved a bunch of
filtering of data and the matrix transpose. Both interesting concepts
to bring to your classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want to see my Clojure solution, you can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day08.clj&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 4</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 19:32:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/4&#34;&gt;Day 4&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the day was spent working on the NY State CS standards
to I didn&amp;#39;t figure to have much time to work on the
problem. Fortunately, I was able to knock out part 1 before work
started and part 2 was a quick adjustment when I got back to it at the
start of lunch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again, it was a problem with a few interesting teacher side
aspects.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I only wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day04.clj&#34;&gt;Clojure solution&lt;/a&gt; today so that&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;ll use for my
code examples.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The gist was that you were going to use a 6 digit integer as a
password but only  subset of the numbers between a start and end
point. Only numbers in that range for which these two properties held:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were at least one repeated digit, that is 123445 is o since
we have two consecutive 4s but 124354 isn&amp;#39;t
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The digits are increasing. That is, given any digit, the digit to
its right has either the same or a greater value.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You had to find the number of &amp;#34;valid passwords.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first read this sounds like a math problem but it really
isn&amp;#39;t. Looking at the first constraint, if you convert the number to a
string, looking to see that at least two consecutive characters are
the same is pretty easy - it&amp;#39;s just a simple loop. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that it&amp;#39;s even easier using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.regular-expressions.info/&#34;&gt;Regular Expressions&lt;/a&gt;. Regular
expressions (regex) aren&amp;#39;t usually an explicit part of a CS sequence
but man are they useful. Basically they allow you to set up a pattern
that will match text. Some examples:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;pattern&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matches&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;doesn&amp;#39;t match&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aa[0-9]bb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Matches aa a digit than bb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aa3bb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ax3b, aacbb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a+bb[a-z]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;one or more of a then two b then an a-z&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aabbc&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;aabcb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can use parentheses to form a &amp;#34;match group&amp;#34; and then use &amp;#34;\1&amp;#34; to
match the group, so this regular expression:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-regex&#34; data-lang=&#34;regex&#34;&gt;([0-9])\1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
will match two any substring with two of digits, adjacent. Many regex
engines allow you to use &lt;strong&gt;\d&lt;/strong&gt; instead of &lt;strong&gt;[0-9]&lt;/strong&gt; as a shorthand for
match a single digit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the line that will take a list of potential passwords in a
variable &lt;strong&gt;passwords&lt;/strong&gt; and return a list that only containsn the
passwords that meet the two consecutive of the same digit rule.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(filter &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(re-seq &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;(\d)\1&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; %) passwords)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I knew that Python has a &lt;strong&gt;partition&lt;/strong&gt; function that would take a string
with a potential password (I convert the number to a string before
doing the regex test above). It would take a string &amp;#34;1245&amp;#34; and convert
it into something like this &lt;strong&gt;(1,2), (2,3), (3,4), (4,5)&lt;/strong&gt;. Here&amp;#39;s the instruction:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;partition&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; %) passwords)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next we test each pair in the partition to see that the first value in
the pair is less than or equal to the second one:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(map &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;(every? (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fn &lt;/span&gt;[ [a b]] (&amp;lt;= (int a) (int b))) %) passwrods)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pull out the ones where the above is true and count them:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(count (filter true?))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s part one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Python equivalent would be easier to read for the non-lisper but
the idea is the same and pretty straightforward. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I like is that we just solved a number problem without math, just
text processing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 is more of the same. This time we still need a pair of adjacent
same digits but runs of 3 or more didn&amp;#39;t count. Now, 122234 wouldn&amp;#39;t
be a valid password because the run is of 3 while 1222344 would
because while the repeated 2s don&amp;#39;t count the 4s would.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, this is just more text processing:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Check to make sure the sequence is increasing (as above)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remove all the sequences of 3 or more repeats. This can also be
xdone using a regular expression search and replace. In Clojure
it&amp;#39;s:
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;     cleaned (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;string/replace&lt;/span&gt; s &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;([0-9])\1\1+&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;) 
     &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
The [0-9]\1\1+ says match any sequence of 3 or more of the same
digit and we replace it with an empty string.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the remaining string has a pair of adjacent same digits (as
above) its a valid password.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s it. Both parts solved as a text processing problem. What
I love here is that it seems to be a numeric problem but it has a text
based solution. Certainly something worth talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another thing I thought about as a teacher but didn&amp;#39;t pay attention to
in my solution was efficiency. My range consisted of about 500,000
values to check. Not huge enough to make a time difference but it&amp;#39;s
worth noting that there are only about 500 that fulfill the
&amp;#34;increasing&amp;#34; requirement but almost 200,000 that have a double digit
subsequence. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This means it could be more efficient to look for increasing first and
throw away most of the data and then do the digit test. This type of
ordering can be a big deal for other problems so could be worth
discussing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another issue is pipelining. Are you looping over the entire (or even
culled) data set over and over or can you take each number and put it
through a sequence of tests and/or transformations - the pipeline
could also lead to a more efficient solution.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of good teacher fodder.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In closing I&amp;#39;ll mention one last thought - not mine but rather a
suggestion I found while perusing the Advent of Code subreddit after I
had submitted my solutions 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Someone noted that since a valid number has increasing digits, if
digits appear more than once they &lt;strong&gt;have&lt;/strong&gt; to be adjacent to each
other. If they weren&amp;#39;t they&amp;#39;d violate the increasing restriction. This
means that you could solve this problem more numerically by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
do the &amp;#34;increasing&amp;#34; test
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Find the sum of the counts of each digit value (0 through 9)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Test to see if at least one digit appears twice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Based on tomorrows schedule I doubt I&amp;#39;ll get to AoC day 5 but we&amp;#39;ll
see.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 19:01:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/3&#34;&gt;problem&lt;/a&gt; dealt with intersecting paths. You start with two
inputs, figure out the paths they represent and where they intersect
and then find the intersection that correctly answers the question.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For part 1 you have to find the intersection closest to the
origin. From a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view, the interesting part here is
data representation. This problem deals with a two dimensional grid on
which the paths live. For most students, at least in my experience, if
they&amp;#39;re trained in a language like C++ or Java they go for the direct
representation - a 2D array. For many problems this makes a lot of
sense. For this one, however, it probably doesn&amp;#39;t. We start at a
specific point but can travel in any direction for any distance. This
means we might need a crazy large array and what&amp;#39;s more, it&amp;#39;s probably
going to be sparsely filled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A more practical solution involves maintaining a data structure with
just the individual points of interest - the points on the path. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I chose a dictionary (or hash-map or hash-table depending on language)
The key would be a tuple representing a point and the value would hold
whatever data was needed. For part one that would be a set of the
paths that went through the point. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if we had a path made up of 2 intersecting lines:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-ditaa&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ditaa&#34; data-lang=&#34;ditaa&#34;&gt; |
-+-----
 |&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We could use a 2D array to represent it (assume the lines have ID&amp;#39;s 1
and 2):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1 2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s already a good deal of wasted space. using a dictionarey we&amp;#39;d
have:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;key (row,col)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(0,1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,0)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1 2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,2)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,3)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,4)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,5()&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1,6)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{1}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(2,1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;#{2}&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Which becomes much more space efficient once we go beyond the smallest
test cases.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we have the representation, the problem becomes one of stepping
through the paths and adding them to the dictionary. After that we can
pull out the small number of entries in our dictionary that were
visited by both paths and then we can find the final answer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I coded this up in Clojure &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day03.clj&#34;&gt;(solution here)&lt;/a&gt; but forgot to account for the fact that
when a path repeats itself it shouldn&amp;#39;t count as an intersection for
the purpose of the problem. Oops. I fudged things to get the right
answer but then had to head off to Albany.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I arrived I fixed the code but was pretty zonked so decide to
code the second part in Python &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day03.py&#34;&gt;(solution here)&lt;/a&gt;. Both solutions are pretty similar but
as I&amp;#39;m more comfortable with Python it didn&amp;#39;t require too much focus
to get it right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Given the wording of this problem, I think that most people will steer
towards the type of dictionary representation I used rather than a 2D
array but this way of storing data is worth discussing with classes
when you might otherwise use a 2D array.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When might you ask?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about something like Conway&amp;#39;s Game of Life. When this is done in a
CS1 class the world is usually represented as a 2D array. It&amp;#39;s simple
 and direct. Another approach would be to only store the live cells in
a list. You can check out a Clojurescript implementation that does
just that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life/tree/master/src&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another would be the N-Queens problem. Insead of a board, just store
the queens locations. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Image processing? Well, there probably not. When doing image work,
you actually use all the cells in the 2D array.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s pretty much all I have to say about today&amp;#39;s problem. It got me
thinking about alternate ways of representing our data. That&amp;#39;s
something we usually don&amp;#39;t have too much of an opportunity to discuss
with our students. That&amp;#39;s unfortunate.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent 2019 Day 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 17:11:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/2&#34;&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt; of Advent of Code 2019 was also pretty straightforward and once
again I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day02.clj&#34;&gt;my solution&lt;/a&gt; in Clojure but in order to talk about this
from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view, we&amp;#39;ll look at a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2019/blob/master/day02.py&#34;&gt;Python solution&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At its core, this is a simulation problem - read the data into an
array or list and write a program to run through the steps. At first I
was hoping that the solution would consume the data - that is, once
you read past an instruction you don&amp;#39;t go back to it. If it was, I was
going to try to write some clever reduce. It wasn&amp;#39;t. In this problem,
any instruction could affect any part of the data set. This means you
have to keep the entire data set in memory and preferably in a random
access structure like an array. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Step 1 is to read in the data and convert it into a list of integers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t know comprehensions you can just do something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we just have to run the simulation:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most likely source of error here is forgetting to change the
values in &lt;code&gt;program[1]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[2]&lt;/code&gt; in lines 18 and 19 as
specified in the question. The other likely error is forgetting to do
the two level indirection in lines 7 and 8. That is writing
&lt;code&gt;program[ip+1]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[ip+2]&lt;/code&gt; by mistake. Truth be told, I made
both of these mistakes but I didn&amp;#39;t find them to be &amp;#34;interesting&amp;#34;
mistakes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The interesting part of this program is part 2 where instead of
setting &lt;code&gt;program[1]&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[2]&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt; you have to try
values between 0 and 99 inclusive for each entry until you find a
specific answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a great platform to talk about memory. The problem refers to
the values you put into &lt;code&gt;program[1]&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;strong&gt;nouns&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;code&gt;program[2]&lt;/code&gt; as
&lt;strong&gt;verbs&lt;/strong&gt;. The issue is that every time you run your program for a
specific &lt;strong&gt;noun verb&lt;/strong&gt; combination you change the array (list)
representing your program. If you don&amp;#39;t reset the array to its
original contents before the next run, the next run will be working
off of new values and therefore give you incorrect results. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a great platform for discussion. Students usually start with
&lt;strong&gt;pass by value&lt;/strong&gt; semantics so passing a list to a function and then
having the list change can seem weird even though it can still be pass
by value:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s a finished solution:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that in line 30 we copy over the original data for each noun,verb
combo. also note the list comprehension in line 35 to find the final
answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One last potential error point is notice that we had to add the array
copy in line 20. Otherwise part1 will change the data and if we run it
before part2 we won&amp;#39;t get the correct result.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. Another nice problem and even though it&amp;#39;s a
straightforward problem, there&amp;#39;s still some interesting meat to
discuss with your students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow, snowstorm notwithstanding, I&amp;#39;ll be heading up to Albany for
the remainder of the week so might not be able to get to day 3 and
beyond until Friday so who knows if I&amp;#39;ll post any more of these
write ups.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2019 Day 1</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 14:23:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/advent-2019-day1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Like most programming challenges, &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; ramps out from
easier, more accessible problems to harder, more complex ones. As
such, a number of the early challenges are great problems for early CS
students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought that while I watched my NY Giants play valiantly in their
attempt to get a high draft pick I&amp;#39;d talk about today&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/1&#34;&gt;challenge&lt;/a&gt;
from a teacher&amp;#39;s point of view.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The summary of part one is that you have a list of inputs (masses of
components) and for each one you have to perform a calculation (how
much fuel is needed). The answer will be the sum of the fuels.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most challenging part of this for a beginner might be reading in
the data but that&amp;#39;s not too much of a challenge:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we can calculate part1:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 adds a twist. Now, you have to also consider the fuel needed
for the fuel you&amp;#39;ve added. Basically, you have to calculate how much
fuel you&amp;#39;ll need for a given item and then how much fuel you&amp;#39;ll need
for that fuel. You repeat this until the amount of fuel you need is
either 0 or negative. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/1&#34;&gt;the challenge&lt;/a&gt; for more info on this. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is our first &amp;#34;teaching moment.&amp;#34; This is going to be messy to work
into our part1 solution but if we had factored out the original fuel
calculation we could probably reused it and maybe more of our
solution:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we can just add an inner loop that repeatedly adds the fuel costs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More &amp;#34;teachable moments.&amp;#34; We have to change up variables in our fuel
calculations (lines 8 and 11) and for a beginner, the loop within a
loop can be somewhat muddled. It&amp;#39;s more complex but it&amp;#39;s doing
something that &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; more complex. It&amp;#39;s also good nested loop practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For more advanced students, if they&amp;#39;re familiar with list
comprehensions you can really clean up part 1:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
#+END_SRC
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but I think part 2 either stay&amp;#39;s more or less as is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I wrote my solutions in Clojure:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;ns &lt;/span&gt;day01
  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:require&lt;/span&gt; [clojure.string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:as&lt;/span&gt; string]
            [utils &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:as&lt;/span&gt; u]))


(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def &lt;/span&gt;test-masses [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1969&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100756&lt;/span&gt;])

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;; load data&lt;/span&gt;
(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def &lt;/span&gt;masses (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
             (slurp &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;day01.dat&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
             string/split-lines
             (map u/parse-int)
             ))


(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;calc-mass-part1 [mass]
  (- (quot mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;))

(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;part1 [masses]
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;calculate fuel for each mass then sum them all&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
  (reduce + (map calc-mass-part1 masses)))



(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;calc-mass-part2
  ([mass] (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc-mass-part2&lt;/span&gt; mass &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;))
  ([mass cost]
   &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Same as part 1 but loop to calculate fuel for the fuel&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
   (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[fuel (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;calc-mass-part1&lt;/span&gt; mass)]
     (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&amp;lt;= fuel &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)
       cost
       (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;recur&lt;/span&gt; fuel (+ cost fuel))))))
  
(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;part2 [masses]
  (reduce + (map calc-mass-part2 masses )))

(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;main []
(println (str &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Part1: &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part1&lt;/span&gt; masses)))
(println (str &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Part2: &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;part2&lt;/span&gt; masses)))
)

(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&amp;#39;s day 1. I don&amp;#39;t know if I&amp;#39;ll write up any more or, given my
travel and work schedule for the week,if I&amp;#39;ll even be able  to work
on more problems until next weekend. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event. If you&amp;#39;re teaching CS0 or CS1 students, you should
really check out Advent of Code.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>