<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AP on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ap/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (AP)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 12:24:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/ap/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating Perfect AP Exam Scores</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/celebrating-perfect-scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 12:24:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/celebrating-perfect-scores/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, it turns out that there were 601 perfect scores on this years
APCS-A exam. Over on Facebook a great question was raised - what does
this mean and should we celebrate this?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What does it mean? There&amp;#39;s no way to know. Maybe the number of perfect
scores is just scaling up linearly with test takers. Maybe More kids
are being exposed to CS prior to APCS-A and that&amp;#39;s leading to more
correct answers. Are teachers teaching to the test? Maybe the test was
just plain easier. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of my normal anti college board leanings, I don&amp;#39;t really have
an opinion on the why. What I do have an opinion on is whether we
should celebrate these scores or not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I don&amp;#39;t think we should. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does a perfect score really mean so much? Has a student who gets every
question correct really show that they know more or are a better
computer science student then another student who merely scores a
regular 5 (or an A on an in class assessment). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There have been countless times when I&amp;#39;ve looked over a test and found
a really clever, innovative solution to a problem. Something that
showed a much deeper understanding than the base solution I had in
mind. More often than not those tests got dinged a point here or there
for what I&amp;#39;d describe as minor errors. The students behind those tests
were much stronger than many &amp;#34;perfect paper&amp;#34; students so celebrating
the 100%s would be neither fair nor appropriate. More appropriate to
share out the interesting solution and hopefully enrich the entire
class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Celebrating perfect scores also encourages prepping for a perfect
score. That means prepping to do a lot of multiple choice questions in
a short period of time. That takes test specific drilling. I&amp;#39;d rather
my students know the material well enough to get the score they need
but would rather they not spend countless hours drilling for that
perfect score. That extra prep time could be better spent in countless
ways including something as simple as playing a game with some friends.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A test - any test - is a limited, imperfect assessment.We should be
moving away from high stakes tests and simplistic numeric grades and
celebrating perfect scores in contrary to this. Celebrating a perfect
test score misses the mark. We should be celebrating how our students
work and progress not how they score on an imperfect testing implement
be it the AP exam or one of our in class tests.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To close, I&amp;#39;ll leave you with a story. It&amp;#39;s about a college acceptance
but if you substitute perfect test score the gist is the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was talking to a friend of mine. His daughter went to Stuy and had
just gotten into her dream school. It also, coincidentally was the
school that her older brothers went to. I said to my friend &amp;#34;John, you
must be very proud of your daughter on getting into her dream school.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;No,&amp;#34; John replied. &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m not proud, I&amp;#39;m happy for her. I&amp;#39;m proud of her when she
helps somebody.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not the outside, imperfect validations we should be celebrating.
Rather we should be celebrating how our kids live, grow, and develop.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Thomas Friedman&#39;s editorial on the College Board&#39;s Two Codes left me concerned</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 10:20:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There was some buzz over &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/12/opinion/college-board-sat-ap.html&#34;&gt;this editorial&lt;/a&gt; about the College Board last
week. The two codes every child needs - Coding and the US
Constitution? Who could argue with that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not going to disagree. Civics and CS are important and can&amp;#39;t wait
until college. The thing that left me chilled though was that nobody&amp;#39;s
paying attention to the fact that the College Board - a private entity
with its own interests has so much influence over American education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the piece, Friedman states:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So rather than have SAT exams and Advanced Placement courses based on things that you cram for and forget, they are shifting them, where they can, to promote the “two codes.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In 2016, the College Board completely revamped its approach toA.P. computer science courses and exams. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nothing wrong here but the AP program is supposed to offer &amp;#34;college
level&amp;#34; work in high school. Back when the program started, from 
best I can figure, they offered exams based on courses that were
essentially HS implementations of college classes. Now they&amp;#39;re
flipping the script. They&amp;#39;re dictating what they think should be
taught at the high school level and, oh by the way, it&amp;#39;s college level
because it has the AP designation. The editorial goes into some
details. Now, I&amp;#39;m not against what they&amp;#39;re doing with AP US Gov, it
sounds like a really good idea. I&amp;#39;m against their overall influence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest concern I had though was with this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides revamping the government course and the exam on that subject, Coleman and Sanford in 2014 made a staple of the regular SAT a long reading comprehension passage from one of the founding documents, such as the Constitution, or another important piece of democracy, like a great presidential speech. That said to students and teachers something the SAT had never dared say before: Some content is disproportionately more powerful and important, and if you prepare for it you will be rewarded on the SAT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we put this on the SAT, schools will teach it so the kids will do
better the SAT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This should be chilling to everyone. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No, I&amp;#39;m not against the details but it&amp;#39;s frightening to have a private
entity with so much influence on public policy like
education. Ultimately, it can&amp;#39;t be good. Just because what the College
Board&amp;#39;s pushing in terms of civics jives with me doesn&amp;#39;t mean they
should be able to influence and manipulate curriculum across the
nation to such a degree. The College Board is pretty much accountable
to nobody. As long as students are told to take AP classes and the
SAT, particularly with politicians and boards of education agreeing to
pay the college board with taxpayers money, the public has very little
say. Sure, more better civics and CS is good but who&amp;#39;s to say the next
initiative will be in the public&amp;#39;s interest?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The same can be said for any of the major education players - for and
non profit alike both in and out of CS. We have to be more aware,
vigilant, and vocal when the power players accomplish things by being
the 800 pound gorilla even when we agree with what some of those
things are.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a big reason why I frequently speak out against the College
Board and other power players, some of whom I greatly like, respect,
and admire, and feel that others should feel obligated to do the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Ap Registration - it&#39;s, um, for the kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I stumbled upon a thread over in the APCS-A Facebook group the other
day. It seems that the College Board is making some changes in their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apcentral.collegeboard.org/about-ap/news-changes/ap-2019&#34;&gt;registration timeline&lt;/a&gt;. In the past, students registered for the exam
sometime in March with the exams administered in May. The new changes
include requiring registration in November along with $40 late
registration and cancellation fees.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The College Board is, of course, spinning this as for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3MCNEYCZWqw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;fbclid=IwAR04Uuj7vpHoYU_8jMjw00YpAPXp7gi3MDGdTKhzpUXv7mI0OILW01KyzvA%0A&#34;&gt;the student&amp;#39;s
benefit&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At least a portion of the teaching community thinks otherwise and has
in fact started &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.change.org/p/demand-the-college-board-not-mandate-fall-ap-exam-requirements-and-deadlines&#34;&gt;this petition&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me this is just another money grab by the College Board - an
organization that already has way too much influence over high school
education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s take a look at what the College Board actually brings to the
table. They offer an exam. A single exam in each subject offered
that&amp;#39;s supposed to in 3 hours encapsulate an entire years&amp;#39;s worth of
learning and from that, colleges might give  a student placement or
credit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you say &amp;#34;they offer so much more.&amp;#34; Do they?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teacher&amp;#39;s have to submit syllabi and the college board approves
them. They offer samples but so do text book authors and third party
organizations. In my case I rolled my own. The teacher also develops
the course. Does the College Board provide materials? I guess, but so
do those same groups that provide curricula. The college board
certainly doesn&amp;#39;t define the subject. Last I checked Calculus, was
pretty well defined way before the AP program. So was 
Chemistry, and most other subjects. Actually, due to their outsized
influence they do define the subset of the subject in some cases and
we should really be questioning this influence. Finally, the teacher does
the actual hard job of teaching the class. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m  just not seeing the value added. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re already seeing schools require that students take the exam to be
in the class or provide &amp;#34;incentives&amp;#34; like a credit or grade bump for
taking the exam or even removing the AP designation from the
transcript if the student doesn&amp;#39;t take the exam. Doing any of these is
just plain wrong. By all means explain the advantages and
disadvantages of taking the exam but to essentially force a student to
fork over money and personal data to an outside independent agency is
just plain wrong. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you say that students in many districts don&amp;#39;t have to pay. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is even more insidious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now it&amp;#39;s the taxpayer on the hook and the College Board has
successfully created an everlasting cash pipeline from the public into
private coffers while providing questionable value.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t agree with me and think that these requirements or
incentives  are fine ask yourself this: If you had a child in a class
and the teacher said &amp;#34;your child has to sit in a room with a friend of
mine for three hours, give them $100 and personal data and I will give
your child a higher grade&amp;#34; you&amp;#39;d be outraged. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spending three hours taking an external exam has no bearing on what a
student did or didn&amp;#39;t do in the class so the grades, credits etc
should be the same whether or not the kid took the AP exam.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s get back to the early registration changes. Currently kids
register for the AP exam in March. By then students might know what
college they&amp;#39;re likely to go to. They&amp;#39;ll know if the AP exam is of any
use to them. In November they don&amp;#39;t. I frequently lost some high
scores on AP exams because I had top students who were accepted early
to schools that didn&amp;#39;t award credit. I also lost a couple of low
scores of students that for whatever reasons had no chance at getting
a 3 or higher so opted not to sit for the exam. I guess the College Board came up
with a good way to get money for those kids without providing value in
return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are block scheduled schools or other situations where kids
don&amp;#39;t start the class until after the new November deadline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, let&amp;#39;s talk a bit about the College Board&amp;#39;s claim that this is
all for the students. The video talks about students doing better if
they signed up earlier. I&amp;#39;m skeptical but even if it&amp;#39;s true, is &amp;#34;doing
better on the AP exam&amp;#34; the goal we have for our students. How about
learning our subject area or being inspired to continue on with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the video, teachers talk about how the kids are more motivated and
focused because the exam. This is getting to sound a lot like the
inane focus on high stakes test where the test is the goal. Is the
motivation that &amp;#34;you paid the $100&amp;#34; so it&amp;#39;s wasted if you don&amp;#39;t do
well or &amp;#34;the school paid $100&amp;#34; so we&amp;#39;ll guilt you into studying more?
Sorry, as teachers we can do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure I&amp;#39;ll get some flak for writing this but I also suspect that
there are many teachers who agree with me that the College Board is
not looking out for students but rather themselves.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How early for APCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/how-early-apcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/how-early-apcs/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
In what grade should students take APCS? This question comes up from
time to time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve heard answers ranging from middle school through never. Infact,
years ago, my chairman relayed a conversation he had with Marvin
Minsky where he asked Minsky what the high schools should be teaching
with respect to CS. The answer was &amp;#34;nothing.&amp;#34; This was then amended to
&amp;#34;teach them to type.&amp;#34; Of course this was a long time ago but I believe
the sentiment was that college was the right time and the high schools
don&amp;#39;t know what they&amp;#39;re doing and will just screw up the
kids. Actually, I still see some of this attitude today and it gets
passed down where high school teachers sometimes don&amp;#39;t want the
middle schools to &amp;#34;mess up their kids&amp;#34; and on down the line.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point, it&amp;#39;s pretty clear that you can do good CS at the high
school level and as things are being pushed down the grades we&amp;#39;ll
eventually figure out what&amp;#39;s right and when.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, within the high school the question of what grade for APCS-A
remains.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There isn&amp;#39;t a single right answer for this but I can share
my experience and what I ended up deciding when I developed things at
Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
MATH BOOKS and Physics First
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As parents, my wife and I learned early on that we&amp;#39;d have to
supplement what our kids would learn in school, particularly in terms
of math and science. I was in charge of math. Since I used assorted
books to help, math time came to be known simply as &amp;#34;MATH BOOKS.&amp;#34; It&amp;#39;s
funny that now while my kids don&amp;#39;t look back super fondly on MATH BOOKS
they agree that it was an important thing for us to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I discovered, as I&amp;#39;m sure many parents do, that there are times when a
kid is just not ready for a subject. At one point I tried to introduce
Algebra too early and saw it wasn&amp;#39;t going to take so I pulled back. A
while later, we tried again. This time it was clear that they could do
the mechanics and solve problems based on rules and formulae but they
really didn&amp;#39;t &amp;#34;get it.&amp;#34; A third attempt some time later, they were
ready. They mastered the subject with deep understanding easily. It
could be argued that the early exposure helped but I don&amp;#39;t think it
did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The takeaway here is that kids can do the mechanics and appear to
succeed but if it&amp;#39;s too early, they don&amp;#39;t really learn the subject.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I saw this on a larger scale with &amp;#34;Physics First.&amp;#34; At Stuy, most
freshmen would take Bio in 9th grade followed by Chem and then Physics
in their Junior year. Physics first kids would take Physics in the 9th
grade. I don&amp;#39;t have any evidence for this but based on my inquiries
over the years it seemed that the kids who took physics in their
junior year had a deeper understanding of the subject.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also personally saw this when teaching math classes early on in my
career. Most Stuy freshmen take geometry. The math aces take
precalc or calc but a few weren&amp;#39;t math aces but were the star in their
middle school. They were pushed through geometry in 8th  grade and
started Stuy in Algebra 2 and Trig. The majority of these kids that I
taught could spit back all the formulas and theorems from geometry but
very few were actually ready for Alg2/Trig and struggled
considerably.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
APCS
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So what about APCS? At Stuy we always taught a superset of the old
APCS-AB. It&amp;#39;s mostly APCS-A in the Fall semester and Data Structures
in the Spring. When I started, there was no prerequisite for APCS so I
had students in all grades. Mostly Juniors and Seniors but a few
Sophomores. I think I only had a freshman in APCS once and they were
an outlier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of my sophomores were ready, more could merely spit back material
and do the mechanics - enough to pass the APCS-AB exam but they really
didn&amp;#39;t get it. There were some, however that weren&amp;#39;t ready. These were
very bright kids and while I can&amp;#39;t say for sure, deep down I very much
suspect that if they took my class a year later they would have done
much better and they might have followed a very different path towards
their future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a teachers we can change lives for the better and in fact save
lives. We can also do great damage. Because of the latter, teachers
should follow the mantra &amp;#34;first do no harm.&amp;#34; This led me to a general
rule of taking kids into APCS-AB until their junior year. If I were to
allow a sophomore in I wanted to be pretty sure that the kid was
ready.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later we were able to create a sophomore year CS requirement which
gave all kids exposure to CS prior to APCS-A (we still taught AB but
by now only the A exam was offered) and also gave us a platform to vet
the outliers who might be ready for APCS. For those kids, in addition
to an interview we had them self study APCS-A, do a project and sit
for the APCS-A final exam and then we&amp;#39;d add them to the second half of
our AP class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Has it worked?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By and large the system has worked. Kids now get an intro in the 10th
grade followed by APCS in 11 and more electives if desired in the
12th. For the kid that&amp;#39;s truly ready for APCS in the 10th grade, we
have a path. We don&amp;#39;t make it easy but the path is there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the years we&amp;#39;ve had some CS superstars come through the
program. Some have pushed back – &amp;#34;why do I have to take the intro?&amp;#34;
&amp;#34;Why can&amp;#39;t i start right away in APCS?&amp;#34; – after all was said and
done, all but one came back to say that we did it the right way and
that they benefited from all our classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Stuy, it seems that for most students, 11th grade is right for our
APCS. Between academic maturity, other classes, scheduling and
everything else, it seems that this works the best for us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Why the rush?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Frequently the question as to when to teach APCS revolves around how
early it can be taught. I have to ask - why are we so caught up with
doing things so early?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we&amp;#39;re just pushing college level courses down to high school then
what&amp;#39;s the point? The kids will have to take the classes again if
they&amp;#39;re going to major in CS anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you have a program that doesn&amp;#39;t duplicate college courses you might
want to have kids finish APCS-A earlier but I wonder how early you
really need.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a society we keep pushing things down younger and younger. We&amp;#39;re
pushing AP classes like history or APCS-P down to 10th grade or even
earlier. You have to ask, is a course that&amp;#39;s developmentally
appropriate for a 18-22 year old developmentally appropriate for a 14
or 15 year old? Probably not. You also have to ask that if it makes
more sense to push further ahead or if it&amp;#39;s better to do enrichment at
a level the kids can handle.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m an enrichment over acceleration guy but other people differ. Just
like the question of when for APCS, there&amp;#39;s probably not a single
right answer to this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Last words and what should you do?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said up front, there&amp;#39;s no right answer to this. I&amp;#39;m still
convinced that 11th grade is probably the best general entry point for
APCS-AB but if I were only teaching APCS-A maybe I&amp;#39;d shift it down a
year. My gut tells me no, partially based on teaching non APCS to 8th,
9th, and 10th graders but maybe. Of course, we all teach different
students in different environments so your mileage may vary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also those outlier kids that can truly master the subject at
an earlier age, I&amp;#39;m not really considering them here but they should
be accommodated when possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;ve been running a program for a while, look at the data - not
how many kids pass the exam - look at how many master the next level
material. If your kids next class is data structures in college, find
out how well prepared they were and see if and how it maps to the
grade in which they took APCS. If you&amp;#39;re just starting, I&amp;#39;d recommend
erring on the side of caution - remember &amp;#34;do no harm.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you have to teach CS and it turns out you have to teach it when the
kids are too young to master APCS-A then don&amp;#39;t teach APCS-A, teach
great CS at a level that&amp;#39;s appropriate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this will work itself out in time. Until we get there, there
will be some mis-steps - I know I&amp;#39;ve had mine. As long
as we continue to move the kids forward and give them something that they
wouldn&amp;#39;t have been getting otherwise while we figure all this out,
we&amp;#39;re doing pretty good.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m not going to congratulate you on your AP results</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While busy finishing off my sides for my talk at CSTA2018 this weekend
I noticed a Facebook post about APCS exam grades now or shortly being
available.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m no longer teaching high school but still fancy myself a teacher
first and part of the K12CS community. We&amp;#39;re a growing community and
we&amp;#39;re growing fast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Usually, at this time of year we see a number of people posting their
results. &amp;#34;I had 16 test takers, had 5 fives, 6 fours etc.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I decided that not only won&amp;#39;t I be congratulating anyone on their
results this year but decided to write this quick post to say no one
should.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying that hundreds of teachers out there don&amp;#39;t deserve
congratulations - they do. The problem is, for everyone who&amp;#39;s kids
got all fours and fives, somewhere out there was a teacher who
possibly through no fault of their own had students scoring ones, twos
and threes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I was at Stuy, almost all of my kids got fours or fives when the
exam was the old AB exam. When it went to A only, it was almost
exclusively fives with a few fours and maybe a single one. That wasn&amp;#39;t
me. It was the kids. The AP CS teacher before me got similar results
as did all of my colleagues and the teachers who are still
there. Again, it was the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s not to say that I didn&amp;#39;t add value. I know I spent a career at
Stuy doing right by those kids regardless of test scores.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The fact is that there&amp;#39;s only so much a teacher can do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Was APCS (A or principles) their first course?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What other demands are placed on the students?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about the teacher?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How many kids in a class? How much time?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is APCS an elective or required??
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is the teacher getting the support they need?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And the list goes on. I know some great teachers who never had classes
with great AP results and meh teachers that did. Actually, I know some
APCS and Calc teachers that consistently had classes with good scores
through drill and kill and building student speed. Of course, at the
same time these teachers totally turned the kids off from the subjects
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our teachers do deserve praise and congratulations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Praise for getting through another year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Praise for forging a path in this new subject area.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Praise for doing more with less.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Praise for inspiring kids and starting them on a path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Praise for changing lives for the better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And so on
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If your kids left with more than they came in with you did a great job
and deserve congratulations. If you set a seed that will later grow
you&amp;#39;ve done an enormous amount of good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s like I would always tell my kids when they won an award. I was
never proud of them actually winning the award. I was proud of how they carried
themselves, prepared, performed or whatever. The award was just some
outsider also noticing they&amp;#39;re awesome.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same thing here so I won&amp;#39;t be congratulating teachers on student test
results. The results coming in do provide some measure of closure for
the year though so I will congratulate you all on the year and your
work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope to see many of you this weekend at CSTA2018.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APCS-P -  Bigger Intake Or Leaky Pipe</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Advanced Placement Computer Science got top billing on Alfred
Thompson&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/01/computer-science-education-things-im.html&#34;&gt;Things I&amp;#39;m Watching in 2017&lt;/a&gt; post. Alfred talks about how
APCS-P exploded onto the scene and wonders what will happen with APCS
this year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have some questions as well but mine won&amp;#39;t be answered for years to
come, if ever.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like it or not, the College Board has an out sized influence on K12
education. As long as people are convinced that AP=good there will be
a push for more and more AP classes and APCS-P is a perfect class to
push. CS is the hot topic in K12, the topic is getting a big push
from both politicians and industry, the class has no pre-requisites
and in spite of being called a college course is somehow appropriate
for a typical tenth grader.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The concern here is that at the end of the day. APCS-P is an exam or
rather an exam plus two other assessments. The quality can vary
greatly. I&amp;#39;ve heard of APCS-P implementations that seem pretty
rigorous and I&amp;#39;ve seen implementations that are, quite frankly, a
joke. The question is this: is APCS-P both motivating kids to go on to
the next level and just as importantly preparing them to succeed at
that level?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We might never know.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A high school might only offer APCS-P. If APCS-A isn&amp;#39;t offered, we
might not know if the student went on to take more CS and we won&amp;#39;t
know if the student succeeded or not. I&amp;#39;ve seen this with some very
high profile, popular, after school/summer non-profits. The kids have
a great time and the non-profits rave about how much their kids learn
but then the kids take a real CS class in school and drop like
flies. Was it the teacher/professor or did the non-profit set the kids up to
fail by convincing them they knew a whole lot more than they did and
that CS was super easy all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If credit is given for APCS-P, it looks like it will be blanket
credit. CS majors and minors will still have to take all the same classes in
college and CS so it will be very hard to tell if APCS-P is
responsible for any uptick in CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the College Board is going to make a lot of
money but if APCS-P becomes the standard high school CS course will
this leave us with true, quality CS4All? I have my doubts.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching APCS-A for the first time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I got  an email from a friend the other day. Among other things, he
mentioned that he would be teaching APCS-A for the first time this
year. He&amp;#39;s a little trepidatious. He knows his stuff but he hasn&amp;#39;t
really done much using Java.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was going to respond in an email but thought I might share here
instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR - for all you APCS teachers who are new or new to Java - learn
your core CS, lean on your resources and support and it&amp;#39;s OK to tell
your kids &amp;#34;I don&amp;#39;t know, I&amp;#39;ll get back to you.&amp;#34;. Don&amp;#39;t worry, you&amp;#39;ll be great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first time I taught APCS was some time around 1991 or 1992. It was at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sewardparkhs.com/Famous-Alumni/&#34;&gt;Seward Park&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sewardparkhs.com/History/&#34;&gt;High School&lt;/a&gt;. It was the AB curriculum - that is one
semester of programming in Pascal and one semester of Data Structures
and Algorithms.  Being a computer science major the core material was
never a concern. I had taken APCS the first time it was offered in May
1984 in Pascal and while most of my college and pre-teaching professional work
was in C, my college started it&amp;#39;s CS sequence with Pascal. I was more
concerned with the actual teaching part. I had taught math for a year
and a half at that point but never CS and by any measure I was still
wet behind the ears. I never finished that first experience because I
was excessed to Stuy mid semester. I wasn&amp;#39;t particularly happy with my
performance but looking back, I think I did a pretty good job given
the situation and my experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After teaching math for a year and a half I was back in APCS at
Stuy. Still in Pascal. I spent the next few years figuring out how to
teach CS and APCS in particular along with starting a couple of new
classes. When the College Board decided to move the AP class to C++ I
was happy, sad and a little worried. Pascal had a bunch of limitations
but I had never used C++. True, I was a C programmer at heart but I
had never really done the OOP thing. I did, as it turned out, design a
number of my C systems in an Object Typed design: I would use a single
file per &amp;#34;class&amp;#34; where local variables were de facto instance
variables and functions in the file were methods and each file was a
singleton class. I read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Analysis-Design-Applications-3rd/dp/020189551X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503519770&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=Grady+Booch&#34;&gt;Booch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8&#34;&gt;Meyer&lt;/a&gt; on my own but I had no
schooling in OOP and no professional experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turned out, I didn&amp;#39;t have to worry. I knew my CS and while it
took me a while to become comfortable with OOP, the class, and of
course I knew this from the get go, started from nothing and built
up complexity a step at a time. The worst that might have happened is
that some of my solutions might have been more C-esque than C++.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The move to Java was a little more jarring. Now we had a totally new
language. I couldn&amp;#39;t fall back on C. It removed memory management and
explicit pointers and it had to be used in an Object Oriented
manner. I remember asking Mike Schidlowsky, a former student turned
friend who was the Java consultant on the Java edition of Sedgewick&amp;#39;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Robert-Sedgewick-Algorithms-Fundamentals-Structures/dp/B008VR3ZH4/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503520269&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=schidlowsky&#34;&gt;Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; book how to do something. It had to do with passing and
modifying arrays. In C there were a number of ways to accomplish what
I wanted to do. In Java, I couldn&amp;#39;t figure out how to do it the way I
wanted. My friend Mike told me &amp;#34;you just don&amp;#39;t do it that way in
Java.&amp;#34; Again, it turned out that I didn&amp;#39;t have to worry. The basic
coding was still the same as were the data structures and
algorithms. The only challenge was that I had to get into a Java OOP
mindset which it turned out wasn&amp;#39;t that hard.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I never really warmed up to OOP - I find other paradigms more
natural for me, I knew my CS and got more and more comfortable with
the Java (or C++) way of doing things as time wore on. Sometimes I
would say &amp;#34;I don&amp;#39;t know&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;let&amp;#39;s figure it out&amp;#34; but that&amp;#39;s OK.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, there are many more resources available for CS teachers. If
you&amp;#39;re new, lean on them. Use the mailing lists, stackexchange,
facebook groups. Online resources like repl.it, codehs.com etc. Yes,
it&amp;#39;s true that you&amp;#39;ll be better next time around and even better years
down the road but right now, you&amp;#39;re probably better than you think.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A number of my former students volunteer for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; - a really great
program that brings software engineers into the classroom to work with
non-CS teachers to deliver instruction. A number of my kids have
shared the following sentiment:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if I&amp;#39;m really helping
the teacher to become self sufficient or if I&amp;#39;m a great teacher but I
do know one thing - while I&amp;#39;m there, the kids are getting a hell of a
lot more than if I wasn&amp;#39;t there.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
– Remember that as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cost of AP Exams</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;m back from vacation and summer&amp;#39;s winding down I thought
I&amp;#39;d start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a
few summer topics I want to write about – standards and side projects
in particular but I&amp;#39;m also looking forward to talking more about the
classroom since, after all, at my core, I&amp;#39;m a teacher. When I saw &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2017/08/how_online_textbooks_could_help_more_students_take_ap_exams.html&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
article in my inbox this morning I thought I&amp;#39;d talk about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the piece, Lindsey Tepe since more kids are taking AP classes and
they&amp;#39;re very expensive, schools should look to lower other costs
related to AP classes so as to provide financial support so that
students can take that oh so important end of year exam:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the College Board continues to reimburse about one-third of the
test cost for eligible low-income students, only about half of states
are now offering any further financial assistance for students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ms. Tepe&amp;#39;s solution? Lower text book costs. As a way of lowering
school costs, I&amp;#39;m all for it. I&amp;#39;ve used free online resources in lieu
of textbooks for years but the savings should go somewhere where it
can make a difference. Perhaps lowering class sizes. The fatal flaw in
Ms. Teps&amp;#39;s piece is that it continues spinning the misplaced narrative
that AP Exams are a very important part of a child&amp;#39;s education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s be reminded of something: The AP Exam is one thing - an exam - a
single test at the end of the year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The narrative is that students should take more and more AP classes,
that they&amp;#39;re somehow better for kids. Part of this is due to the
potential college credit and part is because the public has been
bamboozled by the ridiculous school ratings that give credit for AP
classes taken. Back in &amp;#34;the day,&amp;#34; AP classes were basically early
college. You could then argue that they were the most rigorous classes
offered in a school. AP Calc was basically college Calc. Same for
APCS-AB, AP-Bio and the rest. Now, with classes like APCS-P aimed to
be accessible to typical high school students in the lower grades,
they can&amp;#39;t (but still will) make that claim. In fact, at Stuy, my
former school, there are plenty of non AP classes that are more
rigorous than AP classes and the best AP teachers don&amp;#39;t always cover
the whole syllabus because they&amp;#39;re more concerned with their students
actually learning rather than scoring 5 on an exam.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the college credit front, if a student has a high probability of
saving money through AP credit then I&amp;#39;m all for it but otherwise, it&amp;#39;s
just money going to the college board.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It seems ridiculous for me to have to write this but the important
part of a class is, you know, the class. Not the single exam given by
an outside agency at the end and graded after the semester concludes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My suggestion? Offer college level work to students that are ready for
it but don&amp;#39;t push the AP exam. This would save a ton of money. What value
does the college board actually bring to the table? Remember, they&amp;#39;re
making a pretty penny on all of this testing. A math teacher should be
able to teach calculus with or without AP. A good text being used by
that teacher in class - be it free or paid for is actually much more
important to a student learning calculus than a single exam taken at
the end of the year. I&amp;#39;d go further and say that I&amp;#39;d trust the
teacher&amp;#39;s exam more than the college board&amp;#39;s. If a teacher knows the
math but needs to see some sample syllabi, they&amp;#39;re a web search
way. The same is true for most other college courses that have AP
equivalents and maybe even more so for computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day it should be about students learning not about
students taking high stakes exams.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Plea to AP teachers- don&#39;t measure yourself by your scores</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
AP scores just came out. As usual, I see the posts and take part in
conversations where teachers talk about their results. Some are happy
about their results, some aren&amp;#39;t, some don&amp;#39;t really care.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I just want to make a plea to all AP teachers out there:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;#39;t let your value be dictated by the college board or any other
exam.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I never really cared much about my students&amp;#39; actual AP scores. There
were a number of years when I never even saw the results. Of course, I
had a population that would do reasonably well regardless of teacher
so I was never placed under any pressure to &amp;#34;do better.&amp;#34; One year -
while the APCS-AB exam was still offered, my principal called me down
to discuss the results to see if we could get more kids scoring 4s and
5s (which most of the kids already did). I told him that I thought
we were doing fine, explained why I couldn&amp;#39;t advocate more teaching to
the test (such as more than paying lip service to the case study or
more rote practice on the multiple choice), and told him how I
measured our success as a program. He was happy with my answer and
that was that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The AP exam is one test on one day and in my opinion the least
valuable measure of my students&amp;#39; achievement. This is one of
the reasons I was so dismayed by the CSEd community&amp;#39;s efforts in
pushing the AP exams - not the class or the subject but the actual exam.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, how should you judge your success? That&amp;#39;s up to you. I can only
tell you how I judge myself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost - and I know this sounds cheesy - are you a &amp;#34;force
for good&amp;#34; in your student&amp;#39;s lives. Do you leave them in a better
place? Have you opened the door to a possible future for them? Have
you helped them grow? Beyond that, have they progressed in your
subject and as students in general.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve had kids &amp;#34;fail&amp;#34; the AP exam and go on to wonderful careers in
tech and come back to thank me for giving them their start. I&amp;#39;ve also
had kids that have gone into other fields but appreciate what we&amp;#39;ve
done for them. I&amp;#39;ve also had my failures and I do mean my
failures. Students I couldn&amp;#39;t reach or couldn&amp;#39;t figure out how to
help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As teachers, we work day to day trying to improve but we can get a
great overview of how we&amp;#39;re doing by using a much longer feedback
loop - looking at what our graduates are up to. When young teachers
would comment on former students coming back or running into them at
tech events that they would have graduates of their own in a few years
and invariably they do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To really evaluate how you&amp;#39;re doing you have to go with the long
game. Very few people get that. I remember talking to a Google
Executive while I was designing CAPE 2010. He said something to the
effect of &amp;#34;I know we won&amp;#39;t know if this program works for about ten
years but we&amp;#39;ll have to come up with something short term to satisfy
the powers that be.&amp;#34;  That so few &amp;#34;get it&amp;#34; and need instant feedback
is one of the reasons that our society is so test driven. We shouldn&amp;#39;t
be. Our focus should be on helping the students learn and progress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So don&amp;#39;t get distressed over AP results and don&amp;#39;t get to high on them
either. Certainly don&amp;#39;t use them to drive what and how you teach. Let
your students and your conscience be your guide.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>