<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>languages on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/languages/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (languages)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 17:33:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/languages/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Different languages, different techniques, different solutions</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/different-languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 17:33:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/different-languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent this weekend diving back into Clojure or more specifically,
Clojurescript. For those who don&amp;#39;t know, Clojure is a Lisp that runs
on the JVM. The solution it particularly seeks to &amp;#34;solve&amp;#34; is
immutability. Clojurescript is Clojure that compiles to Javascript for
web applications. Tooling aside, it&amp;#39;s all pretty neat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t do anything earth shaking, just a quick implementation of
Conway&amp;#39;s game of life and Snake. While the code isn&amp;#39;t particularly
good, you can check them out here (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-snake&#34;&gt;Snake&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life&#34;&gt;Life&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Life implementation got me thinking about the value of studying
different languages or more specifically, different paradigms. A
student who implements the game of life in Java will likely implement
something very similar in C++ as both languages are Object Oriented /
imperative. An implementation in Clojure or Haskell will likely look
very different.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look a little deeper.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%2527s_Game_of_Life&#34;&gt;Conway&amp;#39;s Game of LIfe&lt;/a&gt; is a Cellular Automaton and when teaching a CS
class in Java or C++ it&amp;#39;s a really nice application of 2D arrays. On
each turn, for each cell in the world, you calculate its living
neighbors. If the cell is alive and it has 2 or 3 living neighbors, it
stays alive to the next turn. If the cell isn&amp;#39;t alive but has 3 living
neighbors it will become alive. Otherwise the cell dies (or remains
dead).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a Java type language, given a 2D array &lt;code&gt;this_turn&lt;/code&gt; with the current
world and you might get something like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a really nice application of 2D arrays and I&amp;#39;ve done it with my
classes frequently over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another language I&amp;#39;ve done &lt;strong&gt;life&lt;/strong&gt; in is NetLogo. In NetLogo, you have
a world represented by an x,y grid with each cell in the grid known as
a patch. You write a program and all the patches run it
independently. A life solution might look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-text&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-netlogo&#34; data-lang=&#34;netlogo&#34;&gt;ask patches [ 
  set n count nieghbors with [color =  red] ;; red cells will be alive
  ifelse color = red 
    [ ifelse n=2 or n = 3
        [set nextcolor red]
        [set nextcolor black]
    ] 
    [
      ifelse n=3
        [ set nextcolor red ]
        [ set nextcolor black ]  
    ]
ask patches [set color nextcolor]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My NetLogo is a little rusty so my syntax might be off but the idea is
to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
have each patch count it&amp;#39;s living neighbors and figure out it&amp;#39;s
next state - alive (red) or dead (black)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
have each patch set its color to the new state
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a very different solution. In NetLogo you never think about
looping over the cells. It&amp;#39;s much higher level. You think about each
location as it&amp;#39;s own entity whereas in the Java solution you&amp;#39;re
getting much more into the nitty gritty. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NetLogo and Java are very different languages and using them
encourages you to solve problems in different ways. you&amp;#39;d likely
never create a 2D array in NetLogo - you&amp;#39;d exploit the word as your
array. Likewise you&amp;#39;d exploit the patches to distribute the work. In
Java you&amp;#39;d probably wouldn&amp;#39;t create a class to represent each patch in
the array and then run each in a thread. That would be overkill for
the problem at hand.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, what about Clojure?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Clojure isn&amp;#39;t set up for 2D arrays, at least not as cleanly as a
language like C++ or Java. One could use Java Interop - that is, the
ability of Clojure to directly use Java but that would defeat the
purpose of using Clojure. Clojure is all about lists, vectors, and
maps. Instead of a 2D array of the world, I made a list (vector) where
each element contained the location of a living cell. This is
certainly more space efficient. It also let me operate on the world as
a sequence of transformations to the data:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Calculate all the possible next cells (the cells in the list plus
all their neighbors
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For each possible next cell, count it&amp;#39;s living neighbors and
determine if the cell is alive in the next iteration
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Replace the list of cells with these new cells. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-clojure&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34; data-lang=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;generate [state]
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Generate and return the next state&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;[potential-cells (for [[x y] state [dx dy] cell-bloc-3x3]
                          [(+ x dx) (+ y dy)])
        next-state (for [cell potential-cells]
                     (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;alive?&lt;/span&gt; cell state) cell))]
    (into &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;{} (remove nil?(into &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;{} next-state)))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can see the complete code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life/blob/master/src/life.cljs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This again is a very different way of thinking about the problem. In
Java we looped over the world and made adjustments. Here we
transformed the current set of cells into the next generations set of
cells in a pipeline like fashion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another feature of Clojure that results from its focus on immutability
is that in programs like these the computational part of the program
and the presentation part (the graphics) are totally separate. We
first transform the data and then the UI displays the current
data. Clojure does this very nicely and maybe I&amp;#39;ll write a post on
it but for now, I just want to point out that this is very different
from NetLogo. In fact, I completely finished the program for life
before I even thought about the interface. In NetLogo the interface is
an integral part of the language.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The point of all of this is that languages designed around different
paradigms are worth exploring even if you never do real work in
them. Even if you don&amp;#39;t like or use Clojure you can take lessons from
it&amp;#39;s functional side and how it handles immutability and you can add
those techniques to your toolkit when using C++ or Java. It doesn&amp;#39;t
mean you should write Java to look like Clojure but having a complete
toolkit of paradigms to draw from and apply when appropriate can only
be good for us and for our students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use A Real Language</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 15:08:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why can&amp;#39;t we use a real language!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This topic has been coming up a lot recently. Now I&amp;#39;m not talking
about the Drag and drop vs textual language thing. Let me be clear. To
me a Drag and Drop language can certainly be a real language and many
are. I also think they&amp;#39;re terrific when used correctly. I just think
they&amp;#39;re frequently misapplied in later grades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No, I&amp;#39;m talking about people asking things like &amp;#34;Why do we have to use
Java in our class, why can&amp;#39;t we use a real language like &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#34; Or
at Hunter, I might get &amp;#34;Why do we have to use C++, why can&amp;#39;t we use
Java.&amp;#34; Back at Stuy I&amp;#39;d get the same question about Scheme and
Netlogo. It actually doesn&amp;#39;t really matter what language you
use. Someone else, usually a non-teacher always knows better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this reminded me of when I was young. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started with BASIC and then in high school programmed Fortran IV
using punch cards on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_1130&#34;&gt;IBM 1130&lt;/a&gt;. At the time BASIC was considered a
toy language and Fortran IV not to mention punch cards were
yesterday&amp;#39;s technology. I also took APCS the first year it was offered
and that&amp;#39;s where I learned Pascal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then went to NYU - The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. There
we also used Pascal as the core language. That was the language used
in CS1, Data Structures, and Algorithms. It was also the default
language for other classes. That is, unless the class lent itself to
a specific language such as Lisp for AI you&amp;#39;d probably use
Pascal. I learned C early on in my college career and also took
classes that used Ada, and 8088 Assembly. I mostly tried to stick with
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was the hot language at the time and all the cool kids were
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
using it. Some kids continued to use Pascal but it was universally
derided. It wasn&amp;#39;t a &amp;#34;real language.&amp;#34; Nobody used it for anything
serious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Senior year it was time to look for a job. I ended up going  to
Goldman Sachs and developed for PCs running Windows 2.1 in C. They
also hired a bunch of college grads to program the Stratus systems in
PL1 and Cobol programmers for the mainframes. This was
around 1989. Goldman and most other big companies started you in a
training program. I already knew C but they ran a crash course for my
group. They did the same for the Cobol kids although most of them had
learned it in their business schools. The PL1 kids were grouped in
with the C and Cobol groups and had to figure out PL1 on their own
once they were assigned teams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My story tough, isn&amp;#39;t about Goldman. It&amp;#39;s about another big bank I
interviewed with. I won&amp;#39;t name them but it&amp;#39;s a big firm that still
exists today. I think they had at least a whole big building down on
the street back when I interviewed but I don&amp;#39;t remember. The interview
process was tough and thorough. We talked about the firm, what they
did, the platforms they developed and of course they drilled me on
what I brought to the table. The funny thing was that their entire
PC platform was built in, yep, you guessed it, Turbo Pascal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here was a really respected financial firm doing really interesting
tech and they were using that fake toy language that no kid would ever
use for real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it. All this &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s not a real language&amp;#34; stuff is
largely nonsense. If it can solve your problem it&amp;#39;s real. If it can
teach your concept it&amp;#39;s real. The rest is nonsense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a side note, my first programming gig was in the mid 1980s for a
ticket printing company - Arcus Simplex Brown. I worked on a computer
ticket printing system for them. It was in BASIC and ran on a little
PC running CP/M with a big line printer. Best I could figure they were
still using the same system in 2012.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/ticket.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, don&amp;#39;t get caught up with someone else&amp;#39;s opinion of what&amp;#39;s a real
language just make sure your students are getting what they need.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>