<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>langauges on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/langauges/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (langauges)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 15:08:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/langauges/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Use A Real Language</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 15:08:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why can&amp;#39;t we use a real language!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This topic has been coming up a lot recently. Now I&amp;#39;m not talking
about the Drag and drop vs textual language thing. Let me be clear. To
me a Drag and Drop language can certainly be a real language and many
are. I also think they&amp;#39;re terrific when used correctly. I just think
they&amp;#39;re frequently misapplied in later grades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No, I&amp;#39;m talking about people asking things like &amp;#34;Why do we have to use
Java in our class, why can&amp;#39;t we use a real language like &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#34; Or
at Hunter, I might get &amp;#34;Why do we have to use C++, why can&amp;#39;t we use
Java.&amp;#34; Back at Stuy I&amp;#39;d get the same question about Scheme and
Netlogo. It actually doesn&amp;#39;t really matter what language you
use. Someone else, usually a non-teacher always knows better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this reminded me of when I was young. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started with BASIC and then in high school programmed Fortran IV
using punch cards on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_1130&#34;&gt;IBM 1130&lt;/a&gt;. At the time BASIC was considered a
toy language and Fortran IV not to mention punch cards were
yesterday&amp;#39;s technology. I also took APCS the first year it was offered
and that&amp;#39;s where I learned Pascal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then went to NYU - The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. There
we also used Pascal as the core language. That was the language used
in CS1, Data Structures, and Algorithms. It was also the default
language for other classes. That is, unless the class lent itself to
a specific language such as Lisp for AI you&amp;#39;d probably use
Pascal. I learned C early on in my college career and also took
classes that used Ada, and 8088 Assembly. I mostly tried to stick with
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was the hot language at the time and all the cool kids were
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
using it. Some kids continued to use Pascal but it was universally
derided. It wasn&amp;#39;t a &amp;#34;real language.&amp;#34; Nobody used it for anything
serious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Senior year it was time to look for a job. I ended up going  to
Goldman Sachs and developed for PCs running Windows 2.1 in C. They
also hired a bunch of college grads to program the Stratus systems in
PL1 and Cobol programmers for the mainframes. This was
around 1989. Goldman and most other big companies started you in a
training program. I already knew C but they ran a crash course for my
group. They did the same for the Cobol kids although most of them had
learned it in their business schools. The PL1 kids were grouped in
with the C and Cobol groups and had to figure out PL1 on their own
once they were assigned teams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My story tough, isn&amp;#39;t about Goldman. It&amp;#39;s about another big bank I
interviewed with. I won&amp;#39;t name them but it&amp;#39;s a big firm that still
exists today. I think they had at least a whole big building down on
the street back when I interviewed but I don&amp;#39;t remember. The interview
process was tough and thorough. We talked about the firm, what they
did, the platforms they developed and of course they drilled me on
what I brought to the table. The funny thing was that their entire
PC platform was built in, yep, you guessed it, Turbo Pascal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here was a really respected financial firm doing really interesting
tech and they were using that fake toy language that no kid would ever
use for real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it. All this &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s not a real language&amp;#34; stuff is
largely nonsense. If it can solve your problem it&amp;#39;s real. If it can
teach your concept it&amp;#39;s real. The rest is nonsense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a side note, my first programming gig was in the mid 1980s for a
ticket printing company - Arcus Simplex Brown. I worked on a computer
ticket printing system for them. It was in BASIC and ran on a little
PC running CP/M with a big line printer. Best I could figure they were
still using the same system in 2012.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/ticket.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, don&amp;#39;t get caught up with someone else&amp;#39;s opinion of what&amp;#39;s a real
language just make sure your students are getting what they need.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new first language? What&#39;s the follow up plan?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-language-changing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-language-changing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial&#34;&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about Stanford possibly &lt;a href=&#34;https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/04/21/cs-department-updates-introductory-courses-java-is-gone/&#34;&gt;moving away
from Java&lt;/a&gt; as their intro language. This comes on the heels of a
semi-regular thread on one of the lists I&amp;#39;m on asking about what
languages are used at assorted colleges around the country. Invariably
the Pascal -&amp;gt; C++ -&amp;gt; Java progression of APCS turns up in these
threads.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are plenty of arguments to be made both for and against pretty
much any language or platform. There&amp;#39;s no single best universal
answer. Each choice giveth and each choice taketh away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I&amp;#39;m really curious about is who&amp;#39;s looking at intro languages in
the context of complete programs or even complete educations that
could span multiple institutions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Early language choices can make a big difference in engaging and
exciting newcomers but there are ramifications later on that few seem
to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take the APCS change from C++ to Java. It removed memory management
from the first year course. It also simplified issues relating to
pass by value vs pass by reference (or, rather, passing address by
value), bought much more strongly into OOP and moved more towards
using built in implementations of data structures like Lists rather
than rolling your own.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Removing memory management from the first year course in and of itself
isn&amp;#39;t a problem as long as it&amp;#39;s taught and taught effectively
somewhere later on. It could be argued that &amp;#34;memory is already covered
in our required systems course.&amp;#34; That could be the case, but there are
many concepts that kids don&amp;#39;t get the first time around. Is an
institution that covered memory management in CS1/2 and then came back
to it in a later Systems course giving their students the same
understanding now that they&amp;#39;ve eliminated the CS1/2 experience?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about OOP buy in. Personally, I&amp;#39;ve never been a big OOP fan but
that&amp;#39;s neither here nor there. What I have found is that depending on
how a student is exposed to programming in CS1/CS2 can have a big
influence on how they approach problems later. Did the move to Java
cause more of our students to try to use shoehorn OOP into a problem
that really shouldn&amp;#39;t be approached in an OOP manner?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I suspect that the use of built in data structures has had a
negative impact. A few years after the switch to Java, I was talking
to a senior tech worker. He was having a bad day - interviewing
potential internees and full time engineers. My friend was complaining
that the kids couldn&amp;#39;t come up with solutions to what he thought were
pretty straightforward questions. He felt that had the kids actually
implemented algorithms like the nlogn sorts rather than just learning
java .sort method and just talking about the algorithm they&amp;#39;d be
better prepared. I&amp;#39;ve heard this sentiment repeated over and over
throughout the years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that Java is a horrible language or horrible for
teaching - that&amp;#39;s another debate. The point is that you can&amp;#39;t just
look at the intro class and who it draws in. You have to consider how
it will prepare students for the next level and you have to look at
the big picture – will our students get everything they need by the
time they leave us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many schools have moved to Python. Will that effect students take on
type systems later on? Will the flexibility and constructs like list
comprehensions make it harder to teach recursion since there are
&amp;#34;easier&amp;#34; ways to do it?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
None of these are really problems so long as the CS1/2 (or even CS0)
isn&amp;#39;t taught in a vacuum.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I fear, however that too often we&amp;#39;re paying attention to the intake of
the pipe and not so much the output.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>