<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tech on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/tech/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (tech)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 11:56:23 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/tech/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping Current Between Semesters</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/keeping-current-between-semesters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 11:56:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/keeping-current-between-semesters/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
People say that one of the impossible problems for CS teachers is
keeping current - they say the field is constantly changing, how can a
teacher keep up with all the new things going on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, on the one hand it isn&amp;#39;t true - most of the core of CS is the
same. We still teach roughly the same programming constructs, data
structures and algorithms. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it is true. When I was in college, OOP was just
starting to pick up steam and now an established and one might argue,
dominant paradigm. Functional programming has been around forever but
is only recently making inroads into the mainstream. Some fields have
radically changed. Just look at AI and related fields now that data is
so abundant. I remember looking over a Natural Language Processing
text in the mid 90s and it was all about programs with tons of if
statements. A later edition read more like a statistics text book.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are the changing technologies - the web and how we program
it, new languages, embedded systems are more accesible and much more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So the field both changes and stays the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the ways I try to stay on top of things is with my own personal
projects. We encourage our students to write side projects
to scratch itches so why shouldn&amp;#39;t we do the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might be taking a course like when I did the Stanford online AI
and ML courses or it might be writing something like when I wanted to
figure out that &lt;a href=&#34;https://reactjs.org/&#34;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; thing that was all the rage a couple of years
ago but ended up diving more deeply into  &lt;a href=&#34;https://vuejs.org/&#34;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; as I felt it made
more sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re between semesters at Hunter I thought I&amp;#39;d scratch an
itch related to &lt;a href=&#34;https://classroom.github.com/classrooms&#34;&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. I love the tool but it has two pain
points. First, you end up accumulating a HUGE number of repositories
(one per student per assignment) and deleting them is a bear of a
task. The second is that while you can download all the submissions
for a given assignment, there&amp;#39;s no easy way to download all the
assignments for a given student. There are also some issues mapping
student names to GitHub accounts but I&amp;#39;ve pretty much worked that one
out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I figured I&amp;#39;d spend some time this December and January learning
some new technologies adn writing something to make those pain points
go away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what will I be learning about?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The GitHub API
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve worked with APIs before and even messed around with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt;. The
change is that their &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v4/&#34;&gt;latest&lt;/a&gt; version uses GraphQL which brings me to my
first brand new technology:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
GraphQL
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://graphql.org/&#34;&gt;GraphQL&lt;/a&gt; is a query language developed by Facebook for APIs. In spite
of the name, it has nothing to do with databases. The idea is instead
of a bunch of random REST endpoints with every API call being
different you have one endpoint. You put together a query describing
what you want and the services responds with your content. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It looks pretty neat but we&amp;#39;ll see.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Reagent / Clojurescript
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next thing I&amp;#39;ll be playing with is &lt;a href=&#34;https://clojurescript.org/&#34;&gt;Clojurescript&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://reagent-project.github.io/&#34;&gt;Reagent&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;ve
been playing on and off with Clojure for a while ahd Clojurescript
transpiles Clojure to Javascript instead of compiling for the
JVM. I&amp;#39;ve  already made a few &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life&#34;&gt;small&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-breakout&#34;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-snake&#34;&gt;using&lt;/a&gt; it and like it much
better for the web than Javascript. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learnreagent.com/&#34;&gt;Reagent&lt;/a&gt; is essentially React for
Clojurescript.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Electron
&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought for a while about doing this as a command line tool since
that&amp;#39;s how I usually work but decided that if I do finish it something
GUI based might be useful to more people. I then considered a web
applicaiton but realized that wouldn&amp;#39;t do since there isn&amp;#39;t a way to
clone GitHub repos from a web application due to security issues. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then briefly considered doing a Clojure based GUI which would
basically be something like a Java Swing application but then decided
to explore &lt;a href=&#34;https://electronjs.org/&#34;&gt;Electron&lt;/a&gt;. An Electron appication is essentially a locally
run web application. You write it in a similar manner to a web app -
HTML/CSS/JS or in my case Clojurescript but then it&amp;#39;s run locally on a
platfomr based on the open source Chromium browser. Since it&amp;#39;s running
locally it has access to the local filesystem and resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve already started to play with things and already learned a
lot. Looking forward to coming out of this with a bunch of new
technologies and tools in the toolbelt and maybe an application that
will solve a couple of annoyances with what&amp;#39;s overall a great product.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeland 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent today at &lt;a href=&#34;https://codelandconf.com/&#34;&gt;Codeland&lt;/a&gt;, a one day conference in NYC designed for
developers in the early stages of their careers. Just as at CSTA, I
was there with the GitHub contingent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Codeland had talks and a keynote in a common auditorium, smaller
breakout workshops and a couple of small vendor areas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent most of the morning upstairs in the GitHub lounge so I onl
caught part of one morning talk. Up in the lounge we, along with the
other vendors - IBM, Flatiron health, and Command Line Hero were
available to talk shop and hang out with conference goers. To be
honest, not too many people came by. I attribute that to the fact that
we were up on the ninth floor and the elevators didn&amp;#39;t work very
well. We were in a nice space with plenty of areas for conference
goers to relax, schmooze, get a snack and even play games but it was
too much of an effort to get to us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also decided not to attend any of the workshops and stayed up in the
lounge. The workshops were targeted at new devs early in their career
so while some looked interesting to me, I didn&amp;#39;t want to take up a
seat from anyone who really could benefit from them,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, I relocated to the downstairs vendor area. That was much
better. Since it was right near both the snacks and the main
auditorium there was much more foot traffic. I also got to hear and
see all the afternoon talks since audio and video were available right
near where I was set up. They were pretty cool. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, the best part of the conference was the ability to talk with
the conference attendees. On the one hand, I was there to talk GitHub
but I also had the chance to talk general tech with them. I got to
talk to people at all stages on their coding journeys. There were
undergraduate students studying CS, second career people either in
code schools or self learning, Former CS students who&amp;#39;s lives had gone
in other directions but now they&amp;#39;re looking to get back into tech and
more. I got to hear about the excitement of their adventures and tried
to give advice and encouragement to those having a hard time breaking
in to tech. Having shepherded so many people from neophytes to
professionals I&amp;#39;d like to think I could provide some guidance to some
of the people chatted with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if there are any other conferences like Codeland but if
there aren&amp;#39;t there should be. It can be hard to break into tech and
Codeland created both a safe environment for tech newbies and also
provided really valuable content. I wasn&amp;#39;t familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codenewbie.org/&#34;&gt;CodeNewbie&lt;/a&gt;,
the organization behind Codeland before but now I&amp;#39;ll have to see if I
can have a sit down with them to talk shop and tech ed.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New(ish) Blog - cscheerleader.com</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 09:05:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Many of us know &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cscheerleader&#34;&gt;Ria Galanos&lt;/a&gt;. Ria - a longtime friend and longtime CS
teacher who has been very active in the APCS community has started a
new chapter as a software engineer at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yext.com/&#34;&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt;. Ria&amp;#39;s also started
blogging about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know the direction the blog will take but I&amp;#39;m sure it will be
influenced by Ria&amp;#39;s years as an educator. I&amp;#39;m also sure it will be
worth reading.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, Ria added an RSS feed to the blog so you won&amp;#39;t miss a
post. You can us a reader service like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.feedly.com&#34;&gt;Feedly&lt;/a&gt; or if you&amp;#39;re an Emacs
wonk like me, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-31-elfeed-3/&#34;&gt;elfeed&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can find Ria&amp;#39;s blog at &lt;a href=&#34;https://cscheerleader.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cscheerleader.com/&#34;&gt;https://cscheerleader.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Technical Interviews And Diversity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/technical-interviews-and-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 11:27:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/technical-interviews-and-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently stumbled upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/laurieontech/with_replies&#34;&gt;Laurie Barth&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter and noticed a couple
of tweets about tech interviews and the hiring process, something I&amp;#39;ve
been thinking about recently.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Solid rant. I
think the teach to the programming test market already exists. And
it’s why interviewers who subscribe to these tactics get upset if a
candidate admits they’ve seen the problem previously. Because it ruins
the illusion that this is revealing how candidates think. &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/DpHgQx0TST&#34;&gt;https://t.co/DpHgQx0TST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Laurie (@laurieontech) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/laurieontech/status/1121879805862064131?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April
26, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;One of the
things I often think about is feeling like I got lucky making it
through some of my interviews...and then killed it on the job. We know
interviews don’t match the on the job skills, it’s about time we did
something about it. &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/xmUXkGvtoA&#34;&gt;https://t.co/xmUXkGvtoA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Laurie (@laurieontech) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/laurieontech/status/1122496300912717825?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April
28, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I guess I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about it because I&amp;#39;m teaching a section of
Data Structures which, along with Algorithms, provides the base
knowledge you need to have a shot at the typical &amp;#34;Google Style&amp;#34;
technical interview.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I say &amp;#34;base knowledge&amp;#34; because just completing those two classes
doesn&amp;#39;t really prepare you. It gives you the building blocks but you
really have to prep specifically for the types of questions they might
give you. Unfortunately, for most kids it involves a whole lot of
rejection and failure before you start getting offers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You might get a problem that has a bad brute force solution and during
the relatively short interview, devoid of your typical resources and
comforts you have to turn it into a much more efficient one. The
argument is that the interviewer is really trying to see how you think
about a problem but having spoken to many, many tech employees who do these
interviews that&amp;#39;s a specious argument at best. It&amp;#39;s really a test of
&amp;#34;who has seen the problem or something similar before but can fake
that they haven&amp;#39;t the best.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While it&amp;#39;s true that you will get some candidates who can solve the
problems on the spot you&amp;#39;re going to miss out on a whole bunch of
great candidates who just don&amp;#39;t do well on that &amp;#34;Google style&amp;#34; of
interview. At the same time we keep hearing that, as Laurie tweeted,
the skills required on the job don&amp;#39;t match the ones needed to pass the
interview. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn&amp;#39;t really matter to the big, hot companies. The Googles and
Facebooks of the world. So many students coming out of college want to
work for them that they can afford to miss on tons of great candidates
so long as they hit on enough good ones. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I put the word &amp;#34;diversity&amp;#34; in the title of this post and you might
wonder what I was going for there. So far, I&amp;#39;m just ranting about the
interview process. This becomes a diversity and privilige issue
because the process favors &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; CS schools with established CS
cultures. I&amp;#39;m not talking about the fact that they pre-select high
performing candidates nor the fact that all the tech companies go to
those schools, sometimes exclusively for recruiting. I&amp;#39;m talking about
how the school&amp;#39;s student tech culture helps prepare the students for
the technical interview. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From my discussions with many graduates from many of these institutions, while
classes don&amp;#39;t prep for interviews, students at these CS schools
regularly share interview questions. Friends and classmates talk about
the questions they got and help each other out with practice
sessions - formal or otherwise. I&amp;#39;m certainly not faulting students
for doing this but it&amp;#39;s another known  secret. We all know that the
more tech interview questions you see the better prepared you&amp;#39;ll be -
both because you&amp;#39;ll get better at that specific problem solving skill
and also because you&amp;#39;ll likely get interview questions that are
already in your library. It&amp;#39;s that latter part that makes the whole
process very nod, nod, wink wink. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nothing stops other students at other schools from doing similar but
it&amp;#39;s much harder at a commuter school where kids live off campus and
have to work part time jobs. It&amp;#39;s the reason I&amp;#39;m fighting so hard for
space and working on building a postitive tech culture at Hunter. Not
specifically for interviews but to help my students become a support
network for each other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll finish by noting that while this &amp;#34;technical interview&amp;#34; process
might more or less work for the big boys - the hot company du jour, it
probably doesn&amp;#39;t for eveyrone else. A buddy of mine was talking to me
about the process he uses at his much smaller company. He noted that
he could use the &amp;#34;Google interview&amp;#34; process for his future employees
but since his company was much smaller and lesser known, people who
did well would probably also get offers from the big boys and go work
for them. His goal was to come up with a process that catches the
great candidates that &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;#39;t&lt;/strong&gt; do well on the Google interview to try
to catch the great talent that doesn&amp;#39;t do well on today&amp;#39;s technical
interviews. A number of smaller companies seem to be starting to do
this and from the few I&amp;#39;ve spoken to it seems to be going well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get that big companies are machines and look for uniformity in all
processes including the interview process but there has to be a
better, more human way to evaluate talent than a one size fits all
process where the norm is failure - particularly when it seldom
relates to actual skills needed on the job.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Jobs, Diversity, and Equity in the wake of the Amazon/NYC debacle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 11:14:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was planning on either following up on how I use GitHub classroom or
commenting on the recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/12/opinion/college-board-sat-ap.html&#34;&gt;NY Times opinion piece&lt;/a&gt; on the College Board
but the follow up, fall out, and polarization from the Amazon NY thing
has been stuck in my head so I thought I&amp;#39;d write a bit more about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, this isn&amp;#39;t really about Amazon but rather about
the long game, equity, and diversity and how a lot of people are
fooling themselves.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s interesting that the communities I&amp;#39;m in are fairly polarized - my
pure tech world frients are big time upset that the deal fell through while
my pure educator friends, particularly the public school ones, are
really happy things worked out the way they did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big disappointment from the tech side revolves largely around the
jobs lost. Lots of tech jobs no longer coming fast and furious. The problem is,
who&amp;#39;s going to fill them. We&amp;#39;ve been hearing for years that there&amp;#39;s a
tech talent problem. Every company at every meetup seems to say &amp;#34;oh,
and we&amp;#39;re hiring,&amp;#34; Google&amp;#39;s expanding as are, as far as I can tell,
most of the other tech giants in the city. How can both be true? If we
need those new jobs now then there must be a glut of tech people
clamoring for employment. If indeed talent is hard to find, how will
NY be able to fill this new need. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We all know the answer - import them. Companies that can have and will go to
the &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; institutions around the country and try to recruit the
talent to NY. At the end of the day the politicians can look and say
&amp;#34;behold, I have taken this slum and transformed it into a paradise&amp;#34;
and that might technically be true. Problem is that they did it by
further marginalizing and displacing those already on the fringes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s hard to see. When I was younger - before I was deeply immersed in
public education all I saw was the gentrification - look the
neighborhood has gotten better. Now I understand the cost. I&amp;#39;m reminded
of Hofstadter&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%25C3%25B6del,_Escher,_Bach&#34;&gt;GEB&lt;/a&gt; where the anteater is friends with Aunt Hillary -
an ant colony and in fact was an ant surgeon. He &amp;#34;healed&amp;#34; the colony
through strategic amputations. The colony remained healthy but at the
cost of the individuals who didn&amp;#39;t make the cut.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The only way all these high paying tech jobs are going to come from NY
if NY can generate them and the truth is, right now, we can&amp;#39;t.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colleges nation wide are dealing with capacity issues. At least one
dropped its CS minor - arguably more valuable than a CS major for may
students. Stories abound on how hard it is to attract faculty and in
NYC we also have to deal with real estate issues. At Hunter, we can&amp;#39;t
just plop down a new building for CS even if we did have the money. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This of course is not just a capacity issue but also a diversity and
equity one and too many players are rearranging the deck chairs on the
Titanic. Some tech players are making an honest effort to deal with
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usv.com/blog/our-first-network-wide-diversity-inclusion-survey&#34;&gt;diversity&lt;/a&gt; and equity in a meaningful way, too many aren&amp;#39;t. I was
recently speaking with a friend at a big tech company. I was pitching
him on supporting what I&amp;#39;m building at Hunter. He said he really
wanted to help but his companies diversity plan, once you stripped
away the shiny paint was poaching from FANG (or is it FAAMG)
companies. The other thing I see is recruiting exclusively at &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34;
private schools and trying to grab as many &amp;#34;underserved&amp;#34; candidates as
possible. A third strategy involves counting everyone on your team for
diversity counts even if many of them aren&amp;#39;t really tech. Of course
the elite colleges play the same game. When you&amp;#39;ve got an incoming
class of let&amp;#39;s say 2000 and you&amp;#39;ve got 10 times that many applicants
with 4.0 GPAs and perfect test scores you can shape your class however
you want but it&amp;#39;s a zero sum game and doesn&amp;#39;t provide opportunity for
the masses.. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we want to solve these issues we have to deal with K12 and if
that&amp;#39;s the case it&amp;#39;s going to take at least 6 years maybe considerably
more before we really see results and that&amp;#39;s assuming we fix the
college capacity issues.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings me to CS for all. I&amp;#39;m a big believer in CS for All and
I&amp;#39;ve dedicated a lot of time and energy on bringing quality CS
education to the have nots but CS for All might not be the
answer. First, many of us believe that it&amp;#39;s not about turning everyone
into a software engineer. True, by exposing everyone to CS we&amp;#39;ll get a
larger pool working towards that end but the intent isn&amp;#39;t or at least
shouldn&amp;#39;t be as a feeder into the tech industry. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A bigger problem is ensuring that we indeed have quality CS for All
for all and that&amp;#39;s a real concern. Looking over the landscape here&amp;#39;s
what I&amp;#39;m seeing. Rich, well heeled schools are finding those few
really knowledgeable CS teachers and many of the poor schools are
getting quick and dirty training on some generic APCS-Principals
class. Dedicated hard working teachers who want to do a great job but
aren&amp;#39;t being given the time and resources to really learn CS and CS
pedagogy.  Now APCS-P can be a strong class or a weak one but in many
cases by going for the quick fix with a scripted class and then saying
&amp;#34;we&amp;#39;re done&amp;#34; is condemning those kids to sub standard CS. Even if
some do take CS1 in college my guess many will be underprepared and
many will drop. Even with a good APCS-P, the fact that no one is
paying attention to the complete pipeline and the transition from High
School to College and through the major will mean that we&amp;#39;re going to
lose many of the kids along the way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The answer? Good pre-service programs will help - that&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m so
bullish on the program we&amp;#39;re developing at Hunter. A bad preservice
program, however - one that is based on &amp;#34;you take it you teach it&amp;#34;
won&amp;#39;t prepare our teachers to prepare our kids. Even then, we&amp;#39;re not
going to really solve the problem until we deal with little things
like, oh, you know, poverty. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I might sound pessimistic. Maybe I am but it doesn&amp;#39;t change
anything. I&amp;#39;m going to do my best to affect positive change in
whatever circles I can be they large or small and many others are
doing the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All those jobs that aren&amp;#39;t coming to NY?  They&amp;#39;d have been filled
before any sensible fix to our NYC Tech pipeline problem yields fruit
anyway and would likely have displaced the current fringe population
rather than uplift them.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Amazon HQ2 in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 17:57:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-amazon-hq/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
That was the big tech news today. I know there was a good deal of
vocal outrage about the deal but to be honest I was pretty surprised
by the news. Normally deals like these get steamrolled through for
better or worse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have decidedly mixed feelings about this. On the one hand, I have no
problem with Amazon - I&amp;#39;ve got a bunch of former students working
there. Mostly in Seattle but at least one in NYC. On the other hand
there were a lot of things about the deal, none of them having to do
specifically with Amazon as a company that made me very uneasy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s go through these issues from minor to major.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, I&amp;#39;m against special corporate incentives. In one ear I keep
hearing that these were generic incentives are available to any
company but in the other ear I keep hearing about special concessions
for Amazon. I keep thinking about stadium and Olympic deals. Those are
generally driven by politicians and money men with huge egos and from
what I can tell they generally don&amp;#39;t end up helping the little guy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next we have backroom politics. Like so much in New York, it certainly
appeared that this was a back room Cuomo deal where the local
communities weren&amp;#39;t included in the process. It wreaks of Cuomo
Hubris and ego. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Third we have all the jobs. A recent poll indicated that residents
welcomed the fact that this deal would &amp;#34;create new jobs&amp;#34; but the truth
is that it would &amp;#34;create new jobs for outsiders who will come in and
replace you.&amp;#34; This isn&amp;#39;t a knock on Amazon but it&amp;#39;s probably the
truth. The history of hypergentrification is not one of uplifting the
poor into the middle class. It&amp;#39;s more like bring in the middle and
upper class from other communities and displace the poor. This would
likely be the case with this much demand for tech talent this quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The local colleges, specifically CUNY will not be able to up the flow
of tech graduates that quickly without a big infusion of resources and
that&amp;#39;s something that wasn&amp;#39;t included in the deal. It&amp;#39;s great that
Amazon is supporting HS CS but tech companies aren&amp;#39;t hiring kids out
of high school with a single introductory experience like
APCS-Principals. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since New York will not be able to supply the software engineers on a
dime the companies are going to bring them in from elsewhere. I
remember talking to a tech executive a few years ago and he was
telling me that he was going to have to &amp;#34;hire X software engineers in
the next five years&amp;#34; and that while he &amp;#34;would love for them to be New
Yorkers&amp;#34; he&amp;#39;d hire them from wherever he could get them. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Poor and working class people aren&amp;#39;t all of a sudden going to be
getting these high paying jobs. Sure, some will get into programs like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pursuit.org/&#34;&gt;Pursuit&lt;/a&gt; and get entry level coder jobs and the colleges will continue
to produce what they&amp;#39;re producing now and ramp up capacity as they are
able but a lot of people  who were here during the bad times are just
going to be forced out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day most of this won&amp;#39;t change a thing one way or the
other. LIC is already on the upswing and rents are going through the
roof. Companies will continue to need tech talent in NY and NY will
continue to scramble to try to fill the need. Amazon already has a
presence in NYC and if they want to avail themselves of the talent
that comes from and wants to move to NY they&amp;#39;ll continue to build
their footprint here even without HQ2.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me the takeaway is that we have to be much more aware of all our
residents and it is our obligation as a society to work to uplift
those who haven&amp;#39;t had the same opportunities as others. That means
really looking hard at diversity, equity, and things like
gentrification. It means not just bringing in jobs without having a
plan and a path for those at the bottom of the economic ladder to
climb up into those jobs. It means working with the communities for
their and New York&amp;#39;s benefit and not making deals that sound good and
might be good for New York as a whole but get there by amputating the
parts that we just don&amp;#39;t want to deal with.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tech or the Teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Every morning one of the first things I do is quickly glance at my
emails and other notifications. I really should wait until I&amp;#39;m more
awake but old habits die hard.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As some of you know over the past couple of years I&amp;#39;ve been making a
series of &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; and related post on using my editor of choice,
Emacs. I&amp;#39;ve done 48 videos, have over 2500 subscribers on
YouTube and people seem to find some value from the series.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning one of my emails was a new comment on one of my videos:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanks for not describing a single key combination and how that fits
into basic usage of org mode.  I was going to subscribe but if all
your videos are going to be about showing off how fast you are at
typing emacs commands on your annoyingly noisy keyborad, then no
thanks!﻿
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My first reaction was &amp;#34;you know, you could have said something like
&amp;#39;if you slow down an actually say the keys it would be much easier to
follow and would be more valuable&amp;#39; and it would be much better received&amp;#34; but
then I started to think about instructional videos in general. I
started to make these videos for my students. I thought they might be
helpful and then found that the Emacs community by and large liked
them. They&amp;#39;re not teaching anything deep or complicated just how I use
a programmable editor. Even so, I was reminded by this comment about
the limitations of videos and ed tech in general.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Videos provide some nice features - you can watch them at any time,
you can pause and replay, and in some cases you can watch at super
speeds. What you can&amp;#39;t do is slow the video down and most importantly
you can&amp;#39;t ask questions or interact with the instructor. You can leave
comments if the video is on a platform like YouTube but that&amp;#39;s pretty
limited.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if this was a class, we would have been able to
interact and I as the instructor would have had a much better chance
to make sure this &amp;#34;student&amp;#34; was up to speed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this wasn&amp;#39;t a class. I don&amp;#39;t have the time to teach tools
like Emacs in class and since it is a mechanical skill, it can be
offloaded to a video. The video has the ancillary benefit of living on
and being discoverable and viewable by the public at large. This is a
good thing. Videos are tech and tech scales. Unfortunately, good
education doesn&amp;#39;t.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Videos are tech and tech is the rage. Lots of people are working hard
to get more tech in front of our kids - usually at the expense of
having a great teacher. This is something we don&amp;#39;t need. Technology is
nice but I&amp;#39;d rather have my kids in a small class with a knowledgable
teacher and a piece of chalk than all the tech in the world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a computer science guy and a computer science teacher I think it&amp;#39;s
good to remind myself that tech is cool but a good teacher is way cooler.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of
Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching
career, then our family&amp;#39;s West Coast swing was a nice way to pull
down the curtain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she&amp;#39;s interning at
Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south
to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle
for a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, while out there, why not see if some of the StuyCS family
wanted to get together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I knew I had a lot of former students out on the West Coast but still, I was
overwhelmed and humbled by the number of people who wanted to spend
time and catch up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We kicked things off at Bloomberg Beta thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/roybahat&#34;&gt;Roy Bahat.&lt;/a&gt; Roy was
never actually my student but we&amp;#39;ve gotten to know each other over the
years and I value him as a friend and advisor. Roy provided the food
and the space and about 60 former students + a few old timers showed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple of days later, we had a lunch meetup for the Googlers:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/google.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/google.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/google.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and a happy hour at Facebook (sorry, no picture). Then in Seattle, a
nice dinner to close things out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Between these events there were some lunches, a barbecue at Batya&amp;#39;s
place  and even a drive by visit with a former student at
Microsoft. Overall, it was easily over 100 students over the course of
the week or so we were out there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve often said that one of the things I&amp;#39;m proudest of is helping to
build the StuyCS family. A community of people spanning decades. Over
the week, we had events mixing students from the mid 90&amp;#39;s to
youngsters currently in college and on their internships.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Seeing all these people meeting and supporting each other gave me a
&amp;#34;proud pappa&amp;#34; type feeling even though I didn&amp;#39;t do any more than set
the stage for them getting together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the week, the conversations were also great - not the straight
tech ones, but the ones that really made me proud of the crew. From
Seth talking about how to better get good CS Ed to more kids, to PJ
discussing why he feels it&amp;#39;s so important to be an active mentor to
his young programmers and how to get them to be real thinkers, to
Mike, Sam, Kathy, and Leo discussing the disconnect between
privileged families and those struggling to get by.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What more could a teacher want than their former students being both
happy in their lives and careers as well as good people seeking to
make the world better for everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The only thing that made me sad about the trip is that with all the
big events, I really didn&amp;#39;t get a chance to spend the time I wanted
with everyone. I hope to do better next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I&amp;#39;ve now been at Hunter for one semester and things will really
ramp up in the Fall. I&amp;#39;m still a proud part of our StuyCS family and if
being a part of pulling it together is the legacy I left, I can live
with that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The trip was a nice symbolic way to lower the curtain on act 1. I&amp;#39;m
counting on the StuyCS family and all the other players to help so
that we can make sure act 2 is a success and we can build something
similar for more young people throughout the city and perhaps the country.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hillary and Student Loans</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I read over Hillary&amp;#39;s briefing on her initiative on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hillaryclinton.com/briefing/factsheets/2016/06/27/hillary-clintons-initiative-on-technology-innovation/&#34;&gt;Technology and Innovation&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have
my doubts. My feeling is that she&amp;#39;s pretty much aligned with the
current administration education wise and the current administration
has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public
education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much
like some of the others, I don&amp;#39;t want to get into that today. I want
to focus on one specific part of her plan. The part that defers
college debt for up to 3 years for founders and entrepreneurs. This
sounds great but is this really a good thing?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some initial responses from the education community is &amp;#34;what about
young teachers, don&amp;#39;t they deserve some help on college debt? What
about nurses?…&amp;#34; and of course they&amp;#39;re right. On the other hand, I
don&amp;#39;t want people to go into teaching for 2 or 3 years just to get
some debt relief benefit and then jump ship. That&amp;#39;s the Teach for
America model that I feel has become so harmful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But again, that&amp;#39;s not where I&amp;#39;m going with this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s start with &amp;#34;who are these founders?&amp;#34; I don&amp;#39;t have any hard data
but I have read a couple of recent pieces that indicate that founders
right out of college are typically from well to do backgrounds. This
of course makes sense. A kid up to his or her eyes in debt from a poor
background. No savings, no property, likely a family, that is siblings
and parents who are also treading water can ill afford to take a big
financial risk. A kid from a monied family? Much more so.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes Hillary&amp;#39;s plan a boon for the wealthy but not so
much for the people we need to give a hand up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, this plan talks about the founders and only says it will
&amp;#34;explore similar incentives&amp;#34;  for early employees, citing &amp;#34;10 to 20.&amp;#34;
This doesn&amp;#39;t seem right to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now let&amp;#39;s look further into the benefits. I don&amp;#39;t know what the
success and failure rates are for startups. I&amp;#39;ve seen a bunch of
figures including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
90% of startups fail within the first three years
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Three out of four startups fail
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of 10 startups, 3 or 4 totally fail, 3 or 4 break even and the
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
others turn a profit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know where the truth lies but I&amp;#39;d imagine that the success
rate for startup by a recent college graduate, wet behind the ears is
probably higher than for a more season professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hillary&amp;#39;s plan defers debt for up to three years. If any of the
failure numbers cited above are near correct it means that these kids
will have burned through up to three years with the experience of a
failed startup to show for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve always advised my students, all things being equal, start at a
big or mid size company, develop your chops, learn how they do it,
further build out your network, and then go out and do your
thing. Most kids are better served not going directly from college to
their first startup.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. A plan that makes for great &amp;#34;press release&amp;#34; but is it
really addressing the issues?
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>