<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PD on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pd/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (PD)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 12:29:06 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pd/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching CS  - all the educators to all the grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-cs-in-all-the-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 12:29:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-cs-in-all-the-grades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m kicking off a couple of exciting summer projects next week and
it&amp;#39;s been pointed out to me a couple of times that I&amp;#39;ll be working
with educators at every level to help them to deliver CS instruction
to students at every level. What an opportunity to be a part of and
learn from - working with every level of teacher for every level of
student. I&amp;#39;m part of the teaching teams but I think I&amp;#39;m also going to
learn a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, how is this happening? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One project I&amp;#39;m working on, entering its second year is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; on
computational thinking in the early grades. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yadavaman&#34;&gt;Aman Yadav&lt;/a&gt; and I, with the
support of the Robin Hood Foundation will be working with primary
grade teachers to develop experience that both teach computational
thinking and use CT to support the core subject areas. As we had last
time, we&amp;#39;ll have both working teachers and pre-service teachers - that
is, Hunter students close to earning their teaching degrees and
certifications. In the Fall, the pre-service teachers will student
teach under the supervision of the working teachers in our
program. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Based on what we did last year I&amp;#39;m convinced that this years cohort
will get a lot out of the experience but I&amp;#39;m also convinced that the
workshop still faces the limitations of any professional development
style training - short duration, one shot, and no long term
support. PD can be valuable but I&amp;#39;m 100% convinced it&amp;#39;s not the answer
in terms of preparing CS teachers. At the end of the workshop, our
teachers will have learned something about CT, be more comfortable
with it, and have designed some lessons that they&amp;#39;ll deliver in the
Fall. It&amp;#39;s a start but it&amp;#39;s not the end. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The game changer brings me to the other group of people
participating - four full time Hunter Faculty members. They all teach
in our School of Education. The aim is to see where we can add CT to
our pre-service classes. This moves the needle. If we do it right,
soon enough, every Hunter College primary grade teaching candidate
will be learning about Computational Thinking in their required Ed
classes. That&amp;#39;s how you do it - get it into pre-service.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that has me working with pre-service and in-service teachers as
well as full time research faculty. That&amp;#39;s a lot of levels of
educators but it&amp;#39;s not all the grades.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the other project we&amp;#39;re kicking off on Monday and one that I
plan to write a lot about over the next month and into next year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re finally kicking off our Computer Science Teacher certification
program. We&amp;#39;ve got a cohort of a little over 20 teachers that will
take part in a month long intensive followed by more coursework in
the Fall. When they&amp;#39;re done, they&amp;#39;ll be among the first certified
computer science teachers in New York State. The cohort consists
mostly of High School teachers but we&amp;#39;ve got some middle school in
there as well. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This too is a game changer. We&amp;#39;re not giving a curriculum to follow or
scripts to copy but rather we&amp;#39;re teaching serious CS and how to teach
it. Of course it doesn&amp;#39;t hurt that the cohort is comprised of strong,
experienced teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there it is - all the levels of teachers to all the levels of
students. I&amp;#39;m super excited to be part of both of these game changing
projects and can&amp;#39;t wait for Monday when we get to work.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent this past Saturday morning up at the Microsoft building in
Times Square. What was I doing there? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aankit?lang=en&#34;&gt;Aankit Patel&lt;/a&gt; invited me to check
out the professional development that he and his team organized for
the teachers involved in the assorted CSforAllNYC programs that his
office runs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of great things going on. I was only able to stay for a couple of
hours but I spent some time in two rooms run by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, a room of &lt;a href=&#34;https://bjc.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;BJC&lt;/a&gt;
teachers, a group working with &lt;a href=&#34;https://p5js.org&#34;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;, one doing physical computing and
a bunch more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While there was good content all around I was really impressed with
the sense of community in many of the rooms. One of the hardest parts
of being a computer science teacher in K12 is that you&amp;#39;re frequently
the only CS teacher in your school. That can be an awfully lonely
existence. It&amp;#39;s hard to be the only teacher. No one to bounce lesson
ideas off of or to debrief with and if you leave your school they&amp;#39;re
left in the lurch. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s simply amazing that all these NYC teachers have opportunities
like this past weekends PD and the communty it provides. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, teachers who are not part of city programs like
SEP or TEALS don&amp;#39;t have these opportunities and at Hunter we&amp;#39;re trying
to do our piece to help solve that problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few months ago I wrote about our plans to roll out once a month
professional development sessions for CTLE hours specifically aimed at
teachers who are ready for the next step. Those who are already
comfortable with the first courses and student experiences. I&amp;#39;m
describing the sessions as being for high school teachers teaching
APCS-A, similar or beyond.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Were hosting our first session on December 13th. There will be a
couple of presentations or activities to get us started but the bulk
of the time will be about planning the rest of the sessions which will
run until the end of the school year and the hope is that we will
cover both content beyond the basics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re a public school CS teacher in NYC (and need CTLE hours)
and you&amp;#39;re ready for something more advanced than the usual PD
opportunities, why don&amp;#39;t you join us. Just sign up &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/forms/FJDyCx7qFec1yPjr1&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Space is
limited so if we fill, we&amp;#39;ll add you to the waitlist and we&amp;#39;ll work on
trying to find a bigger space to acomodate more teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to getting this thing started!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>