<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>computational thinking on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/computational-thinking/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (computational thinking)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 16:32:17 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/computational-thinking/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Computation Thinking a new idea or a new opportunity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-ct-new/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 16:32:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/is-ct-new/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Saw this earlier today.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Kind of
works, doesn’t it?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Does every discipline do this — decide that
the way experts think in that discipline is a special kind of
“thinking” or “reasoning” or “literacy” that everyone really needs and
that we should be teaching to all our children? &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/cvNvpOMjZZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/cvNvpOMjZZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Mark Guzdial (@guzdial) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial/status/1165624814759043073?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August
25, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EC0hlfKXsAIjlK9?format=jpg&amp;amp;amp;name=medium&#34;&gt;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EC0hlfKXsAIjlK9?format=jpg&amp;amp;amp;name=medium&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a talk Mark gave last year, he also talked about &amp;#34;historical
thinking&amp;#34; and other &amp;#34;thinkings.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This relates to something I&amp;#39;ve thought for a long time about CS and
computational thinking in the early grades. Computational Thinking,
whatever that actually is seems to be the route that CS is taking in
the early grades. Young students aren&amp;#39;t going to be coding up
quicksorts and many elementary schools don&amp;#39;t have the hardware
resources needed anyway. Still, by approaching things through the CT
lens maybe we can lay down a foundation for the future. Along the way,
maybe some of these CT ideas can support students as they explore
other subject areas. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is all old ground for CT but what&amp;#39;s this new opportunity?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, as it turns out, some of what we&amp;#39;d now consider computational
thinking has been going on in elementary schools for years. It&amp;#39;s been
going on under the guise of &amp;#34;logic,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;problem solving,&amp;#34; and other
headings. More often than not, teachers in better resourced schools
where there there is less standardized test pressure, teachers can
spend time on these. There are also CT concepts like pattern matching
and abstraction that are present in elementary school lessons but not
necessarily labeled as such.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe computational thinking isn&amp;#39;t all brand new. Maybe we&amp;#39;re
rebranding some ideas from other &amp;#34;thinkings.&amp;#34; Problem solving and
logic belong to many fields. This is all okay. All
those other &amp;#34;thinkings&amp;#34; are in established fields. The way we do
history, math, science, etc. in our schools is well established and
it&amp;#39;s left us, in many cases, with a tale of two cities. The haves and
the have nots.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we have CS and CT and all the related buzz. Even if the CT we can
do in elementary schools isn&amp;#39;t new, even if it overlaps with
historical thinking or the others, we now have a new opportunity to
change up how we do things in the early grades and maybe we can reduce
the distance between those have and have nots. Let&amp;#39;s see if we can
take advantage of this opportunity.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Thinking  in Primary Grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 17:54:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last week I spent a couple of days as part of a team running
professional development for a
group of pre and in service elementary school teachers. Two days
talking about computational thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wait a minute - elementary school teachers? I&amp;#39;m a high school guy
pretending to be a college guy. My extensive experience with
elementary school education is that I raised two kids and I don&amp;#39;t
think I messed them up too much. I don&amp;#39;t know anything about
elementary education!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How&amp;#39;d I ever get myself into this???
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
About a year ago my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt&#34;&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt; was encouraging me to apply for a grant to
explore computational thinking in elementary schools with the Robin Hood Foundation. I was
hesitant since elementary school is not my bag but since I also knew some
of the Robin Hood players I figured let&amp;#39;s see where things go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, coincidentally, I started talking to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yadavaman&#34;&gt;Aman Yadav&lt;/a&gt;. I had followed Aman
online for a number of years and was hoping to find an opportunity to
meet him somewhere down the line. Long story short, the two of us
decide to apply to for the Robin Hood Foundation grant together. I
felt much more comfortable than going solo since Aman had already done
some great CT work with Detroit teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, in spite of my insistence of not knowing primary ed,
Robin Hood decided to support our efforts. Last week, Aman and I,
joined by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/saraevogel&#34;&gt;Sarah Vogel&lt;/a&gt; who has also done some good work with CT in
primary grades and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CSEdPhil&#34;&gt;Phil Sands&lt;/a&gt; who is currently doing grad work with
Aman we ran two days of PD for 10 pre service and 10 in service
teachers. It was a mix of activities to explore concepts such as
debugging, decomposition, abstraction, and brainstorming on how the
teachers could bring these concepts to their classrooms in support of
core academic areas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Towards the end, I was sitting in on one group of teachers
energetically discussing how they could share what they learned with
their school. I then moved to another group where they were discussing
how core ideas from our exercises could be adapted to support teaching
writing. Really inspiring.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aman and I will be getting together with the pre and in service
teachers again in late August with the plan of developing concrete lessons
that both draw out CT concepts and support core subjects. I&amp;#39;m not
sure if Phil will be able to come out to join us but he&amp;#39;ll be involved
in the project for the long haul. We&amp;#39;re hoping Sara can also be as
involved moving forward but Sara&amp;#39;s very much in demand and very
busy so here&amp;#39;s hoping that her schedule permits it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the end the plan is to make everything the teachers develop
available to the greater CS Education community but we&amp;#39;re going for a
bigger win. If all of this works, the plan is to get some of these
practices into Hunter&amp;#39;s required pre-service classes. Given the number
of teachers we prepare at Hunter, that could really move the needle.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Working with elementary school teachers is new to me and I&amp;#39;m having
fun with all of this. Super appreciative to have partners like the
Robin Hood Foundation, Aman, Sara, and Phil as well as the teachers
who took time out of their summers to come down to Hunter and work on
this with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>