<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hunter on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/hunter/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (hunter)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 07:41:29 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/hunter/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter&#39;s first Honors CS Cohort</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/first-daedalus-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 07:41:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/first-daedalus-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Almost four and a half years ago I left Stuyvesant and joined Hunter
College. One of the initiatives I was charged with was the creation of
a computer science honors program - the Daedalus scholars. Now, a
little over four years later, our first cohort is graduating.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m super proud of that first cohort and what we&amp;#39;ve collectively been
building. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I joined Hunter at the end of January 2016 - a month after college
applications had closed. This meant that we had to build our first
cohort after the fact. Nobody applied to Hunter to be a part of the
Daedalus scholars because we didn&amp;#39;t exist. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, by looking at the students who had already applied to Hunter we
found a few that were interested and qualified. We lost a few along
the way - a student who really wanted an engineering program, one who
had already conditionally been accepted to another school but took our
money for the semester (I really hate it when people exploit a system
like this but that&amp;#39;s another story), one who really didn&amp;#39;t know what
CS was and ended up not liking the subject, and one who really wanted
to leave the city. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During our first semester, some Macaulay students found out about our
program and wanted to join so we padded our numbers with a small
number of them. Overall we ended up with a small group of 12.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I&amp;#39;m proud of all of them for what they did at Hunter and
for what lies ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, four years later we get hundreds of applicants including a
growing number from outside the city and are taking in many more great
students. I don&amp;#39;t know the other colleges that our first cohort
members were accepted to but now we&amp;#39;re competing for students with
Stony Brook, NYU, RIT, and in some cases bigger &amp;#34;names.&amp;#34; My goal was
for us to become the best value CS and the best CS in NYC and we&amp;#39;re
well on our way. with the first cohort, we prototyped some activities
and events that have evolved into staples - tech mentoring, codefest,
interview prep and more. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first cohort led the way and I&amp;#39;m super proud of them. Now they&amp;#39;ll
become our first graduates and continue to be resource for both each
other and future Hunter CS students. This is now the start of another
endeavor - it took decades to create the StuyCS Mafia and now I get to
repeat the process with HunterCS  but this time, since I know what&amp;#39;s
to come I can enjoy the show as it unfolds.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter Codefest 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codefest-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 13:41:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codefest-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Two of the challenges faced by young computer science students are
finding the time to build independent projects for their portfolios
and getting feedback from and networking with tech professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enter Hunter Codefest 2020
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;
.flip {
    -webkit-transform: rotate(180deg);
    -moz-transform: rotate(180deg);
    -o-transform: rotate(180deg);
    -ms-transform: rotate(180deg);
    transform: rotate(180deg);
}
&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left flip&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/codefest.jpg&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left flip&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/google.jpg&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter, like most colleges has a Fall semester that runs from late
August through the end of Decemeber and a Spring semester that starts
at the end of January and runs through late may. There&amp;#39;s generally
around a month between the two. Sometimes a student can take one of
the few courses offered during this &amp;#34;Winter semester&amp;#34; but more often
than not the time is wasted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Hunter, students can do a number of things during this break. Some get short term
mini internships, others take part in our tech bootcamps. Now, they
can all participate in Codefest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We launched in late December at the end of finals. Students are given
a theme and form groups. They then have a month to build a
project. It&amp;#39;s a great opportunity to learn how to work on a team and
explore tools that you wouldn&amp;#39;t normally use in a regular CS class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Friday was the payoff. We all gathered at GoogleNYC for a big
celebration. Each group was set up at a table with professional
Software Engineers. Mostly Googlers but wa also invited some outside
guests. They&amp;#39;d then spend time with discussing the project. After a
while, the Googlers would rotate to another project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rinse and repeat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/gil.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Current Googler and Hunter CS grad Gil advising our current students.&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Current Googler and Hunter CS grad Gil advising our current students.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/sarah.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;My former Stuy student and current Googler Sarah doing the same.&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;My former Stuy student and current Googler Sarah doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards we had some demos and then a big networking session where
our Hunter CS students got to spend more time getting to know and
getting advice from a host of Googlers and other software engineers
while enjoying refreshments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not everyone could make it due to class but we had a pretty strong
turnout.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;flip&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/everyone.jpg&#34; width=&#34;75%&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our student organizers did most of the heavy lifting and made the
whole event work from start to finish. Here are Leo, Angela, Shariar,
and Tracey. Our two other organizers, Miguel and Kun couldn&amp;#39;t make it
as Miguel was travelling and Kun had an interview for an internship.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/organizers.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Our organizers&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Our organizers&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Special thanks to Brendan and hist team of Googlers who helped make
this happen. I also want to say thanks to the dozen or so of my former
students currently at Google who stopped by to help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everyone was super impressed with what the students produced. It was
a great event and it&amp;#39;ll be even better next year.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College Winter Codefest 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 17:34:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s great to see how much Hunter CS has developed since starting here
there years ago. The latest endeavor is Winter Codefest. During the
fall I was approached by one of my students who had asked an older
Hunter CS student about their portfolio and found that the senior&amp;#39;s
portfolio was lacking. This student said we should do something to
help encourage younger students to build that portfolio. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The result was Winter Codefest. A team of organizers was formed and
they came up with the plan. Have students register teams right after
Fall finals and have teams work on independent projects over the
course of January before the Spring semester started. We&amp;#39;d then have an
event where everyone would show off their work. We decided to limit
participants to my Daedalus scholars this time around but planned from
the get go to make it Hunter wide in the future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended up with about 24 participants spanning all three Daedalus
cohorts with most of the participants in the second year group. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Due to the scheduling we couldn&amp;#39;t hold the end of competition event
until today. A bunch of us gathered along with some of our friends
from the tech community to review the projects, network, and generally
talk tech. All in all the event was a real success. All the
participants learned new  technologies and now have one more show
piece to talk about in interviews.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year was unquestionably a success and it&amp;#39;s going to be a bigger
one next year. The CS department is working on creating 1 and 2 credit
projects courses that will be offered during the winter session. This
will enable students to take the courses to develop a Winterfest
project with the support of a class around it. We&amp;#39;re also going to
make the event available to all Hunter CS students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s really exciting to be part of developing programs like Hunter
College CS, Programs that can be super transformative for young New
Yorkers. It&amp;#39;s even more exciting when your students take active
leadership roles and help make our programs even more special.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a
feeling of community. Students aren&amp;#39;t on campus every day and come
from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&amp;#39;t have
a CS &amp;#34;hang out&amp;#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&amp;#39;re
scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my
honors students. The first two cohorts were a single class in
size. Even though some dormed and some commuted, they were all
together in my class twice a week. This year, we&amp;#39;ve close to doubled
in size and about half of my students came in with a good deal of
prior CS knowledge. The result is that I have two different classes of
honors students and we are never all together unless it&amp;#39;s for a
special event.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, we&amp;#39;ve got one of my favorites coming up. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In two weeks, I&amp;#39;ll be taking about half my students up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;Catskills
Conf&lt;/a&gt;. An event that I describe as light tech conference with a focus
on creativity and diversity meets summer camp. I&amp;#39;ve written about the
event in in each of the past three years (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/%0A&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/%0A&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskills-2017/%0A&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;) and also
about the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/%0A&#34;&gt;knitting for charity&lt;/a&gt; event that Devorah runs during the
conference weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event and if you&amp;#39;re anywhere near the Hudson Valley
region you should &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, it&amp;#39;s a great first conference for the students. It only has
one track so no choices and the talks look really interesting this
year. Some of the ones I&amp;#39;m looking forward to are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Designing for Access first
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Behind the Tech: Emoji
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Leaning into uncertainty
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The full schedule is &lt;a href=&#34;https://catskillsconf.com/schedule/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But also mixed in are activities like blacksmithing
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/blacksmith.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and a live bird of prey show
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/BOP.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also hikes that show off the beauty of Fall in the Hudson
Valley
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature1.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature2.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature3.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rather than having the kids spread out in random hotel rooms we&amp;#39;re all
in a camp style bunkhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/bunkhouse.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The weekend is spent  living together along with technologists and
other creative types from NYC, the Hudson Valley and everywhere else. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my favorite parts is at the end of each evening when we all
hang out by the campfire. Hunter CS students, company founders,
software engineers, designers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/campfire.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event overall and a great event to build community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said before, if you&amp;#39;re in the area, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>