<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>csta on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (csta)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 19:32:17 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Conferences - CSTA 2020 part 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 19:32:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that CSTA 2020&amp;#39;s over time for some more thoughts on the
conference and also on virtual conferences in general.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I only got to attend a couple of sessions as I was working my CS
teacher certification program but a nice feature is that I was able to
hop in and out of sessions without disturbing or disrupting. You can&amp;#39;t
really do that in person. I&amp;#39;m also looking forward to when they
release the sessions for later viewing. In addition to not being able
to get to everything I wanted, my session overlapped with Nifty
Assignments - always a fun show. Now I still get to see it!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Speaking of my session, JonAlf and I had fun but I would have much
preferred doing it in person. After a few minor hiccups, Hopin worked
perfectly but it suffers the same problem as Zoom when your kids turn
off their cameras. I didn&amp;#39;t really feel connected to the audience,
Sure, there was the chat, but with the number of people in the
session, it flew by way to fast. We could have invited a few attendees
&amp;#34;up on stage&amp;#34; but that would have made the dual screen share
smaller. None of this was a deal breaker but the tech still has some
limitations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, sessions worked but had some pluses and minuses against in person
and the networking feature I described &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/virtual-conf/&#34;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; was a clear winner so
what&amp;#39;s next - the exhibits. Exhibits didn&amp;#39;t work for me. I can&amp;#39;t say
why. I think it&amp;#39;s because I like strolling the exhibit hall and just
chatting with both attendees and company reps. I generally don&amp;#39;t like
the formal booth talk and that&amp;#39;s all we got here. Nothing wrong with
the booth presentation but it&amp;#39;s just normally not my thing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other thing missing and it&amp;#39;s related to those exhibition hall
chats was the hallway track. That was the biggest loss. The informal
and semi-formal meetups. Impromptu lunches and dinners and one offs
that just happen. Can&amp;#39;t really have that with the current virtual
tools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A final point was that when I go to a conference I get to both explore
a new part of the world and I get to turn off the outside world for a
couple of days - I can just enjoy the conference. You can&amp;#39;t do that if
it&amp;#39;s virtual but you get other advantages - no cost of travel and the
ability to attend at all your schedule doesn&amp;#39;t allow you to get away
for half a week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the verdict? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The 2020 edition of the CSTA conference was a big win in my book. I
hope we can do it in person next year but even if we can, it would be
great to offer at least parts virtually to make at least sessions
available to a wider audience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Either way, I&amp;#39;m there.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Conferences - CSTA 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/virtual-conf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 16:27:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/virtual-conf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t supposed to be in NYC this week. I was supposed to be in
Arlington Virginia with around one thousand of my CS Teacher friends
at CSTA2020. Devorah was going to spend the days at the GitHub booth
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blanket-statement-2020/&#34;&gt;teaching knitting&lt;/a&gt; and I was going to do a GitHub workshop and
generally enjoy the show
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course nobody&amp;#39;s traveling these days and CSTA2020 is running
remote. This is my second virtual conference as I attended parts of MongoDB
world a few weeks ago.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m still forming my opinion on CSTA2020 but I thought I&amp;#39;d share my
thoughts in progress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, virtual conferences aren&amp;#39;t the same as in person - they
can&amp;#39;t be. For me, CSTA is a person first conference rather than
session first. That is, I get most of my value from the hallway
track. That&amp;#39;s not to say I don&amp;#39;t enjoy the sessions, it&amp;#39;s just that
for me personally, I get more from the chats than from the talks. By
contrast, for me SIGCSE is more about the sessions. There are a few
reasons why things fall this way but there neither here nor there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, since there can&amp;#39;t really be a hallway track, I was wondering how
CSTA2020 would feel. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR - it&amp;#39;s different but still pretty great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Keynote&amp;#39;s are keynotes wether virtual or in person so not much to say
in them so let&amp;#39;s move to the sessions. CSTA is using hopin.to and it&amp;#39;s
working pretty well. MongoDB used another platform that seemed to be
more glitchy. Hopin&amp;#39;s been working pretty seamlessly for me. I&amp;#39;m
presenting tomorrow so we&amp;#39;ll see if that changes my view. None of the
sessions I attended brought any participants &amp;#34;on stage&amp;#34; so
interactions were through the chat. It worked pretty well but at times
there was so much chatter that things flew off the screen before you
could read them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, I&amp;#39;m digging the plaltform. Not the same as in person but it&amp;#39;s
a good approximation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The vendor / exhibit area worked pretty much the same way so not much
to say there. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall the interface is pretty smooth. Navigation could be smoother
and so could user search but overall, pretty nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, where are we at? We&amp;#39;ve got a pretty good platform for sessions
with decent navigation, chat, and messaging but what about that
hallway track. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We don&amp;#39;t have one but we have a pretty cool alternative. Hopin has a
networking feature. When you drop in, you&amp;#39;re matched with someone else
randomly for a 5 minute video chat. After five minutes, its over. You
can come back in and chat with someone else or be done with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really like this feature.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For someone asocial and somewhat awkward like me, it&amp;#39;s great. Five
minutes isn&amp;#39;t too long to get awkward but it&amp;#39;s enough for a brief chat
and you can follow up later. The randomness lets you meet new people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In some ways it&amp;#39;s better than in person. I frequently fly solo at
conferences. At this point I know a decent amount of people but when
at a new conference, it&amp;#39;s hard to break in. The reason is that many
colleges or schools send groups of teachers and they cluster together
making it hard for an individual to join in. I see it and fee it all
the time, With this platform, you&amp;#39;re dumped in one on one - no worries
about cliques. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the verdict. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m loving the networking feature and liking the overall tool. I hope
CSTA&amp;#39;s in person next year but I&amp;#39;ll be a happy attendee even if we
remain remote.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA Awards 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-awards-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 11:46:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-awards-2020/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m guessing that pretty much everyone who stops by this blog knows
about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://csteachers.org/&#34;&gt;CSTA&lt;/a&gt; (Computer Science Teacher&amp;#39;s Association) and most of
you probably know about some awards they, well, award. Just in case, I
thought I&amp;#39;d share.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are three awards, two of which are open for nominations /
applications now. If you know someone deserving, nominate them. I&amp;#39;m
guessing students don&amp;#39;t really know about the Cutler-Bell award so if
you have any deserving students, please share the info with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Champions of CS Awards
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tell us about a student, educator, administrator, or organization that
has achieved something in computer science this past year for the
opportunity to be recognized as a 2019 Champion of Computer Science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Champions of Computer Science Awards identify and promote
students, teachers, administrators, and organizations who have made a
significant impact to improve access to and the quality of CS
education. These awards are presented by CSTA and Code.org.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nominations are due Oct. 21, 2019.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Link to award site:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cvent.com/c/abstracts/b2b495a4-4caf-4ed5-88b1-954d5a605b24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cvent.com/c/abstracts/b2b495a4-4caf-4ed5-88b1-954d5a605b24&#34;&gt;https://www.cvent.com/c/abstracts/b2b495a4-4caf-4ed5-88b1-954d5a605b24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Cutler-Bell Prize
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The ACM/CSTA Cutler-Bell Prize in High School Computing is a prize
designed to recognize talented high school students intending to
continue their higher education in the areas of computer science or
technology. The program seeks to promote and encourage the field of
computer science, as well as to empower young and aspiring learners to
pursue computing challenges outside of the traditional classroom
environment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Up to four winners will be selected annually and each will be awarded
a $10,000 prize which will be administered through the financial aid
department at the university the student will attend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Applications are due Jan. 12, 2020.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Link to application / site:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cvent.com/c/abstracts/e90beaf8-9035-4e10-862e-55a8a056f080&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cvent.com/c/abstracts/e90beaf8-9035-4e10-862e-55a8a056f080&#34;&gt;https://www.cvent.com/c/abstracts/e90beaf8-9035-4e10-862e-55a8a056f080&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
CS Teaching Excellence Awards
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The CS Teaching Excellence Awards, sponsored by CSTA and Infosys
Foundation USA, are designed to recognize outstanding teaching by K–12
computer science teachers. Winners demonstrate their excellent work
inspiring students to explore the computer science field; effectively
engage students in learning rigorous, standards-aligned, computer
science content; and a focus on broadening participation of
underrepresented students in computing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Applications open the spring of 2020.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 11:23:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, I got back from CSTA2019 and promptly got a summer cold which laid
me up for the past couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Phoenix was beautiful even with it being unbearably hot at times and
it&amp;#39;s a place I think I&amp;#39;d like to visit again when it&amp;#39;s a bit cooler. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I said in an earlier post that for me, CSTA is typically more of a
person conference and less of a session conference and that held true
again. I missed a few sessions that I originally wanted to attend
because I was involved in really good conversations in the exhibit
hall and before I knew it, the session was over and done. I can&amp;#39;t say
that I regret sticking with the conversations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, for the sessions, I don&amp;#39;t have much to say. I do wish it was easier
to glean information from the session descriptions. Even sessions with
lengthy descriptions left me with some question and given that
sessions were an hour long I wish some had more clarity. Specifically,
there were a good number of sessions on AI and ML but often was left
wondering if the sessions were more about doing cool problems with
some AI engine or api and real world data or if it was really about
learning about AI and ML and how to teach them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The last session I attended was &amp;#34;Nifty Assignments&amp;#34; and that was an
interesting contrast to the SIGCSE session of the same name. Most notably at SIGCSE
the assignments are generally for a college level CS1 or CS2 but these
spanned K12. You can check out all of the assignments &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/cstaniftyassignments/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The one
that I found particularly interesting was Dale Reed and Joe Hummel&amp;#39;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/cstaniftyassignments/home/2019/reed-hummel-letter-frequency&#34;&gt;lesson&lt;/a&gt; which, from a CS point of view is similar to a set of lessons
I&amp;#39;ve been doing for a few years (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-07-rot13-gateway/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;). I think it&amp;#39;s worth looking at
both assignments to contrast how you can have very different
approaches and emphases with similar core material.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I did a session with my partner in crime, JonAlf on using GitHub as a
web presence. I think this approach could be a good way to introduce
students and teachers to Git and GitHub in a low friction manner. It&amp;#39;s
a good first step to using GitHub for program development. You
can use the GitHub web page to update a web page time and again and
each time leave a little comment about what you&amp;#39;ve done. It turns out
this is just a commit message - just like &amp;#34;real&amp;#34; programming with git.
I can&amp;#39;t speak to how good the session was - you&amp;#39;ll have to ask the
attendees. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m thinking of proposing a full blown workshop for next year&amp;#39;s CSTA
conference that goes through both how I use GitHub and also models the
process I use to bring my students from novice to comfortable user.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moving from the sessions, this year CSTA added a poster
session. Unfortunately, the posters went up shortly before the session and came
down right after and since I couldn&amp;#39;t get to the posters during the
official session I couldn&amp;#39;t really take them in beyond a passing
glance. I&amp;#39;m hoping that next year the posters go up early and stay up
for the duration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some notes on the vendors area - wow - it was a far cry from two years
ago where there were just a handful in a hall. I think I heard that
there were around 60. There were the usual suspects - Google and
Microsoft, curriculum providers like CodeHS, BJC,  and PLTW, lots of robotics
stuff and organizations like NCWIT and the College Board. I was there
with the GitHub contingent so I spent most of my time at the
booth. The nice thing is that while I was there to talk to people
about GitHub I was free to give the real deal - my experience - the
good parts and the pain points. Also had plenty of time to talk CS and
CS Education in general.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d also like to mention Devorah&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;Blanket Statement&lt;/a&gt;
project. Crowdsourcing knitting a blanket for a child in need. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;And the total is ... 44 blocks crafted during &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CSTA2019?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#CSTA2019&lt;/a&gt; . 3 are not pictured as I still have to finish them off. Look for the final, finished product early next week. If anyone still has blocks, message me for my snail mail. Thank you all! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ZLDcEEK9ig&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZLDcEEK9ig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; BlanketStatement (@BlanketStmtProj) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BlanketStmtProj/status/1149798258002280448?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 12, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Somewhere between 20 and 40 attendees spent time with
Devorah at the GitHub booth putting idle hands to good use. Devorah
and I are greatful to GitHub for hosting us and for the CSTA
conference organizers for allowing this added activity. We&amp;#39;re hoping
it can become a regular activity at the CSTA conference.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s my conference summary. I&amp;#39;m already looking forward to next
year in Arlington Virginia.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 Preconference</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-preconference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2019 10:41:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-preconference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s Monday morning, 7:45AM local time. Being on East Coast time,
Devorah and I have already been up for about 3 hours, hit the gym and
our first cups of our chosen caffeinated beverages.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since it&amp;#39;s not unbearably hot outside  - a cool and dry  80 in the
shade  - we&amp;#39;re sitting outside. Devorah&amp;#39;s knitting another square for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;Blanket Statement&lt;/a&gt; so I figured I&amp;#39;d write a few words about  what we&amp;#39;ve
been doing here in Phoenix leading up to our starting with our
conference later today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whenever we travel for &amp;#34;business&amp;#34;  I&amp;#39;ll try to tack on a day or so to
try to soak up at least a little local flavor and there&amp;#39;s plenty of
local flavor in Phoenix. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After checking in to the hotel we hit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phoenix.gov/parks/arts-culture-history/pueblo-grande/&#34;&gt;Pueblo Grande&lt;/a&gt; museum. It&amp;#39;s a
pre-columbian archaeological site. You can learn about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hohokam&#34;&gt;Hohokam&lt;/a&gt; who
used to live - see a bit how they lived and the intricate canal
systems they created. The outside path that toured the ruins was about
a half mile walk in the 105 degree hot sun but it was worth it. Inside
there were galleries with a few exhibits and a lot of neat
history. Well worth the visit. We also walked around &lt;a href=&#34;https://heritagesquarephx.org/&#34;&gt;Heritage Square&lt;/a&gt;
which had some original Victorian buildings but I wasn&amp;#39;t really super
impressed - probably had something to do with having by that time been
out in the heat for most of the afternoon.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, it was up bright and early to check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dbg.org/&#34;&gt;Desert Botanical
Garden&lt;/a&gt;. Wow - this is a must see. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/xno986ieH-u7i-QttsABbOM1wIorM2YW6tdJGJhBStz6DwjESPqcKblTZyyw9s7Dv42HbFPrYMxtn1wOGVcO4ZZpe-EWisz6MmRi_NoL26mVwk3VSkVViQBjCpl0Bt78Bh09LEyBulB42bVRD3EjMtmHPLSlc5crmTRRC2QOId3yO9Uz5qrFXdV1tJ55DVt0lk7d0MTeZN6DYoQOHHePVAY5y7hxpzoyfdoGcVUVZWntDsrizwj7UAfWTq1P35bhCi1gsrRIeWGxqCbkkSDeIpATF68yyx6r5_pK1cnQAUcoMsAefB5ZfeC9iZAMmUmgC1T5o1zuw9iFXUDjbtQQydiRd4v5wAhSM2rjYq2flut17A-XIn-pdE9-_3OsaMFoso0p0ANHEVwjMjNf6iMcz3uryl-NbAPX3EXtEfb71UEWw8ZzlPsFEoWavlWnw3srxcVblygpaDpXKdw2zhJLEWQihUxSDR-GcPXQXyIeGEopfJJMcVcc3tJRp0um-vMcgEiZDk3-HhPwpRbJ8_8hFU9jYRtxItQLNI2vm-QkpgLxQAE_-0kf0xuRY61_5ruBhVSh-SHMzITmB4ho14Tfx5RnSBRnAPSjRSGt6yDmtFp3RhAkXjE-KCg9pQ04RYLL7E1yfxGKfuMz5Q_poRqBnDDN8K9-A8PK=w1716-h1286-no&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
 
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/BZ6dFN3m8hrA0k707sl0oVesBrVkY5LjSFhXnegkMA2UGkr9IdecaAiM3BJQ_7_H13B6RatGYAwBFrQzXWBzFrLQX6Ujp8OOkmOaZ4zv7fc__ZrEAYswMHeImLbcP-JH5Sw7Zo6pl4z7BsnweAiJkaW_0ez6og2xwH3QneZm8kVSuJAak5os0MwKeiF5jIC74BWR6DrXJZRCyV3YP9xjXHtYAEH3AaDgQNt_1PtytRH9N1Y2eeHEAM4VW6m9oT48L_esn2s1rAp_ZS_rNjQjiAFmAq_QfekBpM9v99m_GCFeivrzDintpN22XPWvzSej1RL0MCbw59qD51WOmVvR6JWEs1SLMUs8Wfzw-PhBJ-PFIgWqNnLbq0K4ggSH-dCVtKUjkV8NkgjFQkPl-p2qaeGm7mn8dsxE7DtFZuEHz3NxQre_ywp2XPMfYJ6LpfvrBahgRqMEvUhOLwj_beo9FRazHiCLEckJ4o5DCumP0zP0CZB_orbZrj27A7qDwWV1HEEYUQQeYgnB7snV3_2wCL_q29FeubAh-qnIY1OcY9GoGnxtu-UPqPJL4YaS3fLj-HqhRt--Y04zU1qcwvwmwJY6ivPbubbj33FQYNorrnFk7QeaL_MxNxt8i5wCjmWPuW5ku5UDQ6YnUzDlOs7R6ONHDsYiKBn0=w966-h1286-no&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/5_rLpviB7wjdnS5kY_z-kXLbOhZFbt9fsiXaCEFVXwKQx0HbUTQBLCu18Bt8nJD4OUTKZAeavAcV5I7JgOq9fuwrArYZtKaiQ2q9baeiUn32BgZ2vNTMqhv9geOpS6g3jGdXCRiVY8DooPgKBzvdjgByGWWaoWXEAyhNoblC4BsNa8XXHCIXEmXkQ5j6sc70t7vpIJsiG2KCmhJ3rgLPDI-7DqYB9ji3a48bPX6-jIwlGyIuB6F2onLBvz7XVb7iw6qkW_Cd_1mHEk3v-jWWG3i-kCc_g8-kbCkF115b-L8H7Ub-8c5LGW_OzvnG29X3RzdKwzcZflxC_4JsfiKVKF5BxJue-WVMyKraxe8gOvY8GBpxSGCIGTCzm-9HXRlstHhrVVwcTyHXajW6bVGOdBmcnNLnnGr0Y0V7P3X2NTfSrVrvWqIxDsxb2SPbjMz7al3iyipy41FmO9yjKMIav5bAf6Ue5zJTGYnQ4lhzxFxJvL-K27REzhh55XvZcrGALmF72utlDpZ1GE7eBLbbPimjkW9nmoIdG_o2CujHwkX3yt4X_n9xfN6q7WSKL9RBmO6c31KSTcXJ1lSRn4GysqQykWa8GN9Flf6pKSUni5eADkFM2NLeyHIwu4ZENoBxvlbWb-zpL59tpX05PB9eUFIqw6Fzxdwx=w284-h213-no&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
 
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/GOhGZJV2NqgaXzoon9-XVbf6S8OlBjCru2qC_lr906ccTvP6OOpKh2wnvY9xauP-ImD0_0FxcibNUOiTQRoxb7IUxwZ4iOPN_tMVUBkYwoq7-sSL43Pg6NYpm6TQcCs8UU76z5YFOaLAoFaYHdcLL8wEq67Hg_xrRN0vWbrbIbM3c2IyB6RzpgwWE0tdR6exWuZFvUlarxRZOrjeAFzPuwfnr1IkDdZX5qSDaMIVodUpGINE8Y9weG_UVF4X6rS7-3eonZSx5ZttXcApJB4fecI2dxnAvoWMyj0UpfRKWliJhCkHgy2T4QPSx1WX8MtoJ3kLM_nNxz2rvB_ACCAuP_VecNYszuio-8Nb5R3CCztKOL6t5C5j2WRanIpi0Gy5Z8AaGC3Rseo82Y1nc6kf1BGstzY6VPvZSn-4wXgOLgwtbijS5gVCDX2GqsjRjDnGu7d5WGWdXS1G4jFLaOWwukt79E1fczY6rdeNV-B05WvaSgn-RloghbKacI35-bwKncZivH214s3hwvcVcykOek6gsIfVJfLOyL3qlMENgnOlt0IvYNTs7FNZpyVAAqJTgYkTRwV6h1GnaqFcyFlTCrk6AEjZ3dT7Ur50UYYBYeTdbJekYuNMH0lHP-roggHEDt6N5EHJykWjfdfwYc3QRCjMQRM7CRHP=w1716-h1286-no&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Did I mention it was really hot out?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we started at 7:00am it wasn&amp;#39;t so bad out - about 85 and only a
touch humid but after a couple of hours we needed some AC. We
originally wanted to hike over to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g31310-d126770-Reviews-Hole_in_the_Rock-Phoenix_Arizona.html&#34;&gt;Hole in the Rock&lt;/a&gt; but were by
that time leery of the heat so we took a Lyft back into town for some
breakfast.  We chose a place but as we approached there was a long
line outside. Our driver said &amp;#34;I know a much better place&amp;#34; turned off
the meter, and took us to &lt;a href=&#34;http://hob-nobs.com/&#34;&gt;HobNobs&lt;/a&gt;. It was the right choice. Service
was a bit slow but good food in a comfortable environment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We weren&amp;#39;t sure what to do next when I noticed Sarah Judd tweed that
the Museum of Musical Instruments was free for teachers. It&amp;#39;s about 30
minutes out of the downtown but we took the trip. I was a little irked
that the web site said that &amp;#34;educators&amp;#34; were free during the month of
July but they didn&amp;#39;t accept my Hunter ID as a teacher. They were
limiting the free admission to K12 teachers. Still, the museum was
terrific. Gotta love a place that doesn&amp;#39;t take themselves too
seriously:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/tiQyN-6h0nqoh2AZKKrJrj3xOdsm0Dx6AogCAbRd5uU8mtAcdB2E2ZOeL6BQmS0TTR2yyUyf7wG4x61Vyw8Wsl82h8d3ZPh3FVXBlK6wyjoqAxAbwJRZ3fBxZCRlehQy6oqR96tTEqsEyHejf_Bo811d8ha3uCOgSnAgQ8WaIBRNSe0sAj93RUvOSz_LIRq5vfaYNni0NN61_hKaVYxXgAu1LcrZ5Ad5MACqq61M6Tmw775cCOqQMpkSWBql3cgLo5sleCsd9UY0c5iwjf1ep58KAAof_URDfavmKVQYrsqgbsd_-pMsaf08cmXQBG3SKwNceHynzSQ0dUpsT9P0-TowrAZGMcY2DSwm8GUSn6igFQ4mm4tZKGxtMuz1V1b-sw_ASySCAVm0kKHlqbeeE0xDC15-mLlsjg-MNJq4rV1xQ17Mi3R-g11b-NCQjap6orZUN_k9mM2wW-yDnmGwnCbWNO41Gksv67TO3DrKAagwcXQWX1qnxc7AjBt_q8CSANemT0n0JCoKMYZB7vTkaBn-GHPmYbvQzCJwb6UsVsYdkwwJMDaSxPla-ZO054pYWP0cQbnCyyMmj4Xbujy6L679-A_RFd2t-KiGAxDXkMfurVRwor5KL_rFqeoUzv6zlTKW8B--VxlBggr6CfloKd6gzIT5CG6F=w966-h1286-no&#34;
         alt=&#34;air guitar&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;air guitar&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Azvg1hbIPjQUShiw8iSHTNzoRtLxT5JuR-KqkNgefyOMmWL0qWo3aCMSqdnMtx4rubwDs6W868DrlAVe2Eu_RR22Ue1LmEok8w7ti1ssmW_j8D_WgAbzTMSHTVHfLPqePbuBxndlPWajZ6LkboJZNlDqQV-LC2Re92ZZpRr_UhMNqS-94O9fnkKmuwJjnIBki3OMkHrcTvle0Sg_FtRRlwj8-KHpuVJRlhwNr1b3ZZ3c339wx3VkHfsVdG92yOe3Jb2bNJCnTlg2xC1ZXQGquREJT1mKWOdPxq8QWuidb68mvC-q5ztNDcS0SjjyD82lk8juEUo4xh6acV7ND7iCL1B_GVkZaybKLaaApEOwvnHznJjWfvaKulgrl-WLVCj69qQhKc2vLzAOwNpGpeEQEY_gvzZ70fh26kRjR96jozDvBF7PdWFlWgLcCdKYRQ1QDCp-HlvNCkfLPxmhk2KG_UmyL2tV6HQ8Z06ZcHr9U5Oc38Iw1ck3jHzOSohrLbhKIT_d3IT1Wg5r_p19lyO2rmObjjP1boo2lQ9Eqmr9IhvXMfQciUfg8pKvEoDNkv6cohyOfXF-JIUJb-3L3QzszXnFRBGHsEJbPCUsduuugO7OrAQBYQqJKWNUtKuePQx_Lg2krgssxeESL03SIURpSC4EVxBb64nF=w966-h1286-no&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Exhibits on instruments and musicians. If it weren&amp;#39;t at the end of a
long touring day I think we could have spent another hour or two
there. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended up getting a locally made menorah for Natan before we left:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/5wLUyLwvlQ-R_5v6gRRGHm9JpfA5JxlJYZhLuZ2PQKFjBfVAUYaL6TXqEswVw9pF0Us3i88f2_98QUx5D1bHfme6O4Z2M_RSfZgRMDx9lW6mSaTNhsqZMeqoq8yCpD-02qaKFcxu3lJbYF5ust9bC5ldYo1EE2pwVL3OcdDr-OsfvBGjM98wdcEV4qjQycQiPenlfej_7Whu04Gsex-z6195cdaJz4Zrf-_A8bteB60XIDuCIVtEdRVsv_2z39fa5eGQbHW1Ep92PVN-WNcofap4l3RzdJQgItI_JfPpNVcnqeEcZeYSNBh89e9t5sIhHqyZbTZaJlqOLFZySh1b8ks1KCNpvVMivDIZVo9XI8wjF_xn88vOtAIrI7pQa6AugKiIuFLKtwPtLMzdA82R5vfx7mIqyUq4RPoCtvIqP9zzKctGD5pXt8GdYIiTiPSYXiemSykZR-Z8CXRLCOyfewF6IkAZaaSOEcT-rzdDXW0Oi5XB6S7MJDNvp7tn55MwRcBGorBXJrKmtyBCAiZ6FlQlSB4EZA3vhkoPKizAua4-ae9GBVThdtaF8RHSGG9JRazLzOlpUfVH9c-bkqymZmcznCoxz8s0-kBActC1faM9qykxhcJSlkHInIjH0g0U-xr7n3z0WJFJy2OzTy3KLJOtvkm0Vc7B=w1716-h1286-no&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday concluded at the GitHub for Education reception where I had
a great conversation with Nick Stoyas about his efforts in Chicago to
scale out their CS programs and thoughts on internship opportunities
for high school students. I hope to write more on that later. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In about 45 minutes we&amp;#39;ll head out to &lt;a href=&#34;https://heard.org/&#34;&gt;The Heard Museum&lt;/a&gt; which is all
about Native American art and culture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That should bring us to lunch today and then conference time!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re reading this and at the CSTA2019 - hope you also get or got
to see some sites and swing by the Github booth to say hi. If not, if
you have a chance to get out to Phoenix, preferably in the cooler
months, I would certainly recommend it.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning For CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 17:26:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to flying out to Phoenix for CSTA-2019 Saturday
morning. The conference doesn&amp;#39;t officially start until Sunday, Monday
for me since I&amp;#39;m not doing any of the pre-conference workshops. We&amp;#39;ll
have most of Saturday as long as we&amp;#39;re up to it, Sunday, and Monday
morning. Actually, there is the GitHub reception on &lt;a href=&#34;https://csta-github-meetup.confetti.events/&#34;&gt;Sunday evening&lt;/a&gt; so
that&amp;#39;s kind of official conference stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to the conference, I&amp;#39;m super looking forward to it. To me CSTA is
 a people conference. SIGCSE by contrast is more of a sessions
conference. SIGCSE is bigger and less intimate. I have a great time
there catching up with friends from across the country and when my asocial
self manages, making new ones but for me it&amp;#39;s more content/session
driven. There are always a bunch of sessions where I say to myself &amp;#34;I
really should go to that.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CSTA is more intimate so it seems easier to meet and talk to new
people, even for asocial me. On the other hand, I find fewer &amp;#34;must
see&amp;#34; sessions. This makes sense though. I no longer
teach K12 and I had already designed and taught complete course
sequences going from beginner through college level before the first
CSTA conference.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. There are lots of great sessions. It&amp;#39;s more that
many of the sessions I&amp;#39;m interested in are more &amp;#34;that looks cool&amp;#34; or
&amp;#34;interesting&amp;#34; rather than, &amp;#34;I really need to see that for what I&amp;#39;m
doing or where I&amp;#39;m at in my career.&amp;#34;  Maybe it&amp;#39;s just that it&amp;#39;s really
hard for the sessions to match the value added from CSTA&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;hallway
track&amp;#34; which I think is through the roof.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are the sessions I&amp;#39;m zeroing in on:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On Monday, the &amp;#34;Creativity in the K-12 Computing Classroom&amp;#34; BOF looks
interesting so I&amp;#39;ll probably try to hit it. On Saturday, I&amp;#39;m curious
about the &amp;#34;Advanced CS Concepts in High School: One Tool to Rule Them
All&amp;#34; session. Based on the description, I&amp;#39;m curious how much is about
advanced concepts and how much about tooling and resources that let
you get to interesting data and applications. The &amp;#34;How to teach AI
across K-12&amp;#34; session could also be interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JonAlf and I will be doing our session on using GitHub in the next
block so I pretty much have to be there :-).  In the afternoon, I&amp;#39;m
looking at the &amp;#34;You can teach Machine Learning to HS students&amp;#34; mostly
because I&amp;#39;m curious as to how the presenter&amp;#39;s thoughts on the subject
can add to what I&amp;#39;ve done in my classes. Actually, that&amp;#39;s also why I&amp;#39;m
interested in the earlier AI session. I&amp;#39;m also intrigued by Ed Campos&amp;#39;
Bootstrap Data talk but I won&amp;#39;t directly be going down that road in
any classes soon so have to prioritize. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the last block, I&amp;#39;m intrigued by the Embroidery talk but Nifty
Assignments will probably win out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t looked over Wednesday&amp;#39;s schedule yet - I&amp;#39;ll leave that for
Tuesday evening. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;ll be going to most of these sessions, I&amp;#39;ll probably
spend a good amount of time at the GitHub booth hopefully talking shop
with my fellow educators. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides, when I&amp;#39;m at the GitHub booth I also get to hang out with
Devorah (my wife). Did I mention, she&amp;#39;s doing a very cool
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;knitting/crocheting for charity&lt;/a&gt; project that you all should check out?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope to see all my old friends and meet many new ones in a few
days!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crochet at CSTA</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/crochet-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 05:03:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/crochet-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/img/yarn-logo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/img/yarn-logo.jpg&#34; title=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/img/yarn-logo.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ok, probably more knitting but Crochet at CSTA was the line used in
the newsletter and it sounds better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As some of you know, my wife Devorah is all about the fiber
arts. Knitting, spinning, dying, weaving, the works. We&amp;#39;ve got a loom,
two spinning wheels, two bobbin lace pillows, and bins and bins of
deconstructed sheep, llamas, alpacas, and angora bunnies. I even got
her some straw once to spin into gold. I
figured as teachers it would be a good retirement plan.  That never
happened.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point at a conference we attended, Devorah noted that she
wasn&amp;#39;t the only one knitting and an &lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;idea&lt;/a&gt; was born. She encouraged
knitters and crocheters to make 7x9 blocks and at the end of the
conference she put it together into a blanket a it was donated to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.projectlinus.org/&#34;&gt;Project Linus&lt;/a&gt; who got the blanket to a child in distress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/img/knitted-squares.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/img/knitted-squares.jpg&#34; title=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/img/knitted-squares.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can read up about how this all went down &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/catskills-blanket-2018/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, thanks to the CSTA and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jakebask&#34;&gt;Jake Baskin &lt;/a&gt;in particular along with the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GitHubEducation&#34;&gt;GitHub Education&lt;/a&gt; team led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mohardek&#34;&gt;Moira Hardek&lt;/a&gt; we&amp;#39;re bringing &lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;Blanket
Statement&lt;/a&gt; to CSTA-2019. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you knit or crochet, swing by the GitHub booth, grab a ball of yarn and
some needles (or a crochet hook) and knit away. Bring completed blocks
back to Devorah at the booth. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t know how to knit or crochet? No problem. Devorah will teach
you. She&amp;#39;ll be at the GitHub booth for the entire conference.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to all the amazing CS that were all going to do during the
conference, let&amp;#39;s go old school and knit a blanket or two for charity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For more details, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;Blanket Statement&lt;/a&gt; home page or just
drop me a line.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 - Using GitHub as a CMS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 12:09:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
With ISTE ending, the next big event for CS treachers is the annual
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.csteachers.org/page/2019conference&#34;&gt;CSTA Conference&lt;/a&gt;. I first attended two years ago in Baltimore. Last
year the conference, in Omaha was bigger and better in every way
imaginable. I expect this year to be the best yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t go to a lot of conferences so I don&amp;#39;t have much to compare
CSTA with but I like the fact that it&amp;#39;s is about half the size of
SIGCSE. At about 1000 attendees it still feels small enough to be
intimate but at the same time large enough so that there&amp;#39;s something
for everyone and plenty of people to learn and share from and with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just like last year, I&amp;#39;ll be spending a lot of time at the GitHub
booth so if you want to talk about how to use GitHub to support your
students make sure to stop by and say hello.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll also be giving a session with my long time partner in crime
JonAlf. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of us know that Git is a version control system and that
GitHub is pretty much the industry standard platform for using
Git. Many of us also know that GitHub for Education has a great
toolset to support using GitHub with your classes. Tools that help
organize, distribute, collect, and assess assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fewer people know that GitHub can be used to really easily create a
web presence and as a way to distribute class material and you don&amp;#39;t
even have to use the command line if you don&amp;#39;t want to. I use GitHub
as a lightweight CMS with my classes, to host full blown web sites,
and also to host this blog.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Come join JonAlf and me on Tuesday at 11:15 in West 106C and we&amp;#39;ll
show you how you can use GitHub as a web presence as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also want to briefly mention that my better half, Devorah, is going
to be with us at the GitHub booth running a really cool
knitting/crocheting for  charity project (thanks to both CSTA and
GitHub for facilitating this). I&amp;#39;ll write more about it in a day or so
but if you&amp;#39;re going to be at CSTA2019 and you knit or crochet or want
to learn, you can check the project out here:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (note that the site is hosted on
GitHub and the source is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blanketstatementproject/blanketstatementproject.github.io&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
GitHub is also holding a pre-conference reception on July 7 from
5:30 - 8:00. You can sign up &lt;a href=&#34;https://csta-github-meetup.confetti.events/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope to see many of you in a couple of weeks in Phoenix.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>