<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hardware on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/hardware/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (hardware)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 17:10:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/hardware/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Pinebook Pro update</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 17:10:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since posting about my new &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook/&#34;&gt;Pinebook Pro&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;ve gotten a few questions as
it pertains to teaching CS so I thought I&amp;#39;d give a quick update.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of software here&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;ve actually gotten working: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
libreoffice (comes preinstalled)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
C/C++ toolchain (manjaro package install)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Java (manjaro package install)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs (built from scratch and manjaro install)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NetLogo (had to customize the startup script as per the NetLogo
FAQ)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Racket (had to compile from source)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also heard the VSCode works with no issues.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also manjaro which is a little different from Ubuntu which is
probably more well known. I installed a program named &lt;a href=&#34;https://computingforgeeks.com/yay-best-aur-helper-for-arch-linux-manjaro/&#34;&gt;yay&lt;/a&gt; for
package management which also gave me access to the community packages
(like extra repos for Ubuntu). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest difference I&amp;#39;ve had between Manjaro and Ubuntu is with
Ubuntu I&amp;#39;d search for packages with &lt;code&gt;apt-cache search package&lt;/code&gt; and
install with &lt;code&gt;apt-get install package&lt;/code&gt; while with yay it&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;yay -Ss
package&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;yay -S package&lt;/code&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a little more nuanced but it
isn&amp;#39;t harder, just different.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other difference is that the Pinebook is set up with Manjaro
running KDE plasma which is a different interface but all common
windowing interfaces are fairly similar.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A final point I want to mention is that the Pinebook Pro price of
$200 represents the cost of the unit. The Pine64 people don&amp;#39;t make any
money on this. It&amp;#39;s about getting the units out there and building a
community. First, this means that you won&amp;#39;t be able to go online and
order class sets of these (at least I don&amp;#39;t think you&amp;#39;d be able to do
so) and that if a device such as this were made by a tradional vendor
it would cost at least a bit more so that they could make a hopefully
fair profit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, this is a very functional Linux laptop for around $200. It
proves what you can do and After a few days use I highly recommend it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
$200
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinebook Pro - an $200 Linux Laptop</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 17:24:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing this on my new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pine64.org/pinebook-pro/&#34;&gt;Pinebook Pro&lt;/a&gt; - a $200 ARM based Linux
laptop. The Pinebook Pro comes from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pine64.org/&#34;&gt;Pine64&lt;/a&gt; project. As you could
figure out, they do the Pine64 which is similar to a Raspberry Pi and
they&amp;#39;ve got some cool projects. In addition to the Pinebook pro
they&amp;#39;ve also got the Pine Tab and Pine Phone and more. Now, you&amp;#39;re not
going to be able to go to their site and say &amp;#34;I need 30 of these for
my class&amp;#34; - at least not for the Pinebook pro but it is a pretty cool
proof of concept and hobbyist machine and it shows that we could have
affordable devices for our schools and less afluent students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got the PbP out of curiousity and also to see if I could find a low
cost solution for Hunter College students. All of my honors students
get laptops but the rest of Hunter CS is on their own so a low cost
device is pretty attractive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The specs are pretty decent - 1080P 14&amp;#34; screen, 4GB of memory, 64GB
mmc (upgradeable), USB-C, long battery life and more. They claim that
it can drive an external 4k monitor but I haven&amp;#39;t tested this yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, does it deliver?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall yes but with a few caveats. It&amp;#39;s still on the side of a
tinkerer/hobbyist device.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Out of the box it seemed DOA - it wouldn&amp;#39;t boot. I found in the forums
that there&amp;#39;s an emmc enable switch inside that sometimes ended up in
the off position. I had to take out the eight screws from the bottom,
pop the case and flip the switch. Seems like that&amp;#39;s something that
could have been caught before they closed the cases but it wasn&amp;#39;t too
big of a deal. It is, however a deal breaker for a novice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there it booted fine. Right into Manjaro Linux running
KDE. Everything seemed to work. Next I tried to boot of an SD card -
Debian this time. Worked like a charm though the distribution kept
dropping WIFI.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to Manjaro. Being a Linuxmint user and having not used Manjaro in
about two years it took a bit of time to get the lay of the land but
just about everything worked. I installed syncthing which I use
instead of dropbox, zsh, and built Emacs from source. It took forever
but worked. Well, worked with some font problems. I ended up installing
Emacs 27 from the Manjaro repositories and everything went
seemelessly. Even though I ended up not using the source built Emacs
it did show that the G++ toolchain all worked well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also tested Java and Clojure. No problems though starting Clojure
seemed to take a day and a half. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other tests included installing the Cinnamon and Mate desktop
environments. The only thing I haven&amp;#39;t been able to install
succesfully has been a VPN. On the battery front, I haven&amp;#39;t used it
long enough in a sitting to put a dent in it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, at $200, this isn&amp;#39;t going to be a speed demon. My default config
does a bunch of things so even opening a terminal with zsh has some
lag. Once loaded though things are smooth. I would have loved more
memory but 4GB seems sufficient for day to day stuff and student work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will his become my day to day laptop? I don&amp;#39;t know. I think if I can
slim down some of my config it might.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re looking for an innexpensive Linux laptop and are comfortable
tinkering and reading some forums check out the Pinebook. If it was an
option, I&amp;#39;d love to get these for my students instead of the
overpriced Dells we have to get them every year.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>