<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cs4all on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs4all/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (cs4all)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 18:50:11 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/cs4all/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter Launches CS Teacher Certification Programs</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 18:50:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ed-programs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It took a while but we&amp;#39;re finally here. Hunter College is launching
it&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://education.hunter.cuny.edu/admissions/graduate-programs/computer-science/&#34;&gt;Computer Science Teacher Certification&lt;/a&gt; programs. This was the
second big initiative I&amp;#39;ve been working on at Hunter. The first was
the Daedalus undergraduate CS scholars program. The Daedalus program
started my first year and is now providing the best value (and in my
opinion best) undergraduate CS opportunity in New York. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS Certification took longer. I had to design the programs, they had to
make it through the whole CUNY governance process which even under
ideal circumstances takes around a year and then up through NYSED. Oh,
and we had to convince the state to create a certification area in the
meantime.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, we&amp;#39;re live and will kick off our certificate program
this summer. That&amp;#39;s the program designed for teachers already
certified in another subject area seeking to add the CS credential.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what does the program look like? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It combines content and pedagogy. It was designed to give teachers the
CS they need and the knowledge of how to teach it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of content, you need some depth. In my opinion, that depth
should be at least a class beyond what you&amp;#39;d normally expect to
teach. For example a math teacher&amp;#39;s classes would max out with BC Calc
so I&amp;#39;d want a math teacher to have a math class beuond that. Since we
max out with APCS-A, my program takes teachers through data
structures - APCS-AB or CS2. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teachers also need breadth. They don&amp;#39;t need to have a full course in
AI or a full class in Graphics etc. but a course that gives them
exposure to a number of fields. Enough to teach a unit, mentor a
precocious student, or learn more on their own to develop new
courses. We have a topics course for that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To round out the CS part of the program we have a programming heavy
ethics course. While ethics are woven throughout all the courses - CS
and CS Ed we felt that this standalone course also adds great value to
our program.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a far cry from what I&amp;#39;ve seen in many other CS Ed programs
which follow the &amp;#34;you take it you teach it&amp;#34; philosophy. Basically
teachers take Exploring CS, APCS-P, and APCS-A and viola, you&amp;#39;ve got
CS teachers. Not in my book.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then we mix in the CS Ed. Two methods course where we introduce
additional content and how to teach it and also a curriculum design
course. The methods courses are based on current best practices and on
what I&amp;#39;ve learned helping teachers develop over the years but I&amp;#39;m
particularly excited about the curriculum design course. Over the
years I had to take three curriculum design courses and didn&amp;#39;t learn a
thing about curriculum design in any of them. I swore that if I ever
created an education course it would be a curriculum design course
that was good. Over the years, I
developed units, classes and full programs and learned a few
tricks. That in turn developed into the course. Teachers will study
existing curricula and develop their own and since the course
integrates fieldwork, they&amp;#39;ll deliver it as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I had internal help at Hunter, I want to send a special thanks
to JonAlf, Sam, and Topher - three of the best teachers I know who
provided feedback, assistance, and inspiration (sometimes without
knowing it) along with other friends in education, academia, and
industry throughout New York State who made sure I designed a program
that would work for teachers across New York State.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re looking to become certified to teach CS in New York schools,
check us out. You can find more info &lt;a href=&#34;https://education.hunter.cuny.edu/admissions/graduate-programs/computer-science/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS For All The Time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs4allthetime/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 08:20:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs4allthetime/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A question that frequently comes up with respect to CS for All is what
does it mean? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me it means giving all students some fundamental exposure to
computer science so that they can:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Make use of those thinking skills, problem solving approaches, and
practical tools regardless of their future paths. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Provide a path for the subset of &amp;#34;all&amp;#34; that desire to further pursue
computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But even with this, how do you do it?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does it mean that you require computer science? If so, do we require it every
year? some years? One time only?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does it mean you offer it as an elective? If so, when?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think about this a fair amount but decided to write something up
when I saw this tweet:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;STEM related career interests are largely developed before high school (Sadler, Sonnert, Hazari, &amp;amp; Tai, 2012) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/csforall?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#csforall&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/csedweek?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#csedweek&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/TiAUvpP3bQ&#34;&gt;https://t.co/TiAUvpP3bQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Lana Peterson (@tyLanasaurusrex) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tyLanasaurusrex/status/1070475730562084864?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;December 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I responded that I&amp;#39;ve seen many kids get their first exposure in high
school and from that go on to careers in tech so it&amp;#39;s clear to me that
high school isn&amp;#39;t too late. I was reminded that I was talking about
kids who went through my required HS CS class so the kids had no
choice but to be exposed to CS but the people advocating starting at
an elementary level are talking about a compulsory experience so to
compare a required elementary experience against an elective high
school one is really apples to oranges.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even thought it&amp;#39;s an unfair comparison there are a lot of things it
can lead one to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should we teach CS in every grade? Probably not. How about every band?
Maybe. For those of you not living in the K12 world &amp;#34;by band&amp;#34; usually
refers to a set of grades - kindergarten to 2, 3 through 5, 6-8, and
then high school. Where should it be required and where an elective?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teaching a required CS class in every grade or band is going to be a
huge undertaking. I&amp;#39;m also not sure it&amp;#39;s required. To get the best
bang for your buck you want to expose the kids to CS in a way and at a
time when they might pursue it further. If you&amp;#39;re having only one
required experience, I don&amp;#39;t think the elementary grades are the
place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s that point in time, I think around first through third grade
where dinosaurs are all the rage. Maybe more so in NYC where we have
access to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amnh.org/&#34;&gt;American Museum of Natural History&lt;/a&gt; but still. Lots of
young kids want to be paleontologists but it doesn&amp;#39;t hold. Okay. maybe
I&amp;#39;m being a little silly here but I think the basic point is
accurate. Kids are exposed to many things in the early grades that
just fade away. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying that we shouldn&amp;#39;t do CS or CS related things in grade
school. Things like the activity &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fredwilson&#34;&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt; described in his post on
this year&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2018/12/la-hora-del-codigo/&#34;&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt; or the problem solving and logic games good
teachers do if given the time and resources. Things that have
always been done by some teachers in some schools but are now being
relabled CS or Computational Thinking. These are great practices and
should be made available to all students as part of their elementary
education but I doubt that they&amp;#39;ll lead to many kids following CS as a
career path. I&amp;#39;m not an elementary school expert but to me, even
though I see great value in the early logic / problem solving stuff, I
don&amp;#39;t see hyping CS early as making a difference unless there&amp;#39;s some
follow up before the interest fades.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That brings us to the middle school bands. I&amp;#39;ve dabbled a little here
but it&amp;#39;s also not my wheelhouse. In my experience, kids in lower
middle school can dabble in DnD tools and start to develop some 
coding skills and explore some of the CS concepts that they&amp;#39;ll see in
late HS or college and those in upper middle school can play with the
text based languages to do the same. What I also noticed is that what
can be accomplished in a month with those kids in middle school can be
done in a week or two when the kids are a year or two older and with
greater understanding and retention. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a side note, before people get up in arms with &amp;#34;I teach middle
school kids APCS-A and they all master it&amp;#34; let me say that I&amp;#39;m
describing my experience across a range of middle school kids. There
will always be few outliers who can do more when younger. That said
I&amp;#39;m betting that most people who say that any middle school kid can
indeed master APCS-A hasn&amp;#39;t done so in an inner city poor public
school. Have you done it while teaching a class of 34?  With a class
of low income students with all the disadvantages and challenges
inherent to that population? What&amp;#39;s more did you then have to teach
them a data structures course a year or two later to see if they
really mastered the original material.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings us to high school. As with my original tweet, in my
experience if you give kids a good first CS experience in high school
you can indeed give them everything needed for CS for All and it&amp;#39;s
close enough to college so that they might very well continue on the
CS career path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So where does this leave us? We certainly should embed computational
thinking practices (whatever that actaully means) in the elementary
school, particularly if we can do it in a way that also supports other
academic areas and while it&amp;#39;s nice to have a CS middle school
experience and if we can afford to offer one that&amp;#39;s wonderful. On the
other hand, I don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s as important as elementary exposure and
high school exposure so if we have to cut a corner, that&amp;#39;s the
place. To me, and of course I&amp;#39;m biased, the critical time for a
requirement is high school. Sure, if it&amp;#39;s an elective kids won&amp;#39;t take
it but that&amp;#39;s true of a lot of subjects. I don&amp;#39;t know what the
research says but people do indeed change directions. How many of us
are doing what we thought we&amp;#39;d be doing in grade school or middle
school. Heck, even high school. I have a friend that did computer work
in his twenties and thirties, then went to law school and practiced
law for a bunch of years and then in his forties started a production
company in LA. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a big believer in CS for All but to me it doesn&amp;#39;t mean it has to
be in every grade or every band. If I could only do it in one place it
would be required in the high school. If in two I&amp;#39;d add the elementary
school piece and then finally the middle school.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final point I&amp;#39;d like to add that school is a zero sum game. There
are only so many minutes in the day and as we add CS we remove
something else. I believe we can add CS or, more specifically CT to
the elemntary schools without cutting anything and I know there&amp;#39;s room
in high schools in NY. I&amp;#39;m not sure about middle schools. In any
event, I&amp;#39;d hate to see music and art programs - already decimated by
budget cuts and misguided policies like the small schools movement
take a further hit so as to get CS everywhere.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just some food for thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APCS-P -  Bigger Intake Or Leaky Pipe</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Advanced Placement Computer Science got top billing on Alfred
Thompson&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/01/computer-science-education-things-im.html&#34;&gt;Things I&amp;#39;m Watching in 2017&lt;/a&gt; post. Alfred talks about how
APCS-P exploded onto the scene and wonders what will happen with APCS
this year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have some questions as well but mine won&amp;#39;t be answered for years to
come, if ever.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like it or not, the College Board has an out sized influence on K12
education. As long as people are convinced that AP=good there will be
a push for more and more AP classes and APCS-P is a perfect class to
push. CS is the hot topic in K12, the topic is getting a big push
from both politicians and industry, the class has no pre-requisites
and in spite of being called a college course is somehow appropriate
for a typical tenth grader.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The concern here is that at the end of the day. APCS-P is an exam or
rather an exam plus two other assessments. The quality can vary
greatly. I&amp;#39;ve heard of APCS-P implementations that seem pretty
rigorous and I&amp;#39;ve seen implementations that are, quite frankly, a
joke. The question is this: is APCS-P both motivating kids to go on to
the next level and just as importantly preparing them to succeed at
that level?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We might never know.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A high school might only offer APCS-P. If APCS-A isn&amp;#39;t offered, we
might not know if the student went on to take more CS and we won&amp;#39;t
know if the student succeeded or not. I&amp;#39;ve seen this with some very
high profile, popular, after school/summer non-profits. The kids have
a great time and the non-profits rave about how much their kids learn
but then the kids take a real CS class in school and drop like
flies. Was it the teacher/professor or did the non-profit set the kids up to
fail by convincing them they knew a whole lot more than they did and
that CS was super easy all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If credit is given for APCS-P, it looks like it will be blanket
credit. CS majors and minors will still have to take all the same classes in
college and CS so it will be very hard to tell if APCS-P is
responsible for any uptick in CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the College Board is going to make a lot of
money but if APCS-P becomes the standard high school CS course will
this leave us with true, quality CS4All? I have my doubts.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>