<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>teaching on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (teaching)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 07:37:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - what to leave in, what to leave out</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 07:37:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Teachers always make decisions in their courses - what to leave in,
what to leave out. I&amp;#39;ve seen programming and data structure classes
where everything is written from scratch and others where a few things
are explained and the students just use built in types like the
java LinkedList  or Arrays.sort() method.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do too much from scratch and you&amp;#39;ll never finish the curriculum. Do to
little and the students won&amp;#39;t really understand what&amp;#39;s going on and
walk a path towards being programmers or coders rather than computer
scientists. Most teachers work somewhere between the extremes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We not only had to make these decisions for our CS content but also
for our methods. We decided to leave out two particular
methods that are very popular - pair programming and Parsons
problems. We did mention both in passing and did a little talk on pair
programming but the treatment was far less than say live coding,
subgoal labeling or the many other teaching techniques we decided to
explicitly cover. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why did we leave out these two topics? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Partly pragmatism and pragmatism is something that&amp;#39;s always left out
when talking about teaching. Let&amp;#39;s look at Parsons problems. If you&amp;#39;re
unfamiliar with them, they&amp;#39;re basically scrambled code
fragments. Students have to put them in order. They&amp;#39;re cool puzzles
and a nice change of pace. but you have to create them and get them to
your students. That didn&amp;#39;t fit all that well with us. By the time we
got to content that would benefit from Parsons problems our pace or approach
didn&amp;#39;t really fit using them. It&amp;#39;s also worth noting that we haven&amp;#39;t
seen any good online Parson problem generator systems which would be
both a boon to problem creation and potentially distribution and
assessment. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There just wasn&amp;#39;t that much bang for the buck in giving them more than
lip service. Since our cohort was composed of experienced teachers, we
were confident that they can find the appropriate Parsons problems
resources and use them where appropriate in their classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On pair programming we had similar pragmatic issues - it didn&amp;#39;t fit
all that well given how tight the program was and we had to figure out
how bet to do it remotely on the fly. We also knew that the cohort had
all been to at least some NYC CS4All training and so were at least
exposed to the idea. Still, we, or more accurately, Topher, who&amp;#39;s had
great success getting student buy in did do a brief talk on the
subject. Some of the things we covered were: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How to motivate pair programming in a collaborative way
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What activities can you give the navigator while the driver&amp;#39;s
setting up the environment to involve them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How in the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; some developers love PP and some hate it
and that there are many variations on the theme.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You&amp;#39;d not always going to get student buy in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That last point is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; important. Teachers are going to try things
that don&amp;#39;t always work and unfortunately, the system of evaluation
doesn&amp;#39;t promote such necessary experimentation. What&amp;#39;s more every time
you go to a professional development or training session or head
something online it&amp;#39;s about how the presented did it and it worked
perfectly and if you follow the same recipe it&amp;#39;ll work for you. It
might, but then, it might not. It&amp;#39;s all about building the toolbox of
tricks and using them when appropriate and even then, not every lesson
is going to be John Keating or Jaime Escalante on the big screen.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, in the end we made choices. We&amp;#39;re they the right ones? I think
so. Next time around the cohort will be different and the
circumstances a little as well. Will we make the same choices? Maybe,
we&amp;#39;ll have to wait and see. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - adding methods to our madness</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 06:47:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Our summer intensive was, well, pretty intensive. We met all day every
day for a month and knocked out four classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Programming (CS1)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Data Structures
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Topics
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Methods
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you ever took or taught a summer session class, you know that time
is tight and generally you cover a little less than in a fall or
spring semester class. N credits in 5 weeks just isn&amp;#39;t the same as
those same N credits spread over 13. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How did we recapture some time? First, we had some pre-work and second
we integrated some of the courses. We couldn&amp;#39;t really do it with
programming and data structures and we were less successful at
integrating the topics than we liked but it made the most sense with
methods, in fact, I think the methods part of the class was more
successful as a result of it&amp;#39;s integration with the other subjects
than it would have been as a stand alone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s what we did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We first thought about covering methods as we taught topics - that is,
present something using some teaching technique, cover the topic and
then also dive in to the technique. This turned out to be a
mistake. The teachers that came in with a strong CS background  seemed
fine but for the ones newer to the subject matter, it was too much at
once. We had to alter course.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So we did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We continued to model various methods and sometimes made a side remark
here or there but focused on the CS. After a few days in, we were
ready to spend a day on pedagogy. We broke the class into groups and
had them reflect on the content we taught - how did we teach it? Why
did we approach it the way we did? Did it work? This led to some rich
discussion of both CS teaching techniques and teaching in general. We
were very happy with how it all went.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then went back to content but added more side bits here and there
about the teaching methods - as they became more comfortable with the
CS we were able to integrate more methods talk in with the CS talk. At
our next formal pedagogy lesson, we again talked about new techniques
that were modeled but also looked at alternative approaches and
took a deeper look at our individual cohort members student
populations. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the methods we discussed included: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Live Coding 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Subgoal labeling
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Make predictions
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Modifying existing code
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
code tracing
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
diagramming
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
scaffolded assignments (code skeletons)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rubber Duck Debugging
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Code sharing (presenting)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
writing implementations of library code
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
slack techniques (reacts polls, channels, ) 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
thought-grooming/sparking warm-up Qs/tasks
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
relevant quotes at warm-up
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and more but the list doesn&amp;#39;t really do the discussion justice. Take
&amp;#34;live coding&amp;#34; for example - that&amp;#39;s not just writing code in front of
the class. There&amp;#39;s a rich discussion here - how do you narrate? Is it
truly live or from a note sheet? How about discussing workflow while
modeling it? How about live coding subgoals? The actual class is much
richer than just &amp;#34;live coding.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to integrating methods into the teaching of content, we
also merged it with the topics course for some of the assessment. For
topics, each group created a class or unit on some area of CS and
included in the documents they prepared and presentation was a
discussion of how it might bet taught. I know that they all came in as
experienced teachers so weren&amp;#39;t starting with nothing but man, they
knocked it out of the park. I&amp;#39;ll be talking more about the topics in a
later post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll probably say this a lot in my summer intensive wrap up posts but
it was such a treat working with a cohort of great educators and also
to have two of the best teachers I know to work with as the teaching
team.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing teachers to teach CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-recap-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 06:16:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-cert-recap-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that the summer portion of Hunter College&amp;#39;s Advanced Certificate
in Teaching Computer Science is over I thought I&amp;#39;d do a
postmortem. That is, a few posts about what we did and how it all
went. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, though, an overview of the program.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Advanced Certificate program is geared towards teachers who are
currently certified in another subject area who wish to earn an
additional New York State teaching certificate in Computer
Science. Aspiring teachers - people who don&amp;#39;t currently have either a
Masters degree or any teaching certification can enroll in our Masters
in Computer Science Education program. We&amp;#39;re starting a small cohort
of five on that in the Fall. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The certificate program consists of a bunch of graduate classes plus
field work which is required by the state. Over the summer we covered
four of the classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Programming - essentially a CS1 type course.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Data Structures - since K12 teachers should go deeper than the last
HS course which is typically APCS-A.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Topcs in Compute rScience - since K12 teachers need a wide breadth
of CS knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Methods - since teachers need to know how to teach CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the fall, we&amp;#39;ll continue with Ethics in Computer Science and
Curriculum Development which also includes the field work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For this summer we started with a cohort of 22 practicing teachers but
lost one along the way. They all came from different schools and we
had all five boroughs represented. Most of the teachers worked in high
schools but we had some middle school representation and in terms of
current certifications, we had at least math, special ed, and science
represented but that&amp;#39;s something we didn&amp;#39;t officially track.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Staffing wise, it was me along with two of my long time collaborators
JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver and Topher Mykolyk. JonAlf and Topher are two of
the best educators out there and part of my former core team at
Stuy. That team is the biggest thing I still miss having come over to
Hunter. They&amp;#39;re quite simply the best.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The program ran basically all day every day during the month of
July. we knew it would be tight so we also added on some pre-work
which made sure all participants had some experience with Java prior
to our official start. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More will be revealed over the next few posts but I&amp;#39;ll spoil the
ending - I&amp;#39;m super proud of our 21 participants - while they still
have more work to do to earn their certifications, if I ran a school,
I&amp;#39;d love to have any of them teaching my CS classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not planning on writing much about the programming and data
structure classes except possibly through the methods eye because both
of those courses are pretty well established and cut and dry but I do
plan to write at least the following: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The methods course 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More on the methods course 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The topics course 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Use of tools for remote teaching 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our overall philosophy in designing and running the program.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, stay tuned for more.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Varying Remote Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/varying-remote-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 08:33:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/varying-remote-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
When we first went remote I jumped on Zoom. I already new the
technology and it most simulated a live class. Basically, it was the
best combination if quick, easy, and effective and we were under the
gun to get something going and give our students some sense of
normalcy and continuity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we settled in though, it made sense to try some different
things. One was the &amp;#34;lab packet.&amp;#34; A self contained document with
instructions and partial walkthroughs. One of my classes is already
set up to do a number of labs in this way so that was an easy thing to
try.  Basically it ended up being an asynchronous experience with me
being available using the usual suspects - Slack and email. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tried something different this past Monday. It was synchronous with
me available on Slack but we didn&amp;#39;t use Zoom. I set up a series of
videos. Each video was fairly short and most had a small assignment at
the end. I asked the class to fill out a form after each
video/assignment. The topic was binary trees.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The whole process seemed to go well but I&amp;#39;ll report back once I&amp;#39;ve
finished going over the feedback emails I&amp;#39;ve gotten from the class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m particularly proud of this video that I made for the class, enjoy:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OvwIyQJ-s40&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s okay, I Get It</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 14:13:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-get-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was reading Mary Clair Wright&amp;#39;s new &lt;a href=&#34;https://computationalthinkinginroom112.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; the other day. It&amp;#39;s always
great to see another teacher sharing publicly online.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One line caught my eye in her &lt;a href=&#34;https://computationalthinkinginroom112.com/2020/04/07/ap-csa-enrichment-gone-awry/&#34;&gt;latest post&lt;/a&gt; - 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;
Remote instruction is weird, I can’t see them. I have to trust that they will message me with questions.
&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a real problem. It&amp;#39;s hard enough in a regular class where we
can pick up an all sorts of cues and use all sorts formal and informal
assessments but when the students are on the other end of a
teleconference or even more challenging an email or chat it&amp;#39;s even
harder.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also a reminder of how important those non verbal clues and
student feedback can be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s great if we can create an environment where our students will ask
for help if they don&amp;#39;t know something but even under normal
circumstances there&amp;#39;s the danger of students thinking they get
it. If a student is totally lost they&amp;#39;ll usually know they&amp;#39;re totally
lost but after that, it&amp;#39;s not so clear. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A student might think they get it if they can basically follow along
with what&amp;#39;s being presented. It&amp;#39;s pretty easy to watch another student
or a teacher go through explaining a solution step by step and think
you really know what&amp;#39;s going on. Similarly they can read through an
example in a text or on a web site and think they understand. A little
better is when they can do the first couple of problems in the book
but those frequently mimic the samples and don&amp;#39;t require any
additional insight. Even in a traditional class a student can go week
to week like this and really think they understand things and then
they get hit over the head on a test or right before a big assignment
is due. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t the student&amp;#39;s fault. It&amp;#39;s hard to know what you don&amp;#39;t know
and truth be told, we don&amp;#39;t really teach our students how to study and
self assess. It&amp;#39;s also really hard for teachers to assess this even in
person. Now that we&amp;#39;re all remote it&amp;#39;s yet another huge red flag to
look out for.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No solutions here today and no suggestions just yet another concern as
we continue to work to do right by our kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limitations Of Remote Teaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/limitations-of-remote-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:41:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/limitations-of-remote-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While tools like Zoom, Slack and others are a tremendous boon as we&amp;#39;re
forced to do all our teaching remotely the limitations become apparent
as we settle in and try to go beyond the basics of an offsite meeting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-review-2/&#34;&gt;code review&lt;/a&gt; day in my CS1 class. It&amp;#39;s a lesson that I enjoy
teaching and I think my students get a lot out of it. Today we had to
do it remote. The mechanics were largely the same:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pair off the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Have them write out a commentary on their partners code without discussion
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
pair off again
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Have one review the others code but this time via discussion and
note taking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Get everyone together and discuss
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Zoom supported all the basics. Splitting the class was pretty easy via
the breakout room interface and students were able to flag me when
they wanted to bring me in to their breakout. It was also pretty easy
to move newcomers into a room. There were some interface nits that
Zoom has to address like how when I entered and left a breakout room I
ended up losing part of the breakout window interface but I figured
out a workaround.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big difference and limitation was that I couldn&amp;#39;t just lurk. In
a live in person class, I get a top down view. I can basically see what all the
pairs are doing. I can&amp;#39;t get the details from a distance but I can
basically see what&amp;#39;s going on. I can also sidle over near a group to
see how they&amp;#39;re doing without being obtrusive. I can also see some of
the students screens and notebooks to get the gist of what&amp;#39;s going on
and focus in on individual conversations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can&amp;#39;t do these things with Zoom and I daresay you can&amp;#39;t with any
remote conferencing platform. When I wasn&amp;#39;t in a breakout room I was
alone in the main room. When I was in a breakout room it was obvious I
joined and that in and of itself changed the room dynamic. I also
couldn&amp;#39;t see anything the kids were writing on paper or on screen
unless they explicitly shared it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this changes the dynamic big time and limits my effectiveness
as a teacher. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t take this to mean I&amp;#39;m down on Zoom. I&amp;#39;m really loving the tool
and without it or similar products my students would be getting &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; 
less during this crisis. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s just a reminder that teaching is a contact sport and as much as
some people will tell you otherwise the best instruction is in person
in a small class with a knowledgeable dynamic teacher. We&amp;#39;re not
getting back there this semester but here&amp;#39;s hoping that we get back by
Fall.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Necessity is the mother of invention</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mother-of-invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 18:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mother-of-invention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t expect to read a Fred Wilson post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2020/03/teaching-online/&#34;&gt;teaching online&lt;/a&gt; but
that&amp;#39;s what I found when I visited &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/&#34;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt; this morning. Don&amp;#39;t get me
wrong - I suspect that Fred has the makings of a great teacher, it&amp;#39;s
just not what I expected to find. There have been many posts about
education but I don&amp;#39;t recall any about teaching or more specifically
the art of teaching. I did find &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com/2011/07/teaching/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; though which actually speaks
to some of the thoughts today&amp;#39;s post got churning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fred describes what sounds like a typical &amp;#34;lecture style&amp;#34; lesson he&amp;#39;s
delivered numerous times. This time, it would be delivered via
Zoom. Now, Zoom is great but it&amp;#39;s harder to do an interactive
lecture - ie active learning online than it is to do in person which
is what I&amp;#39;m guessing led him to set up some starter Google sheets and
use these shared documents for an active project based class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the post, now that he came up with what sounds like
a much stronger approach. Fred wonders if he&amp;#39;ll ever teach this class
any other way. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first thing I thought was that this would be even better in
person. I don&amp;#39;t know the specifics but I could think of a number of
ways of running this. All in person with time to work on the
spreadsheets is one. Giving some pre-work and the sheets and then pick
up somewhere in the middle is another. In person gives the feel - the
live interaction where a teacher can read the class but there&amp;#39;s no
reason why we can&amp;#39;t also leverage tech tools like shared Google
sheets in a live classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then I got thinking about necessity being the mother of
invention. Nothing stops us from changing things up, from trying
something in normal times but when the norm is disrupted sometimes it
spurs creativity or changes focus. I
try to continually evolve as a teacher but I&amp;#39;m no better than anyone
else and get caught in ruts. I force myself to try new
things. Sometimes they work and it&amp;#39;s great and sometimes &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/try-something-new/&#34;&gt;they
don&amp;#39;t&lt;/a&gt;. Live and learn. On the other hand, when all if a sudden you can&amp;#39;t do things the
usual way the brain works on alternatives. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One example was the lesson where I
&amp;#34;invented&amp;#34; live coding. It was a direct result of a forced change -
for some reason, and I don&amp;#39;t recall why, I couldn&amp;#39;t do things the way I
wanted that day so I winged it. Years later, I was chatting with a
former student and he, out of the blue mentioned that that lesson had
a profound influence on him. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Right now, I&amp;#39;m teaching using Zoom, slack, videos and email. Not being
in a room with my kids sucks. I feel less connected and it&amp;#39;s much
harder to read the class. What am I doing? On the one hand, I&amp;#39;m not
trying to change that much at once as I want my students to have some
stability in an uncertain time but I am working on new things. The
nice thing is that whatever I come up with I can share with my fellow
teachers here and take with me back into the classroom. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was my big takeaway but the post also reminded me of why I turn
to teachers before I turn to &amp;#34;the research&amp;#34; or policy makers on how to
teach. Fred described the evolution of a lesson and a teaching
technique. What he essentially described is what teachers do every day
and we have to do it accounting for all the variables that the
research can&amp;#39;t. We teach multiple classes a day every day of the
week. We try things, assess the results, rinse and repeat. I get that
all teachers don&amp;#39;t do this but the good ones do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final thought I had was with the reality that while coming up with
interesting active learning experiences is great it also takes a lot
of time and there&amp;#39;s not much time when you&amp;#39;re teaching five classes a
day five days a week to 150 kids along with grading, advising, and
everything else. This is why I tell young teachers that you always
want to evolve and improve but not every lesson is going to be a home
run and that&amp;#39;s okay.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s particularly important for teachers to remember this now as
across the nation they&amp;#39;re re-inventing their syllabi on the fly to
move from in person to online and they&amp;#39;re doing it without time,
training, and in some cases tools. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do the best you can and continue to develop your toolset. Not every
new online experience will be great but if they&amp;#39;re sincere, your kids
will know. In the end we&amp;#39;ll all be okay and back to normal but with a
whole bunch of new tricks up our sleeves.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Problems</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 08:12:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I organize a monthly professional development session for CS
teachers. It&amp;#39;s targeted at teachers who are beyond the beginner stage
and don&amp;#39;t want yet another hello world blinky arduino scratch
workshop. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, given the need for CS teachers we need
plenty of beginner workshops but we also need to take teachers to the
next level. I refer to my workshops as being for teachers of APCS-A,
similar, or beyond. Participants get three hours of CTLE credit and
thanks to our gracious hosts at &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; get to use a great space
and enjoy a free meal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly enjoyed last weeks workshop for two reasons. One is
that we talked about &amp;#34;interesting problems.&amp;#34; This in itself is
interesting because different teachers find different things
interesting. For me, this time around, I was thinking of problems that
could be approached by beginners but had some interesting insight that
allowed them to look at the problem differently and solve it more
efficiently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second reason I liked this session is because I wasn&amp;#39;t the only
one presenting!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started the session talking about the Happy Ladybugs problem - a
Hackerrank problem I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then passed off to Justin who talked about finding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull&#34;&gt;convex hull&lt;/a&gt;
bounding a set of points. Justin talked about how you can relate this
abstract geometry problem to real world problems like bounding
neighborhoods as well as how this can be graphically motivated and
then moved to discussing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull_algorithms&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;. Students can pretty easily come
up with a in inefficient O(n^4) solution and then Justin talked about
incrementally guiding them through alternate solutions ending with
something that runs in O(nlgn). At the end of the day we had a problem
that could be done in a variety of ways with students at different
levels of experience. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then moved to Barry&amp;#39;s presentation of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baphl.org/20/&#34;&gt;puzzle hunt&lt;/a&gt; problem he
adapted. It involved decoding, translation, number bases and Barry
uses it as a platform to work with stacks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I finished the evening talking about three problems but we didn&amp;#39;t look
at solutions. These were teasers for next time when we also hope to do a
SIGCSE recap.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers Pay Teachers - part 2 - the report</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 10:03:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Continuing from yesterday, what about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.govtech.com/computing/Report-Most-Teacher-Created-Online-English-Materials-Subpar.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://fordhaminstitute.org/national/research/supplemental-curriculum-bazaar&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; on pay
and free teacher resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The report looked at three sources - one pay and two free. They came
up with a number of results but I think they largely missed the point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Their bottom line conclusion was that &amp;#39;Overall, reviewers rate most
of the materials as “mediocre” or “probably not worth using”.&amp;#39; They
also didn&amp;#39;t seem to find that neither the for profit or free sources
were universally better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The one thing I can agree with though is that a consistent rating
system for the types of resources found on these sites would be very
helpful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think the main problem with the report has to do with what they were
looking for. They concluded things like the resources didn&amp;#39;t line up
well with standards, didn&amp;#39;t have good assessments, didn&amp;#39;t address
cultural diversity and a few other &amp;#34;didn&amp;#39;t dos,&amp;#34;  As I said, I think they
missed the point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It felt to me that the reviewers were looking for rote
experiences. Download a lesson and follow the script.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what reformers would have you think, that isn&amp;#39;t
teaching. A teacher new to a class might start with a well worked out
curriculum and largely follow it verbatim but as they develop their
chops they&amp;#39;ll want the curriculum and all related materials to become
their own.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A downloaded resource, taken as is, will likely not address a specific
classes cultural diversity, at least not more than in the general
sense because it was designed for the authors class and that&amp;#39;s a good
thing. It&amp;#39;s up to the person doing the downloading to take the
resource and then adapt it for their students in their situation. This
is why most of the items that the report considers bad to me are both
inevitable and fine. There is no universal lesson that you can cut and
paste to all schools. To expect it is rubbish.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the CS side, there&amp;#39;s a good amount of sharing of materials as well
as providers well, providing content. Some is free some not but there
is a lot available. Forgetting about whole curricula resources, three
lesson / experience sites  I&amp;#39;m
reasonably familiar with are the SIGCSE &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Nifty Assignments&lt;/a&gt; and now the
CSTA&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/cstaniftyassignments/&#34;&gt;corresponding project&lt;/a&gt; along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.engage-csedu.org/&#34;&gt;Engage CS&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest problem with the Nifty sites is that they&amp;#39;re arranged
chronologically by the conference year they were presented. There are
no tags nor easy way to search.  Engage CS gives you some level of
searching like for course level, keyword, resource type, and more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The sites present resources in a format that&amp;#39;s superficially
 consistent but the truth is, once you get past the headings they can
 be written up in radically different ways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me, that&amp;#39;s not a problem. Each resource was written by some
educator with the intent of sharing but since each author is unique so
to will be the content they produce. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The real value of all these resources are to get ideas - lesson
motivations, code samples, project ideas etc.. Sure, I wish they were
more discoverable via search - better tagged and yes, even better
rated but the value is from reading what some other teacher has done
and then pulling out aspects that can work for you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve rarely used a Nifty Assignment nor something from EngageCS
explicitly but I have gotten value from both sites (CSTA Nifty
assignments are newer and I&amp;#39;ve been at all the CSTA sessions so
haven&amp;#39;t actually used the site). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Would I ever use a resources &amp;#34;as published?&amp;#34; Perhaps - if
it was really well aligned with how I do things. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Would I pay? Probably not. I&amp;#39;m not against paying for resources from a
philosophical point of view. Charge a fair price and give a reasonable
assurance that what you&amp;#39;re selling has value and provide some value
beyond the free sites. I haven&amp;#39;t used Teachers Pay Teachers and
probably won&amp;#39;t look at Amazon&amp;#39;s thing when it&amp;#39;s launched but to me,
they would have to bring value in terms of curation and search. If
they do at a fair price, then they may be worth using.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started teaching there was no public internet. None of this
existed. Teachers kept binders or books of lesson plans and if you
were lucky you could borrow from a friend or colleague. New York&amp;#39;s DOE
at one point had a few teachers in each subject area submit lesson
plans for &amp;#34;lesson books&amp;#34; which they published for each core
subject. My chairman wrote some of the math ones and those materials
largely got me through my first year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we have an embarrassment of riches. That comes with the price
that we have to actually read and evaluate all of the materials we&amp;#39;re
presented with but I&amp;#39;ll take today&amp;#39;s resources over what I started with
any day.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers Pay Teachers  - part 1 - should they</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 08:43:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-pay-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There was a bit of buzz a couple of months ago when Amazon announced
an online marketplace for educational resources. It wasn&amp;#39;t a new
concept - on the pay side, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.teacherspayteachers.com/?msclkid=a426c2c1625613061bc19ce4cdcb6a0a&amp;amp;utm_source=bing&amp;amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Search%2520-%2520Branded%2520-%2520Desktop&amp;amp;utm_term=teachers%2520pay%2520teachers&amp;amp;utm_content=Brand%2520Name&#34;&gt;Teachers Pay Teachers&lt;/a&gt; has been around for a
while and in terms of free, there are many online resources but
they&amp;#39;re not necessarily well organized or curated. What was the buzz?
Should teachers be charging their peers for class materials or should
they be providing them for free.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was going to blog about it then but never got around to it The other
day, someone posted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.govtech.com/computing/Report-Most-Teacher-Created-Online-English-Materials-Subpar.html&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article which questioned the quality of both
free resources and pay ones. The article, based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://fordhaminstitute.org/national/research/supplemental-curriculum-bazaar&#34;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt; by the
Fordham Institute looked at ELA resources. The report also only looked
at Teachers Pay Teachers and two free sites - ReadWriteThink and Share
My Lesson excluding many other teacher resources that could be, for
all we know, better curated and more discoverable. As an aside, I was
turned off by the reports referring to their evaluators as &amp;#34;experts&amp;#34;
which is a description I personally would question. Still, there&amp;#39;s
some good fodder for thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll get to the report in the next post but for now let&amp;#39;s tackle the
question that started the initial buzz - should teachers be charging
each other for materials?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It depends. If you&amp;#39;re paid by a school to develop materials they
belong to the school. In NY you can take a sabbatical to build a
course so anything you build during that time would be DOE property
and therefore you couldn&amp;#39;t sell it. Same thing if you&amp;#39;re being paid
off hours to develop materials. The gray area comes when you&amp;#39;re lesson
planning. Most real planning and development happens outside of
school hours. In an typical school day teacher are typically
allocated around 40 minutes to do all their planing, grading,
and paperwork so realistically most materials as well as planing,
paperwork, and grading are done off hours. This being the case, I&amp;#39;m of
the belief that those materials belong to the teacher (although I&amp;#39;ve
met some DOE educrats who would disagree).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, should they sell it? Well, they have every right to. That said, my
personal feelings and practice is that if you&amp;#39;ve developed something
for yourself and have not spent extra time or effort to prepare it for
others then I think you should make it freely available to your
peers. On the other hand, if you spend extra time and effort to make
it useful for and usable by others then by all means charge if you&amp;#39;d
like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll tackle the report in the next post and we&amp;#39;ll look at some of the
resources available on the CS side.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GitHub issues for class communicatoin</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/git-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 16:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/git-issues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last week I talked about using &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/&#34;&gt;GitHub issues&lt;/a&gt; as a mechanism for class
communication. I thought it might be helpful to follow up on it and
also felt that a video would be better than text.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, here it is, 16 minutes on how you can use GitHub issues for class
communication. I don&amp;#39;t show examples of everything like @ tagging but
I think it shows some of the power of using GitHub and GitHub
classroom beyond just a software repo and versioning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SNsjMKYoLr8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 1 - cleaning the data</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 16:18:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I run periodic professional development sessions here in New York with
my partner in crime JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver. I call them PD for &amp;#34;APCS-A,
similar or beyond&amp;#34; and they&amp;#39;re designed to fill a professional
development gap. We try to run them once a month but it&amp;#39;s a little
less frequent than that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The NYCDOE has taken on the monster task of CS for all and since
they&amp;#39;re trying to get to everyone they have to run a bazillion
sessions but all at an introductory level. Beyond that, most PD is
tied to a curriculum, program, or product. We decided to run sessions
for teachers who are ready for more both pedagogically and content
wise while not affiliating with any specific provider. We&amp;#39;re just
about the CS and the teaching of CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday we had our first session of the year and the content topic
was text processing. Along the way, we used it as an opportunity to
highlight subgoal labeling as a teaching technique.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a lot you can do in both CS0 and CS1 with text and document
processing. By the end of yesterday&amp;#39;s session we had discussed a bunch
of possibilities based on the text processing technique known as a
&amp;#34;bag of words&amp;#34; which basically takes a text and just considers all the
words it contains. What are the words and how many times does each
word occurs. No consideration of order, grammar, or anything else. Just
words and counts. We also talked a bit about more advanced possibilities
like playing with an inverted index. I&amp;#39;ll talk about both of those in
a future post. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For today, let&amp;#39;s talk about what we have to do before we even begin -
preprocessing the data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We grabbed a bunch of texts from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gutenberg.org/&#34;&gt;Project Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically, &amp;#34;Moby
Dick&amp;#34;, a translation of my favorite play &amp;#34;Cyrano de Bergerac&amp;#34; and the
Book of Psalms from the Bible. I also made a copy of the first chapter
of &amp;#34;Moby Dick&amp;#34; so we had a shorter corpus to play with and typed up
the first scene of &amp;#34;Macbeth&amp;#34; - all thirteen lines of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s easy enough to read in the data in a language like Python:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;f &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;cyrano.txt&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
raw_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; f&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;read()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but if you&amp;#39;re using a bag of words you&amp;#39;ve got to do some cleaning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, all Project Gutenberg texts contain a whole bunch of front
and back matter with lots of words. If you don&amp;#39;t get rid of them
you&amp;#39;ll get extra words in your bag. I forgot to do this and was a bit
surprised to see phrases like &amp;#34;Pay a trademark license&amp;#34; in the Book of
Psalms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s easy enough to just cut the tops and bottoms of each file off
with an editor and that&amp;#39;s when we can read our data into our program
and the fun begins.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First we had to turn everything into lower case;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; raw_data&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;lower()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and then the big part - we want to get rid of all the punctuation. We
first tried something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;stuff_to_remove &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;.:;&amp;#39;0123456789&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_letters &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; stuff_to_remove]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join(cleaned_letters)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second line is a list comprehension. It iterates through each
letter in lower_data and copies it into the resultant list only if the
letter is not in our stuff_to_remove list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if we had &lt;code&gt;lower_data = &amp;#34;abc123def g&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt; we&amp;#39;d get a result
of &lt;code&gt;[&amp;#34;a&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;b&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;c&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;d&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;e&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;f&amp;#34;,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;,&amp;#34;g&amp;#34;]&lt;/code&gt;. We then use the join in line 3
to turn it back into a string &lt;code&gt;&amp;#34;abcdef g&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This worked pretty well but we found that there were problems. There
were characters that we didn&amp;#39;t account for like long dashes that
connected words and we didn&amp;#39;t have an easy way to put them in our
removal string.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This led to take 2. Instead of deciding what to throw away, let&amp;#39;s
decide what to keep;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;stuff_to_keep &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;abcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyz &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\t\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_letters &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; stuff_to_remove]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join(cleaned_letters)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This worked better (and yes, I know I could have used isalpha() but I
didn&amp;#39;t remember it at the time) but still had problems. We had words
that were formerly separated by punctuation with no spaces that were
now combined into new invalid words. We also had things like chapter
headings in our text and other stray words that we probably wanted to
get rid of.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this led to rich conversation among the teachers present and
can do the same in class. What do you clean? What do you keep? Is it
worth the effort to write all sorts of cleaning code to get rid of a
couple of stray bits of bad data or can we get the results we want by
leaving it in? There&amp;#39;s no universally right answer and that&amp;#39;s part of
the beauty of doing things like this with a class - it&amp;#39;s something
that can make them think.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we made our final cleaning decisions it&amp;#39;s a simple matter to
convert the long string of text into a list of words:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;wordlist &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; cleaned_string&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we&amp;#39;re ready to start building our bag of words but that&amp;#39;s a post
for another day.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Ap Registration - it&#39;s, um, for the kids</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I stumbled upon a thread over in the APCS-A Facebook group the other
day. It seems that the College Board is making some changes in their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apcentral.collegeboard.org/about-ap/news-changes/ap-2019&#34;&gt;registration timeline&lt;/a&gt;. In the past, students registered for the exam
sometime in March with the exams administered in May. The new changes
include requiring registration in November along with $40 late
registration and cancellation fees.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The College Board is, of course, spinning this as for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3MCNEYCZWqw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;fbclid=IwAR04Uuj7vpHoYU_8jMjw00YpAPXp7gi3MDGdTKhzpUXv7mI0OILW01KyzvA%0A&#34;&gt;the student&amp;#39;s
benefit&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At least a portion of the teaching community thinks otherwise and has
in fact started &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.change.org/p/demand-the-college-board-not-mandate-fall-ap-exam-requirements-and-deadlines&#34;&gt;this petition&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me this is just another money grab by the College Board - an
organization that already has way too much influence over high school
education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s take a look at what the College Board actually brings to the
table. They offer an exam. A single exam in each subject offered
that&amp;#39;s supposed to in 3 hours encapsulate an entire years&amp;#39;s worth of
learning and from that, colleges might give  a student placement or
credit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you say &amp;#34;they offer so much more.&amp;#34; Do they?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teacher&amp;#39;s have to submit syllabi and the college board approves
them. They offer samples but so do text book authors and third party
organizations. In my case I rolled my own. The teacher also develops
the course. Does the College Board provide materials? I guess, but so
do those same groups that provide curricula. The college board
certainly doesn&amp;#39;t define the subject. Last I checked Calculus, was
pretty well defined way before the AP program. So was 
Chemistry, and most other subjects. Actually, due to their outsized
influence they do define the subset of the subject in some cases and
we should really be questioning this influence. Finally, the teacher does
the actual hard job of teaching the class. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m  just not seeing the value added. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re already seeing schools require that students take the exam to be
in the class or provide &amp;#34;incentives&amp;#34; like a credit or grade bump for
taking the exam or even removing the AP designation from the
transcript if the student doesn&amp;#39;t take the exam. Doing any of these is
just plain wrong. By all means explain the advantages and
disadvantages of taking the exam but to essentially force a student to
fork over money and personal data to an outside independent agency is
just plain wrong. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But you say that students in many districts don&amp;#39;t have to pay. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is even more insidious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now it&amp;#39;s the taxpayer on the hook and the College Board has
successfully created an everlasting cash pipeline from the public into
private coffers while providing questionable value.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t agree with me and think that these requirements or
incentives  are fine ask yourself this: If you had a child in a class
and the teacher said &amp;#34;your child has to sit in a room with a friend of
mine for three hours, give them $100 and personal data and I will give
your child a higher grade&amp;#34; you&amp;#39;d be outraged. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spending three hours taking an external exam has no bearing on what a
student did or didn&amp;#39;t do in the class so the grades, credits etc
should be the same whether or not the kid took the AP exam.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s get back to the early registration changes. Currently kids
register for the AP exam in March. By then students might know what
college they&amp;#39;re likely to go to. They&amp;#39;ll know if the AP exam is of any
use to them. In November they don&amp;#39;t. I frequently lost some high
scores on AP exams because I had top students who were accepted early
to schools that didn&amp;#39;t award credit. I also lost a couple of low
scores of students that for whatever reasons had no chance at getting
a 3 or higher so opted not to sit for the exam. I guess the College Board came up
with a good way to get money for those kids without providing value in
return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are block scheduled schools or other situations where kids
don&amp;#39;t start the class until after the new November deadline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, let&amp;#39;s talk a bit about the College Board&amp;#39;s claim that this is
all for the students. The video talks about students doing better if
they signed up earlier. I&amp;#39;m skeptical but even if it&amp;#39;s true, is &amp;#34;doing
better on the AP exam&amp;#34; the goal we have for our students. How about
learning our subject area or being inspired to continue on with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the video, teachers talk about how the kids are more motivated and
focused because the exam. This is getting to sound a lot like the
inane focus on high stakes test where the test is the goal. Is the
motivation that &amp;#34;you paid the $100&amp;#34; so it&amp;#39;s wasted if you don&amp;#39;t do
well or &amp;#34;the school paid $100&amp;#34; so we&amp;#39;ll guilt you into studying more?
Sorry, as teachers we can do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure I&amp;#39;ll get some flak for writing this but I also suspect that
there are many teachers who agree with me that the College Board is
not looking out for students but rather themselves.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Scripts To Freestyle</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 17:35:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/from-scripts-to-freestyle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I just read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@bethanymarz/going-off-script-b69345fc5904&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bethanymarz&#34;&gt;Bethany Crystal&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@bethanymarz/going-off-script-b69345fc5904&#34;&gt;Going off script&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bethany writes that while she normally essentially scripts important
presentations, this time she went more off the cuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It made me think about how I teach and a disturbing trend I&amp;#39;ve
seen in CS education and education in general.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never strictly used a script for teaching. When I started I did
use &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; detailed lesson plans. Back then I was teaching math. It
was also pre internet or at least pre internet as we now know
it. I had an account on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.panix.com/&#34;&gt;Panix&lt;/a&gt; and the internet did indeed exist but
you couldn&amp;#39;t just look for teaching materials. I actually remember
bringing a modem in to Seward Park one day and showing a bunch of kids
this up and coming thing called the internet. I showed them usernet
news, a gopher server and a couple of other things.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of teaching materials, you could buy sample lesson plans from
the teacher store near the Board of Ed in Brooklyn. These were books
that were compilations of mostly handwritten lessons. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I basically copied and modified them. I had an &lt;strong&gt;aim&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;do now&lt;/strong&gt; key
questions were written as were definitions and summary
statements. Of course there were numerous sample problems and
exercises, all worked out
in advance. It wasn&amp;#39;t quite a script but it was a very well fleshed
out guide 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I gained experience and also shifted from math which wasn&amp;#39;t my
passion to CS, my plans become sparser. I&amp;#39;d still write down
definitions, maybe some solutions and a list of key points but a lot
of the particulars were gone. I didn&amp;#39;t write out key questions or
solutions to all the problems in advance. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As time went by the plans got sparser still. I&amp;#39;d still list the key
points I&amp;#39;d want to cover as well as notes on tricky parts of the
lesson but more often than not I&amp;#39;ll just go in with a bullet list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s my plan for a recent lesson:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go over cipher soution
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How to we solve if already ciphered?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rotate 26 times.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about using stats
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Frequency of letters - look up
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Find freq of letter in string then use distance formula against
model
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Get frequencies from a book
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
try it in another language
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We didn&amp;#39;t get to the last two bullet items so that&amp;#39;s where we&amp;#39;ll start
off on Monday. This plan was all I needed but it in no way tells the
full story of the lesson to anyone but me. It doesn&amp;#39;t include the
motivation, ancillary stories and materials nor how the lesson was
developed or delivered. I knew how it would play out because I was
teaching it and for me these notes were more than sufficient. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All this is not to say that I don&amp;#39;t spend a lot of time planning my
lessons. I do. I just don&amp;#39;t create detailed scripts. I know what I
want to cover and how I want to cover it. Then it&amp;#39;s just got to the
class and go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big advantage of this is something that Bethany mentioned in her
piece - the ability to &amp;#34;read the room.&amp;#34; This is a big part of
teaching. If you&amp;#39;re following a script, you&amp;#39;re not reading the room
and you&amp;#39;re probably not really teaching the class. You might be
following a script but your students certainly aren&amp;#39;t and once they
veer off program you&amp;#39;ve got to abandon your script or you&amp;#39;re not doing
right by the class. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having a direction but not a script makes it easier to &amp;#34;call and
audible.&amp;#34; That&amp;#39;s what led me to teach the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman/&#34;&gt;question answering system&lt;/a&gt;
lesson the other day. It was unplanned but as a class we were having a
discussion and that&amp;#39;s where it led.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned, when I started out I couldn&amp;#39;t do this. I needed much
more detailed plans. That said, as a teacher gains more experience
they can better connect to their classes and do more for their
students by not sticking to the script, reading the room and adapting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings me to that trend that disturbing trend. I&amp;#39;m talking about
pushing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2013/11/30/teacher-slams-scripted-common-core-lessons-that-must-be-taught-word-for-word/?utm_term=.6afd6d64f1c6&#34;&gt;scripted lessons&lt;/a&gt;. These crop up in charter schools and no
excuse environments and are typically used as ways of &amp;#34;compensating&amp;#34;
for teachers that don&amp;#39;t really know the subject area or how to teach
and to standardize teaching. To me it&amp;#39;s an attack on the teaching
profession. A script is great for a play. It&amp;#39;s great for a speech and
for some presentations but not for teaching. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I understand having something that&amp;#39;s more scripted to use when you&amp;#39;re
faced with novice teachers or teachers that are new to a subject area
but I fear that at times the scripted lessons are the end game.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was talking to a friend a few years ago. He&amp;#39;s doing great work in the
CS Ed space and among other things, he develops curricula. I mentioned
to him that I loved his work (still do) but I was concerned that his
materials were becoming much more scripted. His reply was something
like &amp;#34;I agree with you in theory but the truth is most teachers aren&amp;#39;t
you.&amp;#34; I understood his point as most of the teachers that used his
materials were novices but I disagreed that they were &amp;#34;not me.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m
nothing special. I&amp;#39;m just a reasonably bright guy who works hard at
his craft. If I can teach script free so can anyone. Maybe not at
first, but certainly after time and we subvert our profession by
settling for less. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final note, at this point in my career I actually find it very
hard to use a script - even for a presentation. Over the last couple
of years, I&amp;#39;ve been spending my Falls visiting high schools to talk
about Hunter&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.huntercs.org&#34;&gt;Honors CS&lt;/a&gt; program. As much as I tried, I couldn&amp;#39;t
script a presentation. No matter what I did, when I got in front of
the students I just ended up doing my thing and talking to them. At
the end of the day I ended up working things backwards. Over my first
few school visits, I developed a set of key points that I kept coming
back to and finally ended up with a list of bullet points that I can
pretty much follow when I do the &amp;#34;navigating from high school to
college in tech&amp;#34; talk. I guess I&amp;#39;m now working in reverse. Starting
free style and working back to a script.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium  and other blog sites you
might get the idea that you&amp;#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The
internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful
lessons they&amp;#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in
professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests
for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that
worked for them or things they think will work. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, for new teachers it can create an unhealthy illusion of what
really goes on in the classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that sharing of the good stuff is a bad thing but
the truth is that not every lesson is a masterpiece, not every teacher
is a super charismatic showman, and not all topics lend themselves to
creative teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing this now? Because I was planning lessons earlier
today and I&amp;#39;m at one of those places where I&amp;#39;m not going to be able to
deliver a whiz-bang lesson in my next class. One of my classes this
semester is for beginners so we&amp;#39;re building up language skills from
the ground up. Right now I want to do some loop applications but
there&amp;#39;s only so much we can do given what the students know. There are
reasons why I don&amp;#39;t want to do graphics with them right now. I also
haven&amp;#39;t introduced lists yet and don&amp;#39;t want to loop over strings yet
so I&amp;#39;m left with doing mathy stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ll look at Newton&amp;#39;s method for square roots. It&amp;#39;s
interesting for the math inclined and does let us explore issues with
floating point and accuracy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not going to be super exciting for everyone though and that&amp;#39;s okay. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could do lists first but I don&amp;#39;t want the kids to have to handle so
much new material so quickly. I&amp;#39;d rather keep the pace slower and work
with what they&amp;#39;ve just learned for a bit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could also do graphics but that adds a level of overhead I don&amp;#39;t
want to get into now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea is to look at the long game. A class runs a whole semester or
possibly a year. You&amp;#39;re going to have some special memorable lessons
and some mundane ones and that&amp;#39;s nothing to be ashamed of. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re still mostly going to see best practices shared online with only
a few brave souls sharing disaster classes and asking for help. That&amp;#39;s
just how the internet works. It&amp;#39;s not the worst thing in the
world. Just remember when you&amp;#39;re struggling to come up with a good
lesson or you&amp;#39;ve just taught a bad one that tomorrow&amp;#39;s will be
better. Judge yourself by your students long term development, not one
day at a time.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>