<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CS For All on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs-for-all/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (CS For All)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 08:27:20 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs-for-all/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Pushback To CS for All</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pushback-to-csforall/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 08:27:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pushback-to-csforall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
On the last day of 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/audreywatters&#34;&gt;Audrey Waters&lt;/a&gt; wrote a great piece on &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackeducation.com/2019/12/31/what-a-shitshow&#34;&gt;The 100
Worst Ed-Tech Debacles of the Decade&lt;/a&gt;. I agree with most of them but
felt it was worth looking at a one in particular. Specifically number 6 -
&amp;#34;Everyone Should earn to Code.&amp;#34;  I might dive in to some others later
but we&amp;#39;ll stick with number 6 for today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I read over these right after reading two recent posts by Alina Adam&amp;#39;s
son Gregory - a sophomore at Stuyvesant High School over on Alina&amp;#39;s blog
&lt;a href=&#34;https://newyorkschooltalk.org/2019/12/what-is-computer-science-the-doe-doesnt-know-cs4all-part-2/&#34;&gt;questioning NYC&amp;#39;s CS For All initiative&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Audrey made some very good points on CS for All (or everyone should
learn to code). It&amp;#39;s industry driven - giving them more of an outsized
influence over education and she questions the tech job crisis. I&amp;#39;ll
personally add that it&amp;#39;s problematic that so much of the emphasis -
particularly in the public schools is CS for jobs. I get it - a well
paying job is a ticket up the economic ladder and this can be a huge
deal for low income families. That said, it&amp;#39;s problematic at best when
the attitude is education for jobs for the poor and well rounded
education for life for  the rich.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While Audrey wrote on 100 items a few paragraphs each, Gregory wrote two
posts on CS for All in NYC and pushed back hard. One line that
resonated with me was his response to the DOE&amp;#39;s claim that &amp;#34; “Students
with computer science degrees are some of the highest-paid college
graduates”  responding with:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;You know what else is a very useful skill for jobs and graduating
college? Reading comprehension and basic mathematics skills.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was a sticking point with me that got me in trouble with DOE on
the AFSE project. They insisted the high school would create industry
ready software engineers our of high school in spite of them coming in
well below grade level. They were wrong. CS is not a substitute for
other important subjects. I personally do think CS for All is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; 
important and I&amp;#39;ll address that shortly but I view it as one more
fundamental - in addition to reading and writing not at the expense
of.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now let me push back on the pushback.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS as a K12 academic discipline is very young. In NYC, things didn&amp;#39;t
really get rolling until &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fredwilson&#34;&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt; (from industry) started to push
things around 10 years go. There were some other small efforts at individual
schools and regions around the country. The national movement, in
spite of the CSTA being in existence for twenty years or more  didn&amp;#39;t
gain any real traction until code.org came onto the scene - also driven by
industry. While I agree very much with Audrey and other&amp;#39;s concerns
about industry&amp;#39;s outsized influence and have publicly criticized
code.org and others on it without Fred, CS Ed doesn&amp;#39;t happen in NYC
and without Hadi Partovi I&amp;#39;d guess that there wouldn&amp;#39;t be the national
push either.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is all to say that the field is young so addressing what I think
are Gregory&amp;#39;s core points, depending on the teacher, a student&amp;#39;s CS
experience can be a total waste of time or it can be life changing in
a good way. This is also true of other subject areas. A bad teacher
can destroy a kid in any subject area as much as good one can
uplift. This will be more of a problem in CS until the system starts
to produce properly prepared teachers - teachers who know both the CS
content and how to teach it. That will take some time and we&amp;#39;re
starting to do that at Hunter. On the other hand, we&amp;#39;ll never get
there unless we start. In the long run, CS teachers should be of
comparable quality to teachers of other disciplines which is, of
course, another can of worms to dig into.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Putting that aside, I&amp;#39;ll also push back on the pushback that teaching
CS isn&amp;#39;t valuable for everyone and I&amp;#39;ll do that on two fronts. The
first is in response to Gregory&amp;#39;s contention that &amp;#34;Computer science will
have very few applications for most people later in life.&amp;#34; While most
people won&amp;#39;t become professional programmers or software engineers
many (most?) people will work with data. It could be some deep
analysis or it could be merely managing company or personal
contacts. A rudimentary background in programming allows one to
automate data processing and focus on the core task. A much simpler
example of this is typing when writing. If you can type, you can focus
fully on the content you&amp;#39;re producing. If you can&amp;#39;t your focus is
split - part on the content and part on the keys. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We teach a variety of subjects. We teach languages in spite of the
fact that we don&amp;#39;t require students learn them to fluency. Everyone
has to take some classes in the arts, multiple sciences, economics,
math - some of which makes sense and some maybe not so much, English
and more. Is CS any less important than taking a smattering of French?
How about Algebra 2 and Trig?  A year of bio, chem, and physics?
Students should be exposed to many fields and I think it would be hard
for an honest person to say that CS is less important that every
single one of the other required classes we force upon our
students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When students are struggling with fundamentals - math/English some
want to put more resources into them - usually at the expense of the
arts - there are many people, myself included that feel that this is a
 &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; mistake. All our students should be entitled to a well rounded
education. They should take art and music, and have the opportunity to
learn an instrument. They should be exposed to a myriad of subjects,
ways of thinking, and yes, things that will lead to possible career
paths. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS is one of these subjects. It&amp;#39;s just the new kid on the block. This is
the other reason why CS for All (beyond &amp;#34;Eveveryone should program&amp;#34;)
is so important. It&amp;#39;s not that CS should replace art or music or
another important subject but that our students deserve to be exposed
to it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some will quibble that there&amp;#39;s no room but, at least in NY State
there is - I looked over the requirements and in fact, you can have 3
years of CS in High School along with all the requirements plus a
couple of other electives but I&amp;#39;m not advocating for that. I&amp;#39;m also
not sure that NY&amp;#39;s plan to have CS at every &amp;#34;grade band&amp;#34; is the right
way to go. I think that if you have the right experience you can do
right by the kids in a one year, single period high school
introduction to CS that includes programming (and I&amp;#39;m not talking
APCS-P). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there it is. CS For All or programming for everyone might end up a
debacle and NYC&amp;#39;s CS For All might turn out to be a waste in spite of
the hard work of many strong educators but if that&amp;#39;s the case it&amp;#39;s
going to be due to implementation, politics, and influence not because
all our students won&amp;#39;t benefit from learning CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>