<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>community on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/community/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (community)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 15:43:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/community/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Class Legends</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 15:43:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/class-legends/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s talk about something other than distance learning and COVID-19.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You know you&amp;#39;ve been doing something a long time when you&amp;#39;ve got
legends.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over on my alumni mailing list JonAlf shared a web site showing off
what his current students were doing in their computer graphics
class. Somewhere in the thread, Con replied:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;
Someone should put up a video of the fabulous and fantastically famous
hand animation called FINGER.MDL. It dates from a little before my
time, but stories elevated it to legendary status.
&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Indeed it had reached legendary status. Other projects over the years
including Larry&amp;#39;s anatomically correct robot had also risen to
infamy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A little later in the thread the project&amp;#39;s author Josh chimed in and
shared his original source code. He still had it from May 1995. I&amp;#39;m
not entirely surprised - I had a copy of the code as well. The trouble
is it was written in Turbo-C on a DOS machine. Good luck compiling it
on a modern system. Fortunately, Josh was able to build and run the
project using an emulator. Check out the  marginally NSFW video at the
end of the post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the legend? Well, in addition to being a pretty terrific
project - particularly when you remember the horsepower it was running
on and that it was written by a student who was concurrently finishing
APCS, there&amp;#39;s a story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It starts in one of my APCS classes. Students were working on final
projects. Tom was working on Tetris - an impressive project for APCS
done in Turbo Pascal. Tom wanted to add music to the project and had a
clever way of doing it. Back then you could get basic sounds by
turning on and off the speaker at certain frequencies. Tom had two
arrays, one with frequencies and one with durations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Something like: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;notes&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;440&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;523&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;440&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;659&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;]
durations&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then for the game loop
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#+begin_src python&lt;/span&gt;

  current_note&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
  note &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; notes[current_note]
  duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; durations[current_note]
  play(note) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# starts the note playing until you change or stop it&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; game_not_over:
      duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:
          current_note &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (current_note&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;length(notes)
          note &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; notes[current_note]
          duration &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; durations[current_note]
          play(note) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# starts the note playing until you change or stop it&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# the rest of the game loop&lt;/span&gt;
  stop_playing() &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# stop the speaker&lt;/span&gt;

    

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#+end_src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, he had to figure out all the frequencies and durations for
&amp;#34;Korobeiniki,&amp;#34; the tetris song. The class was more than happy to help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everyone&amp;#39;s working to help figure this out for Tom. It&amp;#39;s all pretty
cool when in walks Jinx Perullo - Stuy&amp;#39;s new principal along with the
President of the New York City Board of Education. The President&amp;#39;s jaw
drops as she hears a cacophony of Tetris music and screen after screen
of Tetris being played!!!!! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jinx makes an abrupt about face and drags the dignitary out of the
room. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward a week or so. We&amp;#39;re in the graphics class at the end of
the day - it was held during an non-existent after school period so
that the students could attend. Josh&amp;#39;s working on his graphics program
at a computer by the door.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jinx walked in again. This time with the school&amp;#39;s chancelor to be
greeted by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ca_8q3ct6J4&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ca_8q3ct6J4&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again, a quick about face.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For some reason Jinx never brought important people to my classes
again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those were indeed the good old days.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Focus To Feel Normal</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 17:46:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Austin Cory Bart tweeted this a little while ago.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I don&amp;#39;t
always consider how much power I have as a faculty. Right now, I&amp;#39;d
really like to expend that power to make my students understand that I
don&amp;#39;t want them focused on my course during a global pandemic. Not
right now. Later, but not right now.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Austin Cory Bart
(@AustinCorgiBart) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AustinCorgiBart/status/1238565390575456262?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March
13, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While Cory&amp;#39;s right about this it&amp;#39;s also good to remember that as
we&amp;#39;re all going remote, focusing on our courses can be important for
our students not merely due to content but in this time of uncertainty
to have something to focus on to remind us of community and remind us
of normal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While all our students are now home or being sent home they&amp;#39;re going
to be in semi isolation. Most will be with families but many will be
isolated from friends and classmates and without our courses, in a
limbo state left to obsess and stress over the current state of
affairs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Focusing on our class  - through synchronous onlinen classes and
mailing lists, working on assignments, and otherwise engaging in this
approximation of our students regular weeks we&amp;#39;re providing a valuable
distraction in addition to whatever actual course material we can
cover.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve seen it before. After 9/11 and to a lesser extent after
Sandy. After 9/11 we were closed for about a a week. Based on the
email list I was able to put together and the back and forths I had
between parents and students stress was high, information and outlets
low. We managed to set up one event that got a bunch of students
together and it was really needed. We restarted classes at Brooklyn
Tech and stayed for close to a month. Classes were half length
starting in the afteroon. I was teaching CS without any real computer
access, some classes shared rooms and in general it&amp;#39;s debatable how
much learning happened. What it did do though, is it gave the kids
something to focus on other than the 9/11 attacks and their
aftermath. It wasn&amp;#39;t normal but it was &amp;#34;normaler.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the years that followed, I&amp;#39;d hear from both parents and students -
a number of whom I never taught about how important it was giving them
something to do other than obsess about the events of the day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same thing after Sandy. Some students weren&amp;#39;t all that affected but
others suffered tremendous losses. We set up virtual classes for a
couple of days while school wasn&amp;#39;t in session. Again, it gave them
something to focus on that wasn&amp;#39;t the superstorm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same thing this time around. We all should be aware and alert to
everything happening but we also need community and things to focus
on. Our classes can be one of those things.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSEvents.nyc</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 18:52:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csevents-nyc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A couple of weeks ago, a handful of CS Ed folks got together. One
issue we discussed was that of finding CS related events both for
students and teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of our conveners, Dan Fenjves of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.upperlinecode.com/&#34;&gt;UPPERLINE CODE&lt;/a&gt; talked about
possibly hosting a central site. Today, Dan announced
&lt;a href=&#34;http://csevents.nyc/.&#34;&gt;http://csevents.nyc/.&lt;/a&gt; A site where organizers can submit and students
and teachers can find upcoming events. Right now it&amp;#39;s NY centric but
it does list some events beyond the city.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re planning an event or CS Educational opportunity, submit it,
if you&amp;#39;re looking for one, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CS Education Subreddit</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 07:37:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cseducation-subreddit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amyjko?ref_src=twsrc%255Etfw%257Ctwcamp%255Etweetembed%257Ctwterm%255E1230982366706860032&amp;amp;ref_url=https%253A%252F%252Fpublish.twitter.com%252F%253Fquery%253Dhttps%25253A%25252F%25252Ftwitter.com%25252Famyjko%25252Fstatus%25252F1230982366706860032%2526widget%253DTweet&#34;&gt;Amy Ko&lt;/a&gt; posted this yesterday:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;CSEd people:
many have struggled to use Twitter for discussion. How about Twitter
for broadcasting, but when replies turn to discussion, we use &lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/2oivuriOoU&#34;&gt;https://t.co/2oivuriOoU&lt;/a&gt;? It&amp;#39;s a
better (albeit imperfect) platform for civil discourse. Subreddit mods
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AustinCorgiBart?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@AustinCorgiBart&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Amy J. Ko (@amyjko) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amyjko/status/1230982366706860032?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February
21, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d love to see more traffic &lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/CSEducation&#34;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;. For full disclosure, I&amp;#39;m one of
the moderators but in my defense, I&amp;#39;m not much of a moderator and as
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AustinCorgiBart/status/1230992957467168768&#34;&gt;Cory&lt;/a&gt; said, I too am happy to either keep moderating or to step aside.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Twitter is nice for broadcasting but not great for
meaty discussions. The character limit does make you think out what
you&amp;#39;re saying but it&amp;#39;s also a headache and tweet storms are an
inelegant solution at best. Once you start mixing in replies threads
become hard to follow. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An interesting case study of Twitter conversation is over at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/home&#34;&gt;Fred
Wilson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s blog  &lt;a href=&#34;https://avc.com&#34;&gt;AVC&lt;/a&gt;. Fred recently rebooted his long standing blog and
is now using Twitter for comments whereas he previously used &lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;.
I haven&amp;#39;t done an in depth analysis but there appears to be far fewer
comments and less in depth conversation than in his blogs past
incarnations. This could just be my perceptions but given the large
readership, it might be an interesting thing to analyze.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to other communication tools, I&amp;#39;ve written about them with respect
to classroom communications &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/class-communications/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Many of the same issues
exist for using these tools as a professional community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Facebook groups are private, undiscoverable, hard to search, and
scattered. They also exist in the Facebook silo. Data goes in but it
never comes out. I also can&amp;#39;t access those Facebook groups using
anything other than Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Email is a great default. Nowhere else to go - things just show up in
your inbox. I&amp;#39;m on the APCS mailing list as well as SIGCSE. One
problem is the no quoting policy which makes threads hard to follow
and discoverability and long term searchability are a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Slack? Just no.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So let&amp;#39;s think about reddit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can go to the site to read it but you can also subscribe using an
RSS/Atom reader like Feedly. If you post a comment you get replies via
email and an alert in reddit. It&amp;#39;s discoverable, public, and
searchable. It even appears to support chats and a wiki.  Hits all the
buttons for me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We could do a better job with the subreddit - add resource links to
the sidebar for instance - I just started to do that now. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cscheerleader/status/1231177418708267008&#34;&gt;Ria&lt;/a&gt; commented on how she wasn&amp;#39;t happy that people could post
anonymously. I tend to agree with her - I&amp;#39;ve always used my real
identity in forums and would prefer others do the same but that&amp;#39;s not
a dealbreaker to me. I&amp;#39;d rather an open community with anonymous
posting allowed than Zuck&amp;#39;s world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another issue that is sure to be raised is openness. Some teachers
don&amp;#39;t want their discussions public where students can find
them. Sometimes this is to separate class from life and sometimes
because class related issues are being discussed. I&amp;#39;ve never had an
issue with this. Having spent close to 30 years in the classroom I&amp;#39;ve
always been pretty open and public. Sure, sometimes a student can find
an old assignment or blog post going over something but so what, maybe
they&amp;#39;ll learn something. The only time I see this as really being an
issue is that you don&amp;#39;t want to talk about specific student issues in
a public forum to protect the students privacy. It&amp;#39;s harder to ask
your colleagues for help with some specific student related problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, much of what I&amp;#39;m guessing Amy was talking about was the CS
Educator type discourse that doesn&amp;#39;t get into those weeds but I see
these communities as for all educators (which I&amp;#39;m sure Amy does as
well, just separating my read on her specific tweet).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, please do join us over in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/CSEducation/&#34;&gt;CSEducation&lt;/a&gt; over on Reddit. If you want
to subscribe via an rss or atom reader just use this link:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/CSEducation.rss&#34;&gt;https://reddit.com/r/CSEducation.rss&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presenting At CSTA 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 13:05:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/presenting-at-csta/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Presenting at CSTA 2020
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I noticed a few tweets and posts from people announcing that they&amp;#39;d be
presenting at CSTA2020 - the big computer science teachers conference
held every July.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A common thread in a few of these were trepidation&amp;#39;s
presenters. Excited to be doing this but nervous.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s interesting that teachers, myself included, sometimes get nervous
before presentations even though we present every day as part of our
jobs. I know it&amp;#39;s different as we have the same kids every day but
even day 1 jitters each semester aren&amp;#39;t the same as the presentation
anxiety that some of us face.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m certainly not a super master seasoned presenter. I&amp;#39;ve done it a
few times at CSTA and other venues and this year JonAlf and I will be
running a GitHub workshop but I thought I&amp;#39;d share some words of
encouragement anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
You&amp;#39;re really just talking shop.
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Basically, you&amp;#39;re a teacher talking about teaching and I think we all
love to do that. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
It&amp;#39;s an audience of friends
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CSTA is a conference primarily of teachers - our colleague.s Everyone
coming to your session is already interested in your opinion and going
in as a supportive audience. They &lt;strong&gt;want&lt;/strong&gt; to hear from you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll go back to the previous point - you&amp;#39;re basically talking shop
with friends. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
CSTA still feels intimate
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of its rapid growth, the CSTA conference still feels
intimate. It&amp;#39;s not a huge conference where you can attend a talk or
meet someone at breakfast and never find them again. It&amp;#39;s big enough
so that you &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; avoid anyone you want to dodge but you can pretty
much find time to spend with anyone you want to as well. This can turn
your talk more into a starting point for a longer convesation - how
cool is that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t forget to enjoy it
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I used  to get really nervous when giving LARGE talks - we&amp;#39;re talking
to an audience of one or two thousand. I&amp;#39;ve only done that a few
times. A couple of times at the New York Tech Meetup and once when I
was the faculty graduation speaker at Stuy when my best friend was the
guest speaker and my daughter was in the graduating class. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was pretty nervous before I hit the stage at Stuy when a colleague
gave me some great advice - &amp;#34;take the time to enjoy the moment.&amp;#34; I
remembered that just as I said above - I was about to talk to
friends. Two thousand of them, but friends nonetheless. I was reminded
to slow down and take it in. Enjoy the moment. I&amp;#39;ve tried to do that
with any presentation I&amp;#39;ve given since. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Final thoughts
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As  a final thought I&amp;#39;ll leave you by paraphrasing something that I
think was said by Pinchas Zuckerman - the world class violist and
violinist (who I think also used to wear a shirt proclaiming &amp;#34;I
vibrato when I play baroque - Deal with it!!!!!).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He said that you should always be smiling when you&amp;#39;re
performing. Either your performance is going well and you&amp;#39;re creating
beautiful music or it&amp;#39;s going horribly but it will be over soon. :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already looking forward to July.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating With Students - maybe GitHub to the rescue</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 10:17:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/communicating-with_students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Out of class student communication is always a challenge. There are
plenty of options:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Piazza
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Facebook group
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Slack, Discord, or other chat system
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Discourse, Vanilla or other discussion forum system
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mailing list
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but all have warts. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I shared my thoughts on a number of these options &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/class-communications/&#34;&gt;a while ago&lt;/a&gt; but
thought I&amp;#39;d update them now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of my opinions hold form my earlier post. I was using and
continue to use a mailing list as I can be pretty sure that students
will get the email and they don&amp;#39;t have to go to any outside site or
application. Now, getting them to respond or just use it for general
class communication is another story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also tried Slack again but it fared no better than my last attempt
with it. A couple of students used it but mostly, Slack was left to
die. I could have forced some engagement by posting assignments on
Slack but there wasn&amp;#39;t any real upside. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Earlier this semester some students said we should set up Discord -
&amp;#34;all the students use it!&amp;#34; was the line. Discord can be used as a chat
server similar to Slack but was created for gaming and also does voice
communication and other things. Personally, I prefer Slack. Funny
thing was that as I discussed this with my students I pointed out &amp;#34;you
know, we have a Slack channel set up and you all already have accounts
on it.&amp;#34; Most of them didn&amp;#39;t even remember. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, we tried Discord and there was the usual burst of activity when we
first set it up but now it&amp;#39;s again, mostly dormant. A few students who
use Discord for personal use are usually online but I&amp;#39;d chalk it up as
another failure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what am I going to try next? GitHub. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
GitHub doesn&amp;#39;t provide a general chat or email solution but it does
have what they call &amp;#34;issues.&amp;#34;  I got the idea from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ericdrosado&#34;&gt;Eric Rosado&lt;/a&gt; of
GitHub Education who clued me in on what issues can do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When you create a GitHub repository - something I do for class web
pages as well as assignments, you can also open issues. Issues are
associated with the project but also act as a lightweight forum. You
can go to a page and see all the issues (topics) and each one can have
a chain of messages (thread). You can tag them, filter them, and when
you&amp;#39;re done, close them (and reopen them later if needs be). The big
plusses are that:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People who are subscribed to the repo (assignment, web page, etc.)
automatically get email alerts on the issues.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can explicitly tag people to force them to get alerts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can directly reply via email so you don&amp;#39;t need to go to
GitHub.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everything related to a given project or repo is self contained.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re using GitHub / GitHub classroom you can use issues to
create a logged communication with your students on specific assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t used this class wide yet - just experimented a bit but I
plan to dive in much more deeply next semester.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t an overall communication solution. I&amp;#39;m sticking with a
mailing list for that until I can find a better solution but I think
using GitHub issues will be a win for project and assignment related
discussion.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Anniversaries</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alumni-anniversaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 07:32:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alumni-anniversaries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Two days ago, a teacher&amp;#39;s comment on a frustrating situation &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/outside-evaluators/&#34;&gt;made me
mad&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I got to be part of something that made me very happy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last night, Devorah and I ventured out to Coney Island to celebrate
the twentieth wedding anniversary of two former students. It&amp;#39;s such a
joy and an honor to be included in these types of life events and even
more so to count the couple and so many other former students and
friends. Devorah joked that she&amp;#39;d been to more weddings of my former
students than of her own friends. Truth be told, I can say the same. I
commented that nowadays I&amp;#39;m more in touch with friends that I&amp;#39;ve
taught than my own high school and college classmates. Our hosts joked that
it was the right call because my former students are younger and that
helps keep me young :-).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What was also exciting was seeing the couple&amp;#39;s oldest daughter for the
first time in a year or so. She&amp;#39;ll be starting at Stuy next year. The
grow so fast. Almost makes me sad I&amp;#39;m no longer there. Missed my
chance to teach the offspring of my former students. Still, she&amp;#39;s in
great hands with the crew that&amp;#39;s still there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also had a chance to catch up with some other friends and their
families. Loved seeing young Abe, another &amp;#34;grandstudent&amp;#34; who I haven&amp;#39;t
seen since his bris two year ago.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For anyone out there just starting their teaching career - this is the
payoff. The relationships. I know it&amp;#39;s hokie but I say that as
teachers in a general sense we should strive to be a force of good in
our student&amp;#39;s lives. If we&amp;#39;re lucky we see it&amp;#39;s appreciated and we get
to see the results. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB World 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 19:35:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
For those of you who don&amp;#39;t know, MongoDB is a very popular NoSQL
database. NoSQL  is an overarching term describing databases that
are not relational and don&amp;#39;t implement Structured Query Language
(SQL). In a relational database your data is stored in tables with
columns - think spreadsheet where each row of the table is a record in
the database. You link tables together via a common field or row
name. NoSQL databases work differently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
MongoDB is a document store. In MongoDB a document is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://json.org/&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;
object. Essentially a Javascript (or Python) dictionary. As a result
you do things differently. I plan to write up something more on the
differences between SQL and NoSQL in the near future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been using MongoDB on and off for a number of years. I use it for
personal projects and also in the software development course I taught
at Stuy. The community edition is free and easy to install and it&amp;#39;s
very easy for a beginner to get started.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s say you wanted to store information about a students. You might
create this dictionary:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  student &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; { &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Last&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Hugginkis&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;First&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Amanda&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;ID&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1245&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Homeroom&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;5A&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Schedule&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Eng&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Math&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Gym&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;CS&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Lunch&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Physcis&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Band&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;]}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You add this to your database like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;db&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;students&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;insert(students)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later, you can query for all the students in Homeroom 5A:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;db&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;students&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;find({&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Homeroom&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;5A&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Super quick and easy. It also comes with a nice REPL - essentially a
Javascript interpreter -  to play with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve spent the last two days at MongoDB World 2019. A great conference
if you want to get up to speed on MongoDB. I left reminded of a number
of great MongoDB products that I hadn&amp;#39;t really used and a few new ones
they&amp;#39;re just launching:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Atlas
This is their DB as service. Don&amp;#39;t want to administer your own
installation? Just spin up an Atlas cluster. The free tier is plenty
generous and you and your students can get up and running in under
10 minutes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Compass
Back in the day you either interacted with MongoDB pragmatically
using a language driver or used their REPL shell. Compass is a
complete fully functional GUI. It can connect to your database, a
remote one, or an Atlas cluster. A game changer for database
management
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Charts
This is really cool. You link MongoDB charts to an Atlas cluster and
then can interactively build dashboards and visualizations. You can
then embed the visualizations into your own web projects. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Field Level Encryption
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Encrypting passwords for storage and similar practices are important
but can be aslog. MongoDB now takes care of this for you. You can, for
instance, tell your database to encrypt the password fields and your
done. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Data Lake
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This blew me away. Basically, it can take your AWS storage and let you
query it as if it were a MongoDB database. It works with a variety of
file formst - JSON, XML, CSV and more. Basically it transparently
turns cloud storage into a database. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Stitch
This allows for the building of serverless apps. Similar to Firebase
but it looks to interact with all the other MongoDB goodness I&amp;#39;ve
mentioned. .
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were a few other neat things I learned about MongoDB and related
products but those were the highlights.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, I left the conference energized.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t use MongoDB check it out for yourself and your
students. In addition to being a great product, it&amp;#39;s also a great
company.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels in the Architecture - when they used to build schools like cathedrals.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 07:31:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the side benefits of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/&#34;&gt;visiting high schools&lt;/a&gt; is that I end up
going all over the city. This takes me to neighborhoods that I
normally wouldn&amp;#39;t have reason to visit. For a New York History wonk
that can be pretty cool even if you just limit yourself to looking at
the schools. A few of the schools I visited in the last couple of
weeks before the new year were self contained whole building schools:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
James Madison
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goddard High School
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
FDR HS
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Midwood HS
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goddard was interesting because it was founded in 2008 and grew out of
the middle school in the same building. FDR was also interesting. It
was founded in 1965 which makes the building fairly young or at least
early middle aged for a New York City school building. When you
approach it, you see this small short modern looking one story structure:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://proxy.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=http%3A%2F%2Fassets.nydailynews.com%2Fpolopoly_fs%2F1.1408243.1374717210!%2Fimg%2FhttpImage%2Fimage.jpg_gen%2Fderivatives%2Flandscape_635%2Fteacher25n-1-web.jpg&amp;amp;f=1&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hidden from view is the big rectangular tower that the entrance
connects to via a tunnel. I had an interesting conversation with the
school&amp;#39;s principal about how that came to be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
James Madison and Midwood also have their own buildings and they are
both partially screened - that is, they have selective admissions for
at least a portion of their student population. FDR is particularly
interesting becuase it is frankly an &amp;#34;old school&amp;#34; neighborhood
school that survived the destructive years of Bloomberg/Klein.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other schools I visited in that span were all housed in schools
that had been closed during the Bloomberg/Klein years and new small
schools created in their place. The original buildings were:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thomas Jefferson
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Franklin K Lane
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Christopher Columbus
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Andrew Jackson
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the coolest parts about visiting the older buildings is that
they were built in a different time. You have elaborate lobbies of
marble and polished granite. Beautiful murals and ornate
auditoriums. Unique architectural features like the ramps on the first
floor in Thomas Jefferson or the foyer in Brooklyn Tech (a school I
visited earlier in the year).  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also have school history. In many of the buildings the walls are
still adorned with names of notable alumni.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Christopher Columbus boasts Sal Mineo,  (Anne Bancroft), and, well,
David Berkowitz. Andrew Jackson does pretty well for basketball with
Bob Cousy, Lly Daniels, Boo Harvey, and recent Knick Kyle
O&amp;#39;Quinn. Woody Allen and Mimi Sheraton among others went to
Midwood. James Madison has a political bent with Bernie Sander, Ruth
Bader Ginsburg, and Chuck Schumer. Finally, Thomas Jefferson was home
to Sylvia Fine, David Daniel Kaminsky (that&amp;#39;s Danny Kaye to you), Paul
Mazrusky, Al Lewis, and others. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another tidbit I learned was about the history of Franklin K
Lane. Lane&amp;#39;s built in the Brooklyn Queens border. You can see the
hills of Forrest Park left from the last Ice Age rising up behind it
as you approach the building. Apparently there used to be a line of
paint denoting the border. Lane also saw a good deal of race related
turmoil throughout it&amp;#39;s history. I was talking to an alum during my
visit and he was telling me how that in his day, you either left the
building via the north entrance or the south one depending on your
crew and woe is he who got caught on the wrong side. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, many of the older buildings were part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_Progress_Administration&#34;&gt;WPA&lt;/a&gt; from the New
Deal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you do get a chance to go into an old school, take some time to
check out the architecture and the ghosts of the past.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll leave you with a couple of pictures from Brooklyn Tech - mostly
because they were easy to find.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.khomarch.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/kevin-hom-architect-university-college-architect-brooklyn-tech-1.jpg&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/59aec48e9f7456bae98b8609/5ad7b923575d1f7d69412830/5ad7b93d88251b1250984d58/1524087471280/mural-image-bths-2.JPG&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bthsalumni.org/view.image?Id=812&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;#ZgotmplZ&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions 2018</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:59:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reunions-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Thanksgiving weekend is also reunion weekend. I&amp;#39;ve been on and off
invited to Stuy reunions over the years. Not as often it seems as some
teachers but more often than others. I always do my best to attend. I
have very fond memories of many students and many classes over many
years and think a lot about them so feel very honored whenever I&amp;#39;m
invited to one of these.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the past each class due a reunion did its own thing - some club or
bar usually in Manhattan. This year, things were a little
different. Stuy held some &amp;#34;all class&amp;#34; reunion activities at the school
during the day and then multiple reunions were held at the school
during the evening. They hosted three classes - 2008, 2004, and 1998
in different parts of the school. The class of 2013 also had a reunion
off site - that&amp;#39;s my daughter Batya&amp;#39;s graduating class so she got to
catch up with her class wherever they held their shindig. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think the format worked well. Two classes were in the cafeteria
separated by a curtain and the third in one of the gyms. There was
self serve beer, wine, and water along with assorted snacks and finger
foods. Each area also had a DJ playing music though not too
loudly. Everyone knew the location, costs were kept low and for the
most part it wasn&amp;#39;t so loud that you couldn&amp;#39;t talk to each other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual it was great to see some former students that I hadn&amp;#39;t seen
in years and also chatting with non-cs students that I really didn&amp;#39;t
know but there were a few highlights.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spend a good amount of time with some of my 1998 crew. As I told
them, I really honestly missed them. We had some really good
times. Some of them had moved out of the city but talking to the NY
contingent we all left feeling that we should do a better job of
seeing each other in person.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also enjoyed my time with the other groups but I&amp;#39;ve manged to see
more of them more recently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a couple of weeks, I&amp;#39;m actually going to have a reunion of my own
alumni community. I&amp;#39;ve put together a loose association of my former
students and other Stuy students involved in tech. We&amp;#39;re having a
meetup in early December and right now it looks like around 100 people
are going to attend. I love those meetups because they bring together
people across the generations. The downside for me is that it&amp;#39;s
like a big family event. As the host I never get to really catch up
with anyone since I&amp;#39;m running from person to person.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One final nice takeaway from the evening. After I exited Stuy I
started to gear up in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cleverhood.com/&#34;&gt;Cleverhood&lt;/a&gt; for the rainy ride home and
started chatting with a group of &amp;#39;98 grads one of whom was my
student. He said to the group &amp;#34;you might not remember this guy and
probably have no idea what he did for all of you.&amp;#34; He went on to
explain how I got Stuy on the internet in 1994/1995 and set up email
accounts for everyone. I remembered that I ran the internet stuff at
Stuy for years but never really thought about the fact that we got
online and got those facilities to the kids that early. Working with
Bruce, a student at the time we &lt;del&gt;stole&lt;/del&gt; requisitioned one of the IBM
RS/6000 machines that were supposed to be used in the cad classes, got
it onto the net, and set up email accounts for everyone. It&amp;#39;s funny
that I just always thought of that as something we did but to some of
the students it was a pretty big deal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goes to show that you never know what makes a mark on your students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a
feeling of community. Students aren&amp;#39;t on campus every day and come
from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&amp;#39;t have
a CS &amp;#34;hang out&amp;#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&amp;#39;re
scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my
honors students. The first two cohorts were a single class in
size. Even though some dormed and some commuted, they were all
together in my class twice a week. This year, we&amp;#39;ve close to doubled
in size and about half of my students came in with a good deal of
prior CS knowledge. The result is that I have two different classes of
honors students and we are never all together unless it&amp;#39;s for a
special event.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, we&amp;#39;ve got one of my favorites coming up. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In two weeks, I&amp;#39;ll be taking about half my students up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;Catskills
Conf&lt;/a&gt;. An event that I describe as light tech conference with a focus
on creativity and diversity meets summer camp. I&amp;#39;ve written about the
event in in each of the past three years (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/%0A&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/%0A&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskills-2017/%0A&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;) and also
about the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/%0A&#34;&gt;knitting for charity&lt;/a&gt; event that Devorah runs during the
conference weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event and if you&amp;#39;re anywhere near the Hudson Valley
region you should &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, it&amp;#39;s a great first conference for the students. It only has
one track so no choices and the talks look really interesting this
year. Some of the ones I&amp;#39;m looking forward to are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Designing for Access first
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Behind the Tech: Emoji
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Leaning into uncertainty
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The full schedule is &lt;a href=&#34;https://catskillsconf.com/schedule/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But also mixed in are activities like blacksmithing
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/blacksmith.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and a live bird of prey show
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/BOP.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also hikes that show off the beauty of Fall in the Hudson
Valley
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature1.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature2.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature3.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rather than having the kids spread out in random hotel rooms we&amp;#39;re all
in a camp style bunkhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/bunkhouse.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The weekend is spent  living together along with technologists and
other creative types from NYC, the Hudson Valley and everywhere else. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my favorite parts is at the end of each evening when we all
hang out by the campfire. Hunter CS students, company founders,
software engineers, designers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/campfire.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event overall and a great event to build community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said before, if you&amp;#39;re in the area, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunion Season</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Thanksgiving is reunion season. Stuyvesant and I&amp;#39;m guessing other high
schools traditionally hold their reunions, at least the five and ten
year ones over the holiday weekend. It makes sense since grads who&amp;#39;ve
moved away might still be coming to town for family celebrations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year, I was invited to the Stuy07 ten year reunion. I considered
crashing the Stuy97 20 year but it was at the same time and too far
away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m always really flattered and honored when I get a reunion
invite. I&amp;#39;ve been to my share but I was never the hip popular teacher
that gets invited to these things. On the other hand, I&amp;#39;m sincere,
honest, and loyal so when I do connect with students it&amp;#39;s meaningful
and lasting. As one of my students remarked when I was nominated to be
graduation speaker a few years ago and I doubted I would be elected
&amp;#34;hey, you lead the most popular cult in the school&amp;#34; and I guess in
some way the community is a cult, or as I&amp;#39;d rather say, a family. In
any event, whenever I&amp;#39;m invited to a reunion I make my best effort to
attend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I find the role of faculty at reunions as somewhat amusing  we&amp;#39;re
something of a prop. The grads are there and should be there to
reconnect with each other. The teachers are and should be secondary.
From my point of view, there are three groups of students. The ones
that are now part of my alumni family - now friends who I&amp;#39;m in touch
with to varying degrees, the ones that never knew me and the ones that
knew me a bit. For the second and third groups, as a faculty member,
I&amp;#39;m there to remind them of the glory days as a representative of the
institution.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As with all reunions I had plenty of &amp;#34;I was never in your class
but &amp;#34; conversations. I also a number of &amp;#34;I majored in
fill-in-the-blank but just found my way back into tech
so.. thanks.&amp;#34; I love these conversations - it gets someone
new into &amp;#34;the family.&amp;#34; I also had one conversation that was really a
nice ego boost. One of my guys introduced me to his wife. She
immediately exclaimed &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s so great to finally meet you, he talks
about you all the time!&amp;#34; That was kind of weird until she went on
&amp;#34;every time he talks about Stuy.&amp;#34; That made more sense. It&amp;#39;s like
all those times when me and my buddy Ben would reminisce about our
Junior High school days and we&amp;#39;d always get back to talking about
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html&#34;&gt;Herb&lt;/a&gt;, one of our best and favorite teachers and a major influence on
me while Devorah looked on confused. Eventually she met and got to
know Herb and it all made sense. Another grad added &amp;#34;you think we all
forget about you but you come up more than you know&amp;#34; so I take that as
a shout out to all of the teachers out there who never get to hear
back about how much they are remembered and appreciated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With tools like email and Facebook it&amp;#39;s easier to remain connected to
former students but it&amp;#39;s always nice to connect in person. For the
StuyCS family, we have our periodic meetups but for the rest, I love
being included in class reunions and hope to be invited to more in
years to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - we need you to blog</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
At this past year&amp;#39;s CSTA conference, a few of us huddled in a corner
voiced a very common lament - &amp;#34;it would be great if more CS teachers
blogged.&amp;#34; It really would be. We&amp;#39;re still a relatively small
community and while there&amp;#39;s some good conversation going on on
mailing lists and on Facebook, those aren&amp;#39;t easily discoverable or
accessible and in the case of Facebook, there&amp;#39;s a question of
ownership and permanence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been blogging on and off since 2010. Around 300 posts. Not super prolific
but I&amp;#39;ve been doing it long enough to maybe be able to share a bit of
perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not sure exactly why I started. In part I was inspired by my wife
who at the time was blogging about her &lt;a href=&#34;http://squid-knits.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;knitting&lt;/a&gt;. I was also inspired
to share my thoughts after meeting some fellow CS teachers from across
the country at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-02-welcome.html&#34;&gt;CSTA event in Chicago&lt;/a&gt;. It was stop and go for a while
and then I took a break. I was re-inspired months later after meeting
a couple of CS teachers at another CSTA event - &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=ben%2520chun&amp;amp;src=typd&#34;&gt;Ben Chun&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/purplespatula&#34;&gt;Helene
Martin.&lt;/a&gt; Both terrific high school CS teachers at the time who are
unfortunately no longer in the classroom (unfortunate for the kids, I
wish Ben and Helene all happiness and success in all their
endeavors). We all agreed to try to write more and that got me started
again. I&amp;#39;ve been posting around 50 times a year since.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking back to when I used blogger, I had 30 - 50 hits on some early
posts and that was mostly just me hitting the site. It didn&amp;#39;t matter.
Writing has let me work through my thoughts. It also creates a record of
my thoughts and on how my thinking evolves over time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over time, people have told me that they&amp;#39;ve found some of the things
I&amp;#39;ve written useful or helpful and I&amp;#39;d argue that when people disagree
with something I write, even if they don&amp;#39;t comment and I&amp;#39;ve all I&amp;#39;ve
evoked is a reaction of &amp;#34;Z&amp;#39;s full of crap,&amp;#34; it&amp;#39;s gotten them to
re-evaluate their own thoughts on whatever the subject and if it&amp;#39;s
confirmation of their original beliefs, that&amp;#39;s OK.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The important thing is that by blogging I&amp;#39;m getting my thoughts down
&amp;#34;on paper&amp;#34; and sharing them for the world to take or leave as they
please and the more of us who do this, the more we expand the sum
knowledge of CS teaches.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a dispersed community of CS teachers across the country, we need
more people blogging on public platforms not in silos like Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve heard reasons why teachers don&amp;#39;t blog:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;#39;m new and have nothing to write about&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sure you do  write a paragraph about your plans for the days lesson
or how it went. Vent your frustrations (but be careful not to get
yourself in trouble). Rave about some students work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&amp;#39;t have time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yes, this is a tough one. If you have to do PD time, maybe your
supervisor will let you use it for blogging. To be honest, when I&amp;#39;m
writing regularly it doesn&amp;#39;t take that long. When I haven&amp;#39;t written in
a while it takes longer. In any event. It&amp;#39;s important and posts don&amp;#39;t
have to be long
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;#39;m not a great writer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This blog is proof that you don&amp;#39;t have to be. I&amp;#39;m stilted and ramble
and certainly no Shakespeare. I am the weakest writer in my household
and it&amp;#39;s not even close. Even so, we all have something to share.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know how&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was thinking about proposing a session at next years CSTA conference
where I&amp;#39;d work the group through creating a github pages based
blog. In the meantime, there are a lot of easy ways to start out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogger.com&#34;&gt;http://blogger.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wordpress.com&#34;&gt;http://wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and for those who want total control
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there&amp;#39;s my plea. If you&amp;#39;re a CS teacher and you&amp;#39;re reading this
please consider blogging. I assure you, we will all appreciate it and
benefit from it.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Educators StackExchange</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;CS Educators StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; is now in public beta. For those of you
who are not in tech, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stack_Exchange&#34;&gt;StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; is a network of question answering
sites. &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com&#34;&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; is probably the most famous - many peoples go to
site for computer science and programming questions and answers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During this period of public beta the site will be working on defining
itself and also on developing a critical mass of users. I hope the
site succeeds and I encourage everyone to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;, ask questions,
answer some and let&amp;#39;s all see where this goes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An interesting difference between StackExchanges and most other
communities is that it&amp;#39;s a question answering site not a discussion
board or shared resource collection. This works well for programming
questions where you can share a code snippet, algorithm, or derivation
which can be shown to be correct. We&amp;#39;ll see how it works for something
more nebulous like education. The voting system should help but the CS
education community is already awash with anointed thought leaders
with little or no teaching or CS experience. It will also be
interesting to see how things develop given that, by and large, K12
educators know a whole lot more about teaching than those in higher ed
while the on the flip side, the professors are generally much
more knowledgeable about the subject matter and then you have the
education researcher which is another beast altogether.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part of me thinks that discussion could be more valuable than answers
and in fact, I&amp;#39;m finding the comments which are more discussion like
to be more interesting, but that&amp;#39;s just me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A side thing I noticed was that the moderators have taken to asking
contributors not to link to other sites but to either write self
contained answers. I understand this desire to have everything under
your roof but it strikes me as wanting to use their silo instead of
someone else&amp;#39;s silo. This happened to me on an answer because I had
already written a series of blog posts on the subject. Admittedly, I
just put up four links and could have (and will) provide more context
but I also had no desire to rewrite my content just to share info that
was already out there. Likewise there was a question that was posed on
A* which led to &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/a-star-is-born/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to share my thoughts with &amp;#34;my&amp;#34;
community as well as on the stackexchange and didn&amp;#39;t want to have to
do the same thing twice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the moderators claims is that a link might not be
permanent. This is true. My blog might not be around in 5 years but
then the CS Educators StackExchange might not as well. I hope both are
around and thriving but time will tell.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also got me thinking about the  mish mash of
CS Educator communities floating around. I&amp;#39;m familiar with and a
member of:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few Facebook groups (CS Education, CS Education Discussion, AP
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Comp Sci, APCSP)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The CS Education subreddit
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple of mailing lists (the College Board AP Community, SIGCSE)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few blogs are kind of communities in that there&amp;#39;s a core group of
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
readers but discussion is pretty sparse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Are there others I&amp;#39;m not aware of?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This has led to a lot of duplication and some fragmentation and there
is a concern about silos. The Facebook groups are very much a silo and
to a certain extent so are the mailing lists. I guess the SIGCSE list
is more community run than the College Board one, but still. Blogs are
our own personal islands so while I wish more people would both blog
and comment about CS Ed they&amp;#39;re not necessarily open and permanent
either. At least with some blogs and with the subreddit and
stackexchange we can, if we want, download all of the data if we want
and preserve it for posterity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if there&amp;#39;s a solution - maybe we should set up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/discourse/discourse&#34;&gt;discourse&lt;/a&gt;
instance - something really open and accessible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, please do check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;CS Educators StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; and
let&amp;#39;s all help it become the best question answering resource it can
be for our community.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knitting at a Tech Conference</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/knitting-tech-conference/top.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/knitting-tech-conference/top.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/knitting-tech-conference/top.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past weekend was &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;Catskills Conf&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite events of the
year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last year, Devorah joined me and also enjoyed the show.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you know my wife, you know she&amp;#39;s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; knitting. Ok, not true,
she&amp;#39;s always knitting, spinning, weaving or performing some other form
of fiber craft.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#39;t complain. That&amp;#39;s how I ended up with my Kandinsky, Dust Puppy
and Yoda sweaters and my awesome Kang and Kodos socks. It also
keeps her an my entire family in warm amazingly beautiful knit wear.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While at the conference, Devorah was her usual self - knitting during
the talks. That doesn&amp;#39;t mean she wasn&amp;#39;t paying attention, it&amp;#39;s just
what she does. We also noted a few other attendees knitting throughout
the weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, this year, Devorah had an idea  let&amp;#39;s focus those idle hands to
do some good. She asked the conference organizers to send out an email
to attendees - knit squares during the conference and Devorah will put
them together at the end and we&amp;#39;ll donate the blanket we make to
children in need through &lt;a href=&#34;https://projectlinus.org/&#34;&gt;Project Linus&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The organizers were supportive, if not somewhat skeptical. That was
ok - we also had no idea if this would be a win or a flop.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Conference came and Devorah announced the project. She brought yarn,
needles, crochet hooks and instructions and also offered to teach
knitting during the breaks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It started slowly, but as the conference progressed, people started
knitting both during the talks and during the breaks.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DevorahZamansky&#34;&gt;@DevorahZamansky&lt;/a&gt; leading knitting for children in need at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/catskillsconf&#34;&gt;@catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hn0rx633e1&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/hn0rx633e1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/789839861813575680&#34;&gt;October 22, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Experienced knitters cranked out squares and newbies learned.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/knitting-tech-conference/learning.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/knitting-tech-conference/learning.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/knitting-tech-conference/learning.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jcn&#34;&gt;@jcn&lt;/a&gt; knitting for charity with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DevorahZamansky&#34;&gt;@DevorahZamansky&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/catskillsconf?src=hash&#34;&gt;#catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/rvkSnMYDCp&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/rvkSnMYDCp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/790164027494326272&#34;&gt;October 23, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the conference, we collected the partials. Devorah&amp;#39;s
going to finish the blanket up this week and then it gets donated.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;6 X 5 and growing! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/catskillsconf&#34;&gt;@catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/epC9b3ap0t&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/epC9b3ap0t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Devorah Zamansky (@DevorahZamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DevorahZamansky/status/790697247965151232&#34;&gt;October 24, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, how much of a win was this? We got a blanket to donate to charity
and a couple of new knitters. We also heard and overheard some
interesting comments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One speaker commented that it as much better to see members of the
audience knitting for good rather than checking their cell phones.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also overheard some attendees talking about how the knitting
project left them feeling more connected to the conference since they
were able to contribute something.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sounds like a pretty big win to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So much so that Devorah&amp;#39;s thinking about taking the show on the road -
maybe other conferences would like their idle hands doing some good
while listening to talks.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waking up in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/catskills-conf-2016/cc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/catskills-conf-2016/cc.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/catskills-conf-2016/cc.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Waking up to a beautiful brisk morning at the Ashokan Center in the Hudson Valley.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last year, Devorah and I attended the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;Catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt;, a tech
conference in Olivebridge, NY. It was an amazing and unique
experience. I can only describe it as Tech Conference meets Summer
camp. Where else can you hear talks by people like &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dens?ref_src=twsrc%255Egoogle%257Ctwcamp%255Eserp%257Ctwgr%255Eauthor&#34;&gt;Dennis Crowley&lt;/a&gt; and
an alos hear the music of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mikeandruthy.com/&#34;&gt;Mike and ruthy&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year, I gave another educaiton rant and to add to the fun,
Devorah&amp;#39;s been leading a knitting for Charity project and teaching
attendees to knit:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Progress on the charity knitting project led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DevorahZamansky&#34;&gt;@DevorahZamansky&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/catskillsconf&#34;&gt;@catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/catskillsconf?src=hash&#34;&gt;#catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/yoal7r48wO&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/yoal7r48wO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/790155915307737088&#34;&gt;October 23, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and we brought up my Hunter College students to join in the fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of the fact that we were out late at the bonfiere:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Ending a great day by relaxing next to the fire &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/catskillsconf&#34;&gt;@catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/LzKbftZamz&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/LzKbftZamz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christopher Short (@Shortoutloud) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Shortoutloud/status/790020785943539712&#34;&gt;October 23, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and then were kept up by the students bonding and chatting in the
bunkhouse, Devorah and I are first up, bright and early.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll write up more about this amazing event some time over the
week. Right now, I think I&amp;#39;ll just go out and enjoy a cup of coffee
and the clean brisk Hudson Valley air.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can NYCIST become in leader in CS Education?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nycist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nycist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I only learned about NYCIST last spring. They&amp;#39;re the &amp;#34;New York
Consortium for Independent School Technologists.&amp;#34; They had something
of an open house that I attended. I heard about them from friend
and fellow CS educator &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber&#34;&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday I spent an afternoon and evening with NYCIST members for
a discussion of the state of K12 Computer Science Education in the
City.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of my work has been with public schools and most of the teachers
I know, public school teachers so it was great to make new friends in
the Independent school community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing I realized during the evening was that NYCIST has a real
opportunity to do something special.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In some ways, the public schools are leading the way in computer
science education as a result of this administrations CS4All
initiative but at the same time, public schools face some real
challenges. While some &amp;#34;early adopters&amp;#34; have developed their own take
on computer science education, by and large, CS4All is being defined
and driven by few for all and, at least right now, the model seems to
be the &amp;#34;a little PD and you&amp;#39;re a CS teacher&amp;#34; model.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, standardized testing and teacher evaluations are
pressuring schools, particularly schools of our most vulnerable
students to push resources towards test prep in tested subjects rather
than real education, including CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this particular instance, NYCIST and independent schools can be
what charter schools were supposed to be before they were corrupted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Laboratories of innovation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NYCIST has already gathered together interested parties and the
independent schools aren&amp;#39;t burdened by the weight of politically
driven testing and teacher evaluation. At the same time, small class
sizes and flexible models allow for innovation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If they wanted to, they could probably create curricular and
instructional frameworks for CS education and. dare I say it, share it
back to the public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know I&amp;#39;m ignoring independent school politics and other issues that
would prevent this from happening, but I just feel that if there&amp;#39;s a
desire to do so from a group like NYCIST, it could happen.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m looking forward to continuing to work with my new friends and if
any of you are interested in finding out more about NYCIST, just tweet
to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber&#34;&gt;Saber&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if my idea here will take root but if it does, I&amp;#39;d love
to work with NYCIST to make something happen.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impostor Syndrome - I&#39;m not good enough</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been meaning to comment on these tweets for a while:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I went to high school with some scary smart people. Never made math team. Didn&amp;#39;t get into honors math. Thought I wasn&amp;#39;t good at it.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/snikolov/status/748660381392871424&#34;&gt;June 30, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt; :D&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;that&amp;#39;s the thing though you can get such an inferiority complex by always comparing yourself to others &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf&#34;&gt;https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/snikolov/status/748918417667727360&#34;&gt;July 1, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Stan, of course, is one of the most talented people I know.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It reminded me of a conversation I had with my colleague and friend
Jim last year. I had just recieved an email from a former student
turned friend. We were trying to find some time to catch up.  I told
Jim I had just heard from this young lady and Jim replied &amp;#34;I remember
her, she&amp;#39;s awesome. Really smart.&amp;#34; I mention this because the
individual we were talking about, while to us, extremely talented in
addition to being just a terrific person spent much of her career
living in self doubt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Meantime, I was having a conversation with another friend and the
topic turned to impostor syndrome and the desire to make it a thing of
the past.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Problem is, I don&amp;#39;t know if that will ever be the case. I&amp;#39;m
approaching 50 and have a career of good work behind me but I still
find myself questioning my credentials, work, and ability. Then I realized I wasn&amp;#39;t alone
when I read &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RobertTalbert&#34;&gt;Robert Talbert&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://rtalbert.org/blog/2016/tenure-second-time&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about his going through
the tenure process for a second time and &amp;#34;learning through this process
that I have not outrun impostor syndrome and probably never will.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Stan&amp;#39;s tweets tell part of the story. When we surround ourselves with
smart, accomplished people, we sometimes feel we don&amp;#39;t measure
up. I&amp;#39;ve found that for the most part, the extremely accomplished
people I&amp;#39;ve worked with are very unassuming and low key. They seem to
operate assuming that  everyone else is at least as capable and quick as
they. I recall &lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/articles.html&#34;&gt;Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt; talking about this in an essay but
I don&amp;#39;t remember which one. The problem is, if you don&amp;#39;t understand
their sincerity, you end up feeling even more inadequate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It gets worse when we start comparing ourselves to some unreal
composite. I remember feeling pretty stupid back when I was younger
comparing myself with others. The problem was that I clearly didn&amp;#39;t
measure up to the best math kid, or the best computer kid, the best
fencer, the best violinist, etc. Now, the best math kid might have
been a lousy athlete and the best fencer, a so so mathematician, but
to me, I was comparing myself with this composite super human. No
wonder I never measured up. Eventually, though, I realized three
things. First, there&amp;#39;s always someone better at something and always
someone worse. Second, that&amp;#39;s not the true value of ones worth as a
person, and three, I bring some good stuff to the table and I should
be (and am) content with that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I still struggle with impostor syndrome but at the end of the day,
it just serves as a reminder to look back on what I&amp;#39;ve done and what
I&amp;#39;ve learned in the process.  I start out in question but in the end,
leave confident. Maybe the trick isn&amp;#39;t to eliminate impostor syndrome
but rather to understand and contain it. We don&amp;#39;t want to live in fear
and anxiety but both are useful emotions when we control them and not
the reverse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s probably good when we question ourselves and re-evaluate our
positions - we just have to make sure as we&amp;#39;re bringing new people
into the tech fold that we foster acceptance and confidence  and when
impostor syndrome sets in that it can be channeled into a positive
and not scare people away.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of
Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching
career, then our family&amp;#39;s West Coast swing was a nice way to pull
down the curtain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she&amp;#39;s interning at
Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south
to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle
for a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, while out there, why not see if some of the StuyCS family
wanted to get together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I knew I had a lot of former students out on the West Coast but still, I was
overwhelmed and humbled by the number of people who wanted to spend
time and catch up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We kicked things off at Bloomberg Beta thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/roybahat&#34;&gt;Roy Bahat.&lt;/a&gt; Roy was
never actually my student but we&amp;#39;ve gotten to know each other over the
years and I value him as a friend and advisor. Roy provided the food
and the space and about 60 former students + a few old timers showed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple of days later, we had a lunch meetup for the Googlers:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/google.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/google.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/google.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and a happy hour at Facebook (sorry, no picture). Then in Seattle, a
nice dinner to close things out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Between these events there were some lunches, a barbecue at Batya&amp;#39;s
place  and even a drive by visit with a former student at
Microsoft. Overall, it was easily over 100 students over the course of
the week or so we were out there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve often said that one of the things I&amp;#39;m proudest of is helping to
build the StuyCS family. A community of people spanning decades. Over
the week, we had events mixing students from the mid 90&amp;#39;s to
youngsters currently in college and on their internships.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Seeing all these people meeting and supporting each other gave me a
&amp;#34;proud pappa&amp;#34; type feeling even though I didn&amp;#39;t do any more than set
the stage for them getting together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the week, the conversations were also great - not the straight
tech ones, but the ones that really made me proud of the crew. From
Seth talking about how to better get good CS Ed to more kids, to PJ
discussing why he feels it&amp;#39;s so important to be an active mentor to
his young programmers and how to get them to be real thinkers, to
Mike, Sam, Kathy, and Leo discussing the disconnect between
privileged families and those struggling to get by.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What more could a teacher want than their former students being both
happy in their lives and careers as well as good people seeking to
make the world better for everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The only thing that made me sad about the trip is that with all the
big events, I really didn&amp;#39;t get a chance to spend the time I wanted
with everyone. I hope to do better next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I&amp;#39;ve now been at Hunter for one semester and things will really
ramp up in the Fall. I&amp;#39;m still a proud part of our StuyCS family and if
being a part of pulling it together is the legacy I left, I can live
with that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The trip was a nice symbolic way to lower the curtain on act 1. I&amp;#39;m
counting on the StuyCS family and all the other players to help so
that we can make sure act 2 is a success and we can build something
similar for more young people throughout the city and perhaps the country.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discussion Silos</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-03-discussion-silos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-03-discussion-silos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In response to the past couple of days where my friends and fellow CS
Ed advocates Alfred Thompson, Rob Underwood, and I had a nice little
discussion via our blogs, Alfred wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2016/01/when-blogging-works-for-educators.html&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s great when a number of voices in the community have an open
discussion but one of the things I found myself lamenting was the fact
that a lot of the discussion isn&#39;t truly accessible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The silo known as Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have no problem with Facebook - I like it and use it daily - it&#39;s a great way to
keep in touch with former students turned friends. The problem is that
much like Las Vegas, discussions that happen on Facebook stay on
Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently I&#39;ve seen a number of blog posts, some mine, some Alfred&#39;s,
some others where the post garnered nary a comment. Head over to
Facebook  and if you&#39;re friends with the right people, you might find
a lively, informative discussion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In one case in particular, one post had independent, overlapping
discussions in at least three Facebook threads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How much richer would the discussion have been  in a public forum
plus it would be left open for people to discover in the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://disqus.com/&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;. I like it since I can also follow people on
it and I can just embed the code in any page but others like what
Wordpress or Blogger uses for comment threads. In any event, it keeps
the conversation open.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is this really a problem? Maybe not but I do wish people would look
beyond Facebook for discussions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s something I&#39;ve been trying to get my students to do for
years. I&#39;ve used a number of tools for class communication:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mail lists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piazza&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;custom forum software like vanilla&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and haven&#39;t found anything that really does the job quite right. I&#39;m
still looking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The kids use these but invariably end up also setting up a Facebook
group for my class and their other classes. I encourage this - they
certainly should have a forum that I can&#39;t see. How else can they plan
that surprise party for me :-). In all seriousness though, ideally
they should have a forum free of teachers but they should use the one
with the teacher as much as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The real problem with the kids setting up Facebook groups every year
is that there&#39;s no institutional memory. I see the kids, year after
year, have to clear the same hurdles. If they started thinking outside
of the silo of their Facebook communities and just had an ongoing
community for each class - one that passed on from year to year, it
would be of tremendous value for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I&#39;d like to encourage everyone out there to get our discussions
out into public forums. It would be terrific if more of us would blog
or blog more often and also to take the time to add to the dialog in a
public place.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halloween 2015 - the video</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-01-halloween-video-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-01-halloween-video-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a teacher, sometimes your gut tells you to do something and it
turns out to be a really good idea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&#39;s what happened in October, 1994. I decided to dress up as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groo_the_Wanderer&#34;&gt;Groo
the Wanderer&lt;/a&gt; for Halloween. I never dressed in costume for school
before and back then, no many did. A few students and very few
teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, I noticed that my younger students - the ones that didn&#39;t
know me that well yet, really loosened up and so a tradition was born.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over each of the next 20 Halloweens, I did something
different. Sometimes solo, sometimes as a pair and more recently as
part of a team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What started as a lark has now become something of an obligation but
it&#39;s still fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, with no further ado, let&#39;s go to the video tape:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/81qHI-iNkXg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And of course, the full playlist:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inner voices</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-30-halloween-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-30-halloween-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
div.half {width:50%;}
&lt;/style&gt;



&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/halloween-2015/inner-voices.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;inner-voices.jpg&#34; width=&#34;480px&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s Halloween again. This time, &#34;Inside Out.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No video yet, but stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the time being, enjoy some of our past madness:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Semi Formal</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-15-semi-formal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-15-semi-formal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today marked the last day of classes and time for the 8th annual Stuy
CS Semi Formal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&#39;s the Stuy CS Semi Formal? It&#39;s another bad idea that we refuse
to let die. Eight years ago JonAlf joked that someone in class joked
that they should have a party and they should all get dressed up. My
thought? &#34;YEAH!!! LET&#39;S DO IT!!!!!&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Eight years later, still going strong.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We cleaned out and decorated the room - classed things up by serving
cheese, dried fruits, nuts and the like. Drinks served in fake plastic
&#34;wine&#34; glasses and we encouraged the kids to dress up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-3&#34;&gt;Pictures from the first year -  2007&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;float:left&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure style=&#34;float:left;padding:20px&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;350px&#34; &#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-1.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style=&#34;padding:20px&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;350px&#34; &#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-2.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;clear:both&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-4&#34;&gt;And from 2011&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;float:left&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure style=&#34;float:left;padding:20px&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;350px&#34; &#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-3.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style=&#34;padding:20px&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;350px&#34; &#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-4.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;clear:both&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Kids can come and go any period they don&#39;t have any other class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s a signature event and a fun time. Whats more is that throughout
the day you&#39;ve got pockets of CS students all dressed to the nines in
all their other classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the first few years JonAlf and I did the heavy lifting but these
past two, it&#39;s all been the students - particularly Jenny, Miranda,
and Veronika (apologies if I&#39;m missing anyone).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s just another event that makes StuyCS unique.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just another day at StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.photo {width:60%;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;photo&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/just_another_day/pic.jpg&#34;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last post was a little heavy so just a short fun one for today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&#34;Just another day at StuyCS.&#34; That was the subject of the email Brian
sent with the photo above. What&#39;s going on?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;re working on advanced JavaScript while also looking at
&lt;i&gt;Backbone.js&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, as sometimes happens, Batya, while in her CS class up at college,
decided to open up a Google chat with me. This happens now and then. We try to
have some fun with it. We actually have a plan to mess with the kids
later this term, but I&#39;ll keep that to myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, Batya, of course, was sitting in her CS class in college. I told
her what we were doing and continued with the lesson.  She responded
that Zach, her boyfriend and my former student said not to forget to
emphasize certain things. I also asked Batya if her professor was
having a chat with his kid while he was teaching. Everyone was having a
laugh.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then things got sillier. Another chat popped up. It was Natan, my son,
who happens to be in that class. So, the insanity continued on when I
get a video call -  it was from Aida sitting in row 1 - that&#39;s what you
see on the screen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now it was getting a little ridiculous and it all started with Batya
and Natan. So, what&#39;s a a teacher to do? I had to contact their
parent, my wife, to tell her to discipline her children. That&#39;s the
third chat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, just another day at StuyCS.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions part 2 - My Stuy, Your Stuy</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-30-reunions-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-30-reunions-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
About a month ago, I was at my 30 year high school reunion. Yesterday
I was at the class of 2009&#39;s 5 year one. Stuy 2004 also had their 10
year reunion last night.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s always nice to be invited to reunions - I know it&#39;s largely
dependent on who&#39;s on the organizing committee but it&#39;s nice to be
remembered.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/10/25/reunions.html#.VHuvPJ-c30o&#34;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt; I wrote about Stuy reunions I noted how similar they all
are. It&#39;s something I&#39;ve noticed over the years. The kids are all
unique but the vibe is the same. I tell people that the biggest
difference between my class reunion and the ones I attend as a teacher
is that I know more people when I&#39;m there as a teacher. That&#39;s
probably more of a statement about me than the reunions or classes though.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Interesting to me was that I didn&#39;t really feel like I was at a Stuy
event. The people I chatted with were by and large part of our CS
family. We&#39;ve got our own mailing list, have our own meetups and are
already a community that spans the years. It was nice to actually see
people, particularly the out of towners in person and it was nice to
speak to some of the people who are more comfortable lurking on our
list but it&#39;s not like we&#39;ve been out of touch for the past five years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It really cemented my feelings that my Stuy really doesn&#39;t have much
to do with the actual school any more. It&#39;s the kids and teachers I
work with right now and the many graduates that I now consider
friends. It&#39;s also the CSTUY kids from the summer and the kids that I
hope to work with in the future. There are more than a few non-Stuy
people that are part of the community as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&#39;s my Stuy. On the one hand, it&#39;s pretty cool. We&#39;ve got a
community that&#39;s around 700 people and spans almost four decades and
StuyCS is a known quantity in the tech world.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand it&#39;s kind of sad that I no longer feel passionate
about the institution that I attended as a kid and have worked at for
over 20 years.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hi, I&#39;m Mike, I went to high school with....</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-16-weddings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-16-weddings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&#39;s how I introduce myself whenever I attend a former student&#39;s
wedding. It leads to all sorts of confusion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even better was the time I was at the wedding of two former
students. I had just dropped around 65 pounds and was wearing my hair
differently. I sat at a table filled with former students that didn&#39;t
recognize me &amp;#x2013; they had no reason to expect me, out of context and
all. I joined the conversation - able to go toe to toe on stories of
&#34;the old days at Stuy.&#34; It really confused them. We all had a good
laugh when I outed myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, a many of my graduates have moved from student to
friend and I&#39;ve shared life events with a number of them. Rule one is
that I don&#39;t reach out to them after graduation - that would just be
creepy. If, however, they reach out to me, then we stay in touch. As
an educator, even if it&#39;s a periodic note or update, it&#39;s something
that really touches me - it reminds me that even with all the teacher
bashing going on in this country, the kids, at least some of the time,
appreciate us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This weekend was particularly memorable for me. I was at JonAlf and Jamie&#39;s
wedding. JonAlf falls in a special category.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He was a former student and also on my fencing teams. I don&#39;t remember
how much we stayed in touch, but it must have been enough for me to
know that he minored in CS and was teaching high school at Brandeis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I heard Brandeis was being phased out and I saw we had a couple
of math openings, I tried to find him to bring him over to Stuy. You
try finding JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver in &#34;the system.&#34; Is it Jon Dyrland?
Alf Weaver?  JonAlf Dyrland? Nothing worked. In any event I did
eventually find him. Unfortunately, I wasn&#39;t allowed to bring him on
in spite of his being a Stuy graduate with a CS background and a
successful teaching record. Nonetheless I kept trying and a couple of
years later I got him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since then, JonAlf has been my partner in crime. A kindred spirit whom
I describe him as a younger hipper version of me although the hip bar
was set pretty low to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In addition to the lunacy - The Blues Brothers, Austin Powers and
Dr. Evil, Clyde &#34;Thluffy&#34; Sinclair, the CS Semi Formal and all, he&#39;s
one of the best teachers I know.  A former student that I&#39;m now proud
to call friend and colleague.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was touched to be included in the festivities this weekend. I&#39;m
incredibly proud of JonAlf as a teacher, a person, and a friend. He
and Jamie looked so happy together and I just know that their union
will be as amazing as Devorah and mine has been.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So this post is my way of raising a glass to JonAlf and Jamie.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rich and Rich - two legends on opposite sides of the hall</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
.leftborder {border-left:1px; border-style:solid;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ll get back to CS content soon, but for now:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last Tuesday was Election day - no students in the school - a day
devoted to professional development. Traditionally, math team coaches
from around the city descend on Stuy for a day full of lectures,
discussion, and general catching up. I&#39;ve never actually attended
these meetings. In the past, they were for math team coaches only and this
year, I was actually allowed to do something with the CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These meetings used to be organized by my late friend and colleague,
Rich Geller so it made sense that we took time at end of the day to
honor his memory and unveil a memorial dedicated to Rich and his
work. Rich was a legendary Stuy teacher, but more on that shortly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I looked at Rich&#39;s memorial, I couldn&#39;t help and turn my head
around to gaze at another memorial - &#34;Celebration&#34; - created to honor
the memory of another legendary teacher that died before his time -
Richard Rothenberg.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both of these men were friends and mentors. I thought I&#39;d dedicate
this post to some of the things I learned from both of them.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;c6&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rich (Doc)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img height=&#34;250px&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/rich-rich/doc.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Celebration - the Rothenberg Memorial&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Richard Rothenberg, known to me as Richie or Doc was the math chair
when I was a senior. He taught AP Computer Science that year and he
hired me back a few years later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He didn&#39;t give me my first teaching gig. He knew that I had to go
somewhere else to develop my chops. We did stay in touch, though, and
he hired me two and a half years later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Doc was an amazing teacher but he was also someone who worked
tirelessly behind the scenes for the good of his students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember one year he heard that one our recent graduates got into
some trouble at college. Doc got wind of this and went out of his way
to contact the college on the student&#39;s behalf. The student never
knew. That was Doc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He also understood the &#34;big picture.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was at a parents association meeting early in my Stuy career. All of
the assistant principals were taking turns talking to an audience of
Freshman parents.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each got up  and started to brag about their program:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;org-ul&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had n intel semi finalists last year
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our kids won whatever essay writing contest
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six kids won gold medals in&amp;#x2026;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each AP was bragging about how awesome their department was but in
truth they were talking about a handful of excellent kids who would
have excelled no matter where they went. I&#39;d guess Stuy or at least
Stuy&#39;s educational programs probably had very little to do with these
top kid&#39;s development and in any event, this wasn&#39;t really relevant to
parents of incoming students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then it was Richie&#39;s turn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Richie got up and said the following:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go home, hug your children, ask them how their days were.
Encourage them and support them.
Everything else will work itself out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That really stayed with me. So few teachers look beyond their field. I
remember talking to one of the best chemistry teachers I know - I
asked &#34;what do you do knowing that most of your kids won&#39;t be and in
fact shouldn&#39;t be chemists?&#34; The reply was that he looked at all his
students as though they all wanted to be and were going to be
chemists. Doc looked at his students as whole people first -
mathematicians second. That&#39;s one of the many lessons I learned from Doc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;c6 leftborder&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rich (Richard)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img height=&#34;250px&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/rich-rich/geller.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Rich Geller Memorial Display&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Richard Geller was never my teacher. He was my colleague and friend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He introduced me to fine dining and wine. We talked food, biking, and
teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rich had a reputation for being unyielding and strict. Many students
went into his class in fear but just as many came back after
graduating to thank him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember one of our mutual students saying:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I need to be in Mr. Geller&#39;s once every three terms to keep me in good
habits. Then I need a couple of pushover teachers in between to pump
up my GPA.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He was a top math teacher but his students learned much
more. Responsibility, respect, having care and pride in one&#39;s work,
and more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rich was a demanding teacher and one who really cared about his
students. When grads came back from college and Rich would great them
with a smile. The scary teacher was gone. He asked how and what the
graduates were doing and he honestly cared. Gone was the in class
persona. That was business.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In some ways Rich was much like an earlier Stuyvesant math
legend. Phil Fisher, who terrorized us poor calc students in the
&#39;80s. I got to know Phil when I came back as a teacher and once he
explained why he was so rigid and strict in class. Phil explained that
here he was, charged with teaching these amazing talented Stuy
students while at the same time, he felt he wasn&#39;t nearly as smart as
them. Phil needed 100% focus during every minute of every class to
give the kids what they deserved.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think Rich was something like that. Not exactly the same, he also
wanted the kids to learn to be responsible and respectful but I think
the core idea was the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a colleague and friend, Rich was the first guy to show appreciation
and the guy with enough character to tell you not what you wanted to
hear but what you needed to hear. I also learned to always be open and
honest with my team. Make sure everyone had all the information.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I learned a lot from both of these men. Stuyvesant misses them and I
miss them, but the there influence lives on through me, their
students, colleagues and friends.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evil</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-31-halloween/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-31-halloween/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
October 31, 2014. Twenty years after my first Stuy Halloween.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/groo.jpg&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;30%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/groo.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Little did I know that a goof of an idea would turn into a twenty year tradition.
This year, I had a chance to team up with Natan in his senior
year. Last time we had a Zamansky family duo for Halloween it was
Batya cameoing in our Austin Powers - Dr. Evil sketch. This time it
was me and Natan center stage. We&#39;ve been wanting to do &#34;The Pit of
Ultimate Darkness&#34; for some time now. We knew it wouldn&#39;t have the
room rolling on the floor with Laughter but we had a lot of fun and I think the classes enjoyed it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LjoUUvEUFbY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And in case anyone&#39;s looking for what we&#39;ve done during Halloweens at Stuy in past years, here&#39;s a Youtube playlist:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reunions, StuyCS and community</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-25-reunions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-10-25-reunions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-sec-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sec-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34; id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a few hours Devorah and I will be off to our thirty year high
school reunion. It&#39;s going to be a boat ride - reminiscent of those
excursion day trips to Bear Mountain that Stuy had back in the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having taught CS at Stuy for the last twenty plus years, I&#39;ve also
been invited to my share of reunions as a teacher. Sometimes the
current crop ask me about the reunions and how they compare to mine. I
usually say that the reunion that I just went to was pretty much the
same as my high school reunions just that I knew more people at the
reunion that wasn&#39;t my class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess that makes sense &amp;#x2013; as a teacher I work with and get to know a
large swath of students over their careers - when I was a student I
was pretty quiet and fairly asocial. I had friends, but not a huge
amount. Since 1984 I&#39;ve only kept in touch with a few. Ben, Bill,
John, more recently, Eliza and Steve. There are others would have like
to have stayed in touch with but life happens.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, while each year is different, all the reunions I&#39;ve
been to have had a similar vibe. Similar clicks, similar groups, and similar
conversations. I guess that&#39;s what happens when you put a bunch of
smart people interested in a range of things in a room together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Funny thing is, I don&#39;t think the Stuy Vibe is unique to Stuy. I&#39;d bet
that, if you permit me to posit, that Bronx Science reunions are
largely similar and if we put some Science alums in a Stuy reunion and
the conversation was not Stuy specific, we probably wouldn&#39;t spot the
interlopers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also had another reunion of sorts earlier in the week. As many of
you know, I maintain our StuyCS Alumni group or family, sometimes
called the StuyCS mafia. We had our latest meetup this past Wednesday
Around 60 Stuy alums, most of whom are my former students but some
from &#39;84 and even before gathering together sharing food, drink,
stories, and fun. At the end of the evening I was chatting with Peter
and Ilya. We spanned 25 years of Stuy but we&#39;re all part of the same
family. Incidentally, if anyone reading this is in Tech and a Stuy
grad, head over to &lt;a href=&#34;http://family.stuycs.org&#34;&gt;family.stuycs.org&lt;/a&gt; fill out the form and join
the family.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve been thinking about my Stuy class and the StuyCS family a lot
recently. Probably because I see that the end of the Stuy portion of my
career is close at hand. The thing I&#39;ve realized is that my Stuy isn&#39;t
the building on Chambers street nor is it the one on 15th. It&#39;s my
graduates, who have become my friends and my classmates that started
that way. It&#39;s like minded interesting people who do interesting
things and it&#39;s about the type of kid that grows into that type of
person.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to reconnecting with some of those people in a few
hours and meeting some that I never knew before.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An old tradition reborn</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-06-25-joesshanghai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-06-25-joesshanghai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, some of the seniors from the 301 crowd along with a few
teachers had an end of year dinner at Joe&#39;s Shanghai.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/joesshanghai/restaurant.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;restaurant.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it&#39;s Famous for its soup dumplings:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/joesshanghai/dumplings.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;dumplings.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m partial to the braised pork shoulder:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/joesshanghai/pork.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;pork.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We haven&#39;t had a 301 dinner in a long time, but I remember the crew,
first unnamed, then using the moniker &#34;the Z-team&#34; used to go their all
them time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was always Joe&#39;s Shanghai, followed by a trip to the Chinatown Ice
Cream Factory:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/joesshanghai/icecream.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;icecream.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and then the obligatory photo in front of the Mei Dick Barbershop at
37 Mott St (now gone):
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http:/img/joesshanghai/meidick.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;meidick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The 301 crew, or Z-team as it&#39;s some times been called are the
students that spend their time in the CS room at Stuy. It&#39;s one of the
few rooms where students and teachers co-exist in harmony. Some times
we have to kick the kids out when we&#39;re doing things like working on
exams, but basically, it&#39;s a shared space. They work with us on
projects and we help them with theirs. It&#39;s a unique community - at
least within Stuyvesant.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back in 1995 it was Yu Ping, Josh, Bruce, Winnie, Amit and others. Later it
was Paul, Emily, Orian, and Sam to name a few. Sam of course now, is
back teaching with us. We didn&#39;t go with the seniors for the last few
years. I&#39;m not sure why. It was a great way to end the school year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember one time getting an earful from a colleague the day after
such a dinner because I decided that I would rather spend the evening
with my students than take extra pay to grade regents. I didn&#39;t really care.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ve had a few reunion dinners there over the years as well, but
always pretty small scale.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Maybe we should try to get a whole bunch of alums together and take
over the whole place for an evening &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;fnr.1&#34; name=&#34;fnr.1&#34; class=&#34;footref&#34; href=&#34;#fn.1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;text-footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footdef&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;fn.1&#34; name=&#34;fn.1&#34; class=&#34;footnum&#34; href=&#34;#fnr.1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class=&#34;footpara&#34;&gt;
In case you&#39;re wondering why none of the pictures are of the
301 crew, it&#39;s because I never had this group sign photo releases.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I love about StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-20-wolfram/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-20-wolfram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
.pic {height:500px;width:500px;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I love about StuyCS is that we&#39;ve built a true Geek culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last week, we had a last minute visitor - &lt;a href=&#34;http://stephenwolfram.com&#34;&gt;Stephen Wolfram&lt;/a&gt;. Well known
for Mathematica and more importantly, Wolfram Alpha, without which
our students wouldn&#39;t be able to complete all their homework.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only problem was that we had about 24 hours from when the visit
was confirmed til the talk was to take place.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a little rough, but we pulled it together - convinced the the
administration to let us use the auditorium, sent a letter out to the
teachers and in general get things ready.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve heard our auditorium holds anywhere between 400 and 800 students &amp;#x2013; the kids filled the place!!!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;pic&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/wolfram/wolfram.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Image blurred intentionally&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Only at a place like Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The talk was great talk and the kids followed up with terrific
questions. Dr. Wolfram spoke for about 40 minutes and then stayed to
answer questions for another 40. Had the auditorium not been booked
after school, I think he would have gone on for another hour.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I loved is here we have a Math/Science/CS guy, but to the  StuyCS students, he&#39;s a rock star.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next day I got comments like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&#34;That was amazing,&#34; &#34;I&#39;ve heard talks by brilliant people before, but
never a visionary,&#34; &#34;He&#39;s actually building the future,&#34; and &#34;that was
the best hour of my four years at Stuyvesant.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All in all, it was well worth the craziness of putting it together at the last minute.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StuyCS  family from coast to coast</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-11-tapia-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-11-tapia-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think my one regret over the years is that I haven&amp;rsquo;t done much
travel. So, when I had the opportunity to go to the 2014 Tapia
conference, I jumped at the chance. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get to see too much of
Seattle, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. Now I&amp;rsquo;ve more incentive to go back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to seeing new sites, it also gave me an opportunity to see
friends that I don&amp;rsquo;t get to see too often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I frequently talk about the StuyCS family. That it&amp;rsquo;s all about people
and all about community. I&amp;rsquo;m proud that I started this family and I&amp;rsquo;m
always blown away by the guys. It&amp;rsquo;s one thing for alums to swing by
the school a couple of years after they graduate but it&amp;rsquo;s another when
they want to see me as much as I them even after ten or twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a little tricky to coordinate between conference commitments
and their schedules but we ended up having two dinners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I got together with Mike (StuyCS &amp;lsquo;97), his wife Linsday, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~ln/&#34;&gt;Helene&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll always remember
Mike for being the police officer when he, William, Emil (I think) and Paul
were the Village People for Halloween. It was amazing to see him, meet
his wife talk about old times and see what he&amp;rsquo;s doing today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helene isn&amp;rsquo;t StuyCS, but she is an educator of a kindred spirit, over
the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve met many CS educators. Some &amp;ldquo;get it&amp;rdquo; many
don&amp;rsquo;t. Helene clearly does. We clicked right off the bat. As with my
alums outside of the city, I regret that we only get to see each other
once every few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two nights later, I got together with Sam (StuyCS &amp;lsquo;96), Daemon (StuyCS
&amp;lsquo;06) and Matt (StuyCS &amp;lsquo;07) along with Boback, Alan, and Ephraim, three
other high school teachers who attended the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope we didn&amp;rsquo;t bore the teachers with our high school stories, but I
really had a blast. We talked about old times, we talked of current
issues, good food and good friends. We spanned 27 years of Stuy but
that didn&amp;rsquo;t matter. Get a bunch of bright interesting like minded
people together and good things happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel amazingly blessed that I can travel across the country and
students from 10 and 20 years ago want to get together to catch up. I
guess I should really say friends, not students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about my career as I close in on 25 years of
teaching. What impact I&amp;rsquo;ve had, what I could have done better, what I
did right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I can live with the StuyCS family as my legacy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four to beam up</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-31-halloween/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-31-halloween/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/crew.jpg&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/crew.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

Today was Halloween. This year we were the crew of the Enterprise. The original series, that is.

&lt;div align=&#34;Center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9SQwjfzlpso&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

Overall, the school had a much more subdued spirit than past years but
it was fun. Certainly more fun for me than the past couple of years.
&lt;p&gt;
For those of you that don&#39;t know - I have a long history of going all
out for Halloween. Starting in October 1994 as Groo the Wanderer:

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/groo.jpg&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;30%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/groo.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

To Bob Ross:

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/bob_ross.jpg&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;30%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/bob_ross.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/painting.jpg&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;30%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/painting.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

To many more. I&#39;ve been Little Ceaser, Hulk Hogan, Duffman, The Hulk,
Fred Flintstone, The Jolly Green Giant, Homer Simpson and more.

Some of my favorites were caught on video. Here&#39;s a playlist with a bunch of them:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really enjoy costumes like this one because it&#39;s all about schtick
-- interaction with others in the school.

When it first started, I wasn&#39;t sure how the whole costume thing would
go over. Now, 20 years later, it&#39;s expected. Every year I&#39;ve got to do
something good and something different. That&#39;s OK though, because it
has a great affect on the classes. True, most students know me before they enter my class due to reputation, good or bad, but after Halloween there&#39;s a noticable change in the class. All of a sudden I&#39;m just a little less scary.

Looking forward to next year.
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYTM &#43; StuyCS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-11-nytm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-11-nytm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For those of that don&amp;rsquo;t know, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nytm.org&#34;&gt;New York Tech Meetup&lt;/a&gt; it&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that
help make the New York Tech Scene so awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a group of some 30k+ members and once a month, at Skriball Center
at NYU they hold a meetup. It&amp;rsquo;s really quite an event. Members of the
tech community demo their projects, there&amp;rsquo;s question and answer time,
and afterwards theres a gathering for schmoozing amongst the crowd and
the presenters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the QA period, there&amp;rsquo;s one rule &amp;ndash; You can&amp;rsquo;t ask &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s your
business model.&amp;rdquo; I think we all love that it&amp;rsquo;s about the tech not
about the buck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuy CS family members such as
&lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tactonic.com&#34;&gt;Tactonic Technologies&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vantageousvideo.com/pages/about&#34;&gt;Vantageous&lt;/a&gt; have all
presented. I&amp;rsquo;m not able to go to the meetup regularly - It&amp;rsquo;s usually
on a school night and tickets are hard to come by, but I love the fact
that whenever I&amp;rsquo;m there, I reconnect with old Stuy CS family members
and meet new ones. Yesterday, at the meetup I met Ron Williams, of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://knod.es&#34;&gt;Knodes&lt;/a&gt;. He&amp;rsquo;s Stuy &amp;lsquo;94 - one year before my first CS
grads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why am I writing about NYTM? As a result of our
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/2013/06/27/Demo_Night.html#.Ud6jHKBtw7w&#34;&gt;Demo Night&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/brandondiamond&#34;&gt;Brandon Diamond&lt;/a&gt; invited a couple
of the groups to present as part of the &lt;strong&gt;Hack of the Month&lt;/strong&gt; segment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian, Eli, Jules, and Shan got up on stage and presented their work
to a live audience of about 1000 technologiest plus those viewing the
simulcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterwards the we mixed with the crowd. A great experience for the guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Brandon said afterwards - &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s another 1000 people that know what you guys are doing.&amp;rdquo; Given the difficulties in getting our program recognized and to more students, this exposure is so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, thanks Brandon, Jessica, and everone else involved in giving the kids this opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; If you want to actually see the kids, check out the vide here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://mlb.mlb.com/shared/flash/mediaplayer/v4.4/R7/MP4.jsp?calendar_event_id=14-376935-2013-07-10&amp;amp;source=NYTM&amp;amp;media_type=video&#34;&gt;NYTM Video&lt;/a&gt;. Just go to the 4th yellow dot (about 52 minutes in).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demo Night</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-06-27-demo_night/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-06-27-demo_night/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past year, I was able to convince my administration to allow me
to create a new course - Software Development. I really felt there was
something missing in our kids CS preparation - missing both from
Stuy&amp;rsquo;s program and from many youngsters college experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to do a few posts on the course, it&amp;rsquo;s design, implementation,
and lessons learned, but for today, let&amp;rsquo;s look at the years
culminating event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class had students working in teams taking projects from idea to
completion. Last week, we had a demo night, hosted by
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org&#34;&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt; and Google. Neal Zupancic, part of our Stuy
CS family attended the event and put together a wonderful write up on
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org/blog/stuy-cs-software-development-demo-night-neal-zupancic&#34;&gt;CSTUY
Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before getting into details, thanks goes out to Ben Fried, Mike Mu,
and the rest of the Stuy CS Googlers who helped out. Ben for securing
the space, Mike for coordinating everything, and the rest for manning
the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students, parents, friends, alums, and guests from the NY Tech scene gathered at Google at 6:00 last Thursday. Judging the event, we had
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/brandondiamond&#34;&gt;Brandon Diamond&lt;/a&gt; of HuffPost labs, founder of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hackerunion.org/&#34;&gt;Hacker Union&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://nytm.org&#34;&gt;NYTM&lt;/a&gt; board member, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/evankorth&#34;&gt;Evan Korth&lt;/a&gt;, founder of &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackny.org&#34;&gt;hackNY&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://nytm.org&#34;&gt;NYTM&lt;/a&gt; board member and NYU Professor and Lee Fischman, &lt;a href=&#34;http://family.stuycs.org&#34;&gt;StuyCS family&lt;/a&gt; member, currently at Galorath, and as dinosaurs like me remember, one of the creators of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Big_Electric_Cat&#34;&gt;The Big Electric Cat&lt;/a&gt;. Awesome folk all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students presented a set of amazing projects. They can all be
found on the class &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/stuycs-softdev&#34;&gt;github page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening was like a NYTM for a group of amazing high school youngsters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;scavenger-tours&#34;&gt;Scavenger Tours&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;tied-for-winning-project&#34;&gt;Tied for winning project&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team: Denis, Claire, Sofia, and Sarah&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/ScavengerTours&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/ScavengerTours&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ml7.stuycs.org:1995/&#34;&gt;http://ml7.stuycs.org:1995/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create tours that people can take using their mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;stuy-wiggles&#34;&gt;Stuy Wiggles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;winner---scratch-your-own-itch&#34;&gt;Winner - &amp;ldquo;Scratch your own itch&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team: Georgianna, Mengdi, Victoria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/StuyWiggles&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/StuyWiggles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ml7.stuycs.org:7007/about&#34;&gt;http://ml7.stuycs.org:7007/about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An attempt at fixing all the problems students have registering for classes at Stuyvesant. This is probably the most polished project of all the demos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;stall-wall&#34;&gt;Stall Wall&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;winner----most-amusing-project&#34;&gt;Winner &amp;ndash; most amusing project&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team: Ivan Smirnoff Jules Skrill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/StallWall&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/StallWall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ml7.stuycs.org:45454/&#34;&gt;http://ml7.stuycs.org:45454/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaborative network writing on the bathroom wall!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;web-explorer&#34;&gt;Web Explorer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;tied-for-winning-project-1&#34;&gt;Tied for winning project&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team: Eli Nass, Shan Shi, Brian Yan, Brain Zhang&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/NSYZ&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stuycs-softdev/NSYZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live &lt;a href=&#34;http://ml7.stuycs.org:1999/&#34;&gt;http://ml7.stuycs.org:1999/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn any web page into a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students had a great time and got lots of feedback from the
audience, particularly during pizza time after the demos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post more about the course in the coming weeks but demo night was
a terrific conclusion to a terrific first year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking it out of the school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-10-taking-it-out-of-the-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-10-taking-it-out-of-the-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


Inspired by the likes of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JonSimantov&#34;&gt;Jon
Simantov&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davidblerner&#34;&gt;David
Lerner&lt;/a&gt; as well as the greater Stuy CS family, a few of us have
been working on &lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org&#34;&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;, Computer Science
and Technology for Urban Youth. Yeah, we backed into the
acronym. Let&#39;s bring Stuy CS out of Stuy so we can work on inspiring
a wider range of students.
&lt;p&gt;
Well, last Wednesday we had our inaugural event. Hosted
by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.techstars.com/program/locations/nyc/&#34;&gt;NY
TechStars&lt;/a&gt; (thanks Moisey), we invited 75 youngsters to an evening
of talks. The idea was to have five different speakers each deliver
words of wisdom and inspiration on a different but related topic.
&lt;p&gt;

First up, John Lee of &lt;a href=&#34;http://schoolyourself.org/index.html&#34;&gt;School Yourself&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.com/img/techstars-2-6/johnlee.png&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/johnlee.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

John talked about big data. Starting with a question &#34;Who plays Chase
on House?&#34; John showed that by looking at huge data sets we can,
relatively easily, come up with the answer. John showed that problems
such as question answering are really accessible to youngsters. They
might just be beginning, but they&#39;re not far away from being able to
do some really cool things.
&lt;p&gt;

Next up &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/moiseyuretsky&#34;&gt;Moisey Uretsky&lt;/a&gt;. Moisey talked about his journey from
graduating high school through his college days, to starting
companies, successes, failures and the adventure along the way. Moisey was frank and engaging and really gave the kids a lot to think about.
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/spikegronim&#34;&gt;Spike Gronim&lt;/a&gt; was next.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike.png&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Also talking about big data but Spike talked more about the dangers of
misinterpreting data and how different representations can yield very
different results. Spike also spent time giving career advice.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike2.png&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike2.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TimNovikoff&#34;&gt;Tim Novikoff&lt;/a&gt; gave a different perspective. Tim spoke about how his explorations in IOS development lead in a roundabout way to his doctoral studies and very interesting research.

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Hitting cleanup was Gerry Seidman of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tactonic.com/company.html&#34;&gt;Tactonic Technologies&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Gerry gave a whirlwind talk about many of the things he&#39;s worked
on. As he said &#34;I don&#39;t have time to talk about anything, so I&#39;ll talk
about everything.&#34; Highlights included the latest touch technology he&#39;s
working on as well as vacation man++.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;f
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/vacationman.png&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/vacationman.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Gerry also dispensed words of wisdom to the audience.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/gerryadvice.png&#34; rel=&#34;lightbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;img width=&#34;50%&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/gerryadvice.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

While each talk was different, there were common themes:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do something you&#39;re passionate about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build stuff and do stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journey can begin in unexpected ways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

It was a great first event. We&#39;re very excited about &lt;a
href=&#34;http://cstuy.org&#34;&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt; and are looking to roll out more
programs including more talks, classes, mentoring, internships and
more. We&#39;re also planning professional development opportunities for
computer science teachers.

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

We&#39;ll be putting some of the attendees&#39; takes on the event up on the
CSTUY &lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org/blog&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; over the next few days.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

To hear about our latest, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cstuyrun&#34;
class=&#34;twitter-follow-button&#34; data-show-count=&#34;false&#34;
data-size=&#34;large&#34;&gt;Follow @cstuyrun&lt;/a&gt; &lt;script&gt;!function(d,s,id){var
js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;;fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,&#34;script&#34;,&#34;twitter-wjs&#34;);&lt;/script&gt;
on twitter, sign up for our &lt;a href=&#34;http://cstuy.org&#34;&gt;mail list&lt;/a&gt;
and keep an eye on the CSTUY &lt;a
href=&#34;https://cstuy.org/blog&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;.

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investing in People</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-20-investing-in-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-20-investing-in-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A little over a year ago, I decided it was time to reach out to my
alums, a group I refer to as the &amp;ldquo;Stuy CS family&amp;rdquo; and try to get us
together. The most rewarding part of my job involves the relationships
I&amp;rsquo;ve developed over the years but is was always between me and my
alums and them to their classmates. This was an attempt to start
building a network that spanned the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we had our fourth meetup. Somewhere between fifty and
seventy tech professionals getting together over pizza and drinks. Our
past meetups were always at bars - it was easy - send out an email
with an address, time., and date, and people show up. This time, we
really wanted to include the younger crowd, the 18-20 year olds so a
bar was out. I asked the family if anyone could host and Ethan came
through, volunteering &lt;a href=&#34;http://pave.com&#34;&gt;Pave&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pave.com&#34;&gt;Pave&lt;/a&gt; is a pretty neat company. The best way I can
describe them is that they invest in people. It&amp;rsquo;s a place where
backers invest in prospects, not only financially, but socially as
well. I really like the idea and you should all check them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pave folks were really awesome, offering space, helping to
oraganize and also taking part in the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was great and having it at a company rather than a bar or
restaurant had some unexpected side effects. Since there weren&amp;rsquo;t
nearly as many chairs, people mixed more and as I said, this allowed
the younger set to meet the older alums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being at Pave made me think that as a teacher, my entire career is
about investing in people. Not in the same way as Pave, but still. My
results aren&amp;rsquo;t financial but in community. Although Pave does have a
financial component to it, I really think they &amp;ldquo;get it&amp;rdquo; and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t
be surprised if they end up getting the community rewards as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Day(s)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-25-alum-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-25-alum-days/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The day before Thanksgiving is always fun. For as long as I can
remember, recent graduates descend upon Stuy. For the most part, they
mull around the senior bar but we get our share up in 301.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year was a little quiet but I got to see more than my share of
graduates over the weekend as I attended the 2002 and 2007 class
reunions. I&amp;rsquo;ve only been invited to a handful of reunions and really
consider it an honor when I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at both events but here are some notes for those of
you organizing reunions in the future:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got to also give particular props to Gary He for keeping the class of 2002 crush lists for the past 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the two reunions and the alumni visits prior, I noticed a few
things. First. I was reminded that each years is like a separate
stratified layer. You might know a couple of students from the year
before or after, but that&amp;rsquo;s about it. It&amp;rsquo;s like groundhog day. Each
year has a similar assortment of personalities and archetypes and
exists in semi-isolation. I also noticed that while the graduates were
strongly connected to each other, not so much to the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are two of the things that I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to address by creating &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;family.stuycs.org&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping this
group can bring Stuy grads together across the years. The feedback I
got from people at both reunions was very positive. I&amp;rsquo;m also counting
on this community to give back to help us in our efforts to enhance
computer science education at Stuy and in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the lack of connection to the school, I do think things will get
better. Stuyvesant&amp;rsquo;s new principal, Jie Zhang was at the 2002
reunion. The fact that she was there was huge. I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine the
previous principal coming in to attend a class reunion. After all,
he&amp;rsquo;s the principal that tried to keep the alums out of Stuyvesant on
multiple occasions. There was also a point in the evening when one of
our alums was telling Principal Zhang that many graduates wanted to be
more connected to Stuy but felt alienated. She seemed shocked and
emphasized that graduates should be welcome at and feel part of the
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a tiring weekend &amp;ndash; too many late nights, but a good one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sense good things to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Work</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-going-back-to-work-today&#34;&gt;On going back to work today&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since school was still out due to Sandy, we ran a second online class
yesterday. At the end of the session, which I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize below, I
told the class what I wanted them to accomplish today and over the
weekend. One student queried &amp;ldquo;you mean no class on Friday :-(?&amp;rdquo; Alas
no &amp;ndash; while students aren&amp;rsquo;t reporting to school this morning, teachers
are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the logic as to why is far from sound. Some schools are
fine, some not, in our case, there&amp;rsquo;s no subway service south of 34th
street or coming in from Brooklyn and we&amp;rsquo;re located near the tip of
Manhattan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are we going to do? Who knows. We don&amp;rsquo;t have lessons to plan and
while Stuy has power, phones and internet are out. Professional
development? Even when planned extensively, I&amp;rsquo;ve found it to be mostly
useless (I always have to sit through math PD, for example, learning
how to use a graphing calculator).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we&amp;rsquo;re going to report in for no real purpose. Best I can figure,
the city wants teachers in so they can call it a professional
development day then they can try to change things so that students
will report during Brooklyn Queens day next semester thus restoring
one instructional day lost this week. Not a bad idea to recapture the
day but to make teachers - coming from all over the area - trudge in
for no purpose just to play politics is distasteful but unfortunately typical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add to the insult, not only are us teachers still in the dark as to
what&amp;rsquo;s going on, we weren&amp;rsquo;t even told when to report until after
midnight yesterday. I woke up at my usual 5:00am to exercise but first
checked my email &amp;ndash; waiting was an email from Chancellor Dennis
Walcot. I recieved it at 12:52 this morning. This was when I was first
told that I was to report to school at 10:00am. I can&amp;rsquo;t believe this
decision couldn&amp;rsquo;t have been made and emailed out a few hours
earlier. In any event, I&amp;rsquo;m waiting until 10:00 to get in - I&amp;rsquo;ve often
found the building locked when I&amp;rsquo;ve shown up before official opening hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now for the part of my job that I actually enjoy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-did-yesterdays-online-class-go&#34;&gt;How did yesterday&amp;rsquo;s online class go?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s class was a wrapup of a mini project &amp;ndash; basically an
add-a-line story site. You can see an unfinished version that two of
the students put together &lt;a href=&#34;http://ml7.stuycs.org:5200&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You can
see more of the stuff we are using on our &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/organizations/stuycs-ml7&#34;&gt;class github
page&lt;/a&gt;. The students are
using &lt;a href=&#34;http://flask.pocoo.org&#34;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; which is a python website
generator along with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mongodb.org&#34;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;. We had to tie
up some loose ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We again broadcast a Google+ hangout live through YouTube and we again
used a google doc as a chat space. This time we used the right hand
side bar for comments and only used the document for more permanent
material (a web refernce for example). It worked much better.  The
vertical flow of comments on the sidebar were much easier to track and
work with than a freeform document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session still had the time delay problem and the feedback loop is
still a killer but the students again seemed to enjoy the
experience. This is clearly not a replacement for in person teaching,
but again, better than nothing on a day off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-a-note-on-the-stuy-cs-culture&#34;&gt;And a note on the Stuy CS Culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seniors were game for this experiment and would be happy to go
again today if we were able to.  They also continually surprise me in
little ways. When we started this mini project, we all had to learn
how to use MongoDB (myself included). At first I had a hard time
confirming that they had done the outside work to learn the MongoDB
specifics. Only as they continually gave me better alternatives to my
approaches did I know that they were on top of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, my sophomores were much less receptive to an online
class during the hurricane days. A handful wanted to give it a go, but
the majority never responded to my email. Why was that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A big reason is that I&amp;rsquo;ve only been with my sophomores for a short
time. We haven&amp;rsquo;t yet built the rapport and culture that exists in my
senior classes. I always notice a difference in class attitude around
Halloween but we really don&amp;rsquo;t have the feeling of family until late
November or some time in December.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sophomores are in a required course, the seniors an elective. I
think this is secondary to the culture / rapport but I&amp;rsquo;m sure it has
an effect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe the seniors have a better understanding that what we&amp;rsquo;re doing in class is to their benefit and the sophomores are still&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to pay more attention to the time line from when
students come into my class and when they become part of &amp;ldquo;the family.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandy Bridge and Screen Casting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-10-31-sandy-bridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-10-31-sandy-bridge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


Here&#39;s what the bridge leading across the West Side Highway over to
Stuy during the storm. Hence the title with the weak tech reference.

&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img  width=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hurricane-bridge.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

The storm has kept the schools closed all week so it&#39;s as good a
time as any to try to resurrect this blog.
&lt;p&gt;
As you can see, I&#39;ve moved from blogger to a Jekyll based blog hosted
on Github. I&#39;m really liking the way it works but more on that at a
later date.
&lt;p&gt;
Some time Monday evening or Tuesday morning, I asked Batya if she
thought my seniors would be up for a livestreamed class (Batya, my
daughter, for anyone who doesn&#39;t know, is in one of the sections of
the class). It turned out they were all in.
&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve got to say that I&#39;ve got amazing classes -- the fact that they&#39;re
into the same brand of insanity as I am and even willing to go again tomorrow isawesome.
&lt;p&gt;
So, here was today&#39;s experiment:
&lt;p&gt;
A Google+ hangout based live stream of Stuyvesant&#39;s
Software Development class. In my favor was the fact that I was just
going to introduce CSS - not a subject that lends itself to deep
classroom discussion. Against me was the use of technologies I haven&#39;t
used before and the fact that we have about 64 students that I was
hoping to reach.
&lt;p&gt;
So, how did it go?
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;First, let&#39;s talk about the technical side.&lt;/h3&gt;

Here&#39;s the basic setup:

&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/screenshot.png&#34;&gt;

I&#39;ve got two monitors and Google would only broadcast the screenshot
from the smaller one on the right. It had Emacs and a chrome going
most of the time with an occasional shell. While teaching about CSS, I
also introduced the students
to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/magit/magit/downloads&#34;&gt;Magit&lt;/a&gt; as
well as
Emacs &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/skeeto/impatient-mode&#34;&gt;impatient&lt;/a&gt;
mode both of which are awesome. On the left hand screen I had the
actual Hangout as well as the Google shared doc.
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that you can&#39;t make a public Hangout and also stream it
live on YouTube, you can only invite people in your circles. Since
most of my students aren&#39;t in my circles, only a few could &#34;join&#34; the
Hangout. Most watched the YouTube stream and we all connected to a
shared Google Doc for notes and questions.
&lt;p&gt;
The Google Doc turned out not to be the best idea. It got everyone
writing in the same document but people ended up writing all over the
document. If something wasn&#39;t on the screen I wouldn&#39;t see it. We&#39;re
going to try something more sequential tomorrow -- maybe disqus
comments.
&lt;p&gt;
The other two problems were the low resolution of the screenshot
broadcast and the lag. I really had to blow up the font size. If
anyone has any ideas how to do this well, please share. The lag was
also a problem since it kept me from having anything resembling a reasonable feedback loop.
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, my students were left with this enduring image of me:


&lt;div align=center&gt;&lt;img width=50% src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/monocle.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;And the view from a teacher&lt;/h3&gt;

On the one hand, it was pretty cool to be at home and able to work
with my students but there were some major deficiencies:

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Can&#39;t see the audience&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Even at best, with the Hangout you can only see 10 people. I&#39;m guessing it feels like a stage actor doing a movie. I was talking but couldn&#39;t see my audience. No nodding heads, no nodding off heads, just talking to a screen. It was a little disconcerting. Teachers adjust to their class all the time both consciously and subconsciously. You might do something overt like call on a particular student or maybe sense it&#39;s time for a joke or even little things like how or where you stand. All of this was lost.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Need a better chatroom&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I mentioned that the Google Doc wasn&#39;t a great idea. I think
something that&#39;s more vertical like a chatroom will work better. I&#39;ll
know tomorrow.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;An shared board space would be very cool&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The other missing piece is a way for the students to directly interact with what I&#39;m presenting. A shared Emacs would be amazing.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;The delay is a killer&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This was also a problem. I found myself saying or doing something then waiting until something came through the document. This hurt the flow considerably&lt;/dd&gt;

I really found the experience enlightening. People keep talking about
recorded lectures and MOOCS and all that but if anything, today&#39;s
experience just confirms to me that there&#39;s nothing like an in class
teacher, particularly with a small group of students.

That said, I think this was a good experience and my students seem to
agree. We spent part of an otherwise unproductive day in a productive
manner and we&#39;re planning on doing it again tomorrow.

&lt;p&gt;
Since Students will be home until Monday, I&#39;d like to go for a third
class on Friday but I&#39;ll be back at work so it looks like no class
after tomorrow until Monday.

&lt;p&gt;
Comments?


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Year Teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;

Sorry for the weak title and movie reference.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&#39;s teacher appreciation week -- one of our lesser celebrated weeks. I&#39;m waiting for the annual letter we get from the chancellor. Given the level of teacher bashing over the last few years, I&#39;ve recently found their emails amusing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I though I&#39;d take the time to thank a few of my most influential teachers. To paraphrase: whatever good I&#39;ve been able to do, it has been because I have stood on the shoulders of giants.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: large;&#34;&gt;Alan Goff - 7th grade English - Wagner JHS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Great teacher, great storyteller. &amp;nbsp;Every now and then class would be spent with Mr. Goff &amp;nbsp;telling us a story of his childhood. From his school days when he discovered how to make explosive &#34;goffolini&#34; bombs and had to deal with &amp;nbsp;the bully &#34;GodDilla&#34; to when he blew his hand off with said bombs to his time in the merchant marines. I think I learned more about bringing characters to life from listening to Mr. Goff than anywhere else. I&#39;d like to think I&#39;m somewhat entertaining in class and it started with Mr. Goff. Mr. Goff also shared with us the range of his interests. For me this led to a life of trying to learn something about everything. Thanks.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mr. Goff passed away a number of years ago and I never had a chance to thank him. I still regret that. A few years ago, when Batya was graduating from Wagner. I drew the short straw and had to go to the awards ceremony. I love going to Batya and Natan&#39;s concerts and other things they do, but I hate these award ceremonies. When the vast majority of the students get awards, there really isn&#39;t anything special about them - I wasn&#39;t thrilled to go. It turned out that Batya won the Alan Goff Memorial Medal for writing. I didn&#39;t even know there was one. Brought a tear to my eye.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: large;&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Herb Greenhut - 7th grade History - Wagner JHS&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wow, what can I say about Herb. He was the first teacher to challenge me to really think. Every year he would start the semester by impersonating a famous figure. Someone his students would never have heard of but their parents would have. For us I think it was William Jennings Bryan. Another year it was Thoreau. All his paperwork was under the pseudonym and he&#39;d play us on for days. He&#39;d engage us in debates as if we were adults.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Herb was a straight shooter. We were young but he never sugar coated things. Herb got us to question things like no teacher had before.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I could go on and on about Herb. He influenced generations. By the time I was in his class in the seventies, he was a veteran and he continued on until right before his death a couple of years ago.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Both my son and daughter had the&amp;nbsp;privilege&amp;nbsp;of being in Herb&#39;s class during his final years. He had retired from the school system but still taught at our synagogue. I asked them both about Herb. Their response &#34;he makes us think.&#34; Thanks&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As I said, I could go on and on about Herb but I found this piece&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://newworld1.blogspot.com/2010/12/herbert-greenhut-rip.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;that does a better job than I&#39;d be able to.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: large;&#34;&gt;Richie Rothenberg - 12th grade AP CS - Stuy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The only way you could describe Richie would be a mensch in the truest sense of the word.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Richie was my teacher at Stuyvesant. He was a great teacher, but I got more from him as a colleague years later. Richie was always on the side of right and always did the right thing. Never a self promoter and never the &#34;hip&#34; teacher, &amp;nbsp;he just went about his business of being a great teacher. If there was something he could do to help a student, he did it. Many times, the student never knew.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Richie passed away at 50 in 1997. &amp;nbsp;The day it happened, school basically shut down. Normally a small memorial plaque is placed up near a room in memory of a teacher. This wouldn&#39;t do for Richie. Students, teachers, and alums contributed money and Madeleine Segall-Marx, artist and Stuy parent, contributed a year of her life creating &lt;u&gt;Celebration&lt;/u&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;File:Danny-Jaye
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuing the Journey</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-04-24-continuing-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-04-24-continuing-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Shortly after our event at Foursquare, I was chatting with Kevin Friedman (Stuy &#39;96). Kevin&#39;s startup is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cojourneo.com/&#34;&gt;Cojourneo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and since it has an educational bent, he thought I might be interested in hearing about it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I certainly was.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rather than visiting Kevin, I thought it would be fun to have him come down after school, present Cojourneo to any students that wanted to stay late and then field questions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L7-QKnsProM/T5dO_0YvmRI/AAAAAAAAG_A/YsV-hRI3-ws/s1600/IMG_20120424_154655.jpg&#34; imageanchor=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;320&#34; src=&#34;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L7-QKnsProM/T5dO_0YvmRI/AAAAAAAAG_A/YsV-hRI3-ws/s320/IMG_20120424_154655.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Cojourneo is an interesting product. There&#39;s been a lot of hype around on line education in the past year, but it seems to me that Cojourneo&#39;s a little different. We&#39;ve got efforts like Coursera and Udacity that are trying to bring university style offerings to the masses while places like Codecademy seem to be more vocational in nature. All three efforts are &#34;class&#34; based. That is, you are taking a class over a period of time. Despite some resources to make these classes shared experiences -- specifically things like discussion groups, they mostly seem to have students watching videos or working through on line material on their own.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Cojourneo&#39;s approach is to organize around &#34;journeys&#34; which aren&#39;t necessarily academic in nature, one of the journeys they have going now is&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://u125899.sendgrid.org/wf/click?upn=RFLYp28x4tn3zctFtSv9u26CpQORa-2F0ctjP5N2rt-2BPjEwScoB8-2FDiOTIH3A2decWJOBzbvP-2BL04E-2BTSUUzAnnrfeBTKDP98OMWzCupR8df4-3D_0yQd2FpqhdDJMpTKTRf0-2Bgkt9TsX0gLH-2FMd1xsBq45m-2BDWXDwm9y5rOApSyT2yeJcwKLUGkENJdoY9rRSsOVmrBLVPyJXYbty3GU3x6bt2xa-2Bn7F4b-2Brh2n-2Flt7pIOH-2Bzk3N2i42qHszSVEJ5ojVeg-3D-3D&#34;&gt;Surviving the Startup Journey&lt;/a&gt;, but Kevin mentioned that they could have things like book clubs, travel journeys or any number of other types of journeys. They&#39;re also different in that they&#39;re really trying to create a shared experience -- you take the journey with a small circle of people, not solo - I love this aspect.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;By no means am I an expert, but I like a lot of their ideas.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;A bunch of students gathered and we were off. I had no idea how the talk would go but I figured that the kids hadn&#39;t had an opportunity to speak one on one with someone in the early stages of a startup so it would probably be valuable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Kevin presented the product, talked about some difficulties and decisions along the way and generally tried to give the kids the flavor of what it was like to start a product and a company. The kids tried to reciprocate by providing feedback on the product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Most of the questions focused on the business side rather than the technical. Kevin was asked about funding, monetization, building a user base, scaling, and any number of other ideas.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;All in all, I think it was a valuable experience and look forward to bringing more alums down to talk to the current crop.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#39;1&#39; height=&#39;1&#39; src=&#39;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/468689896075458340-3559652079994112054?l=cestlaz.blogspot.com&#39; alt=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checking in with the family</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-03-31-checking-in-with-family/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-03-31-checking-in-with-family/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;&#34;...&amp;nbsp;the standardized courses don&#39;t shed much light on future opportunities and they make it hard for students to identify what they&#39;re most interested in. The CS department, on the other hand, is great at demonstrating all the things that are going on in the modern comp sci world.&#34;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;-- Asa, one of our current CS students.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: x-small;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222; font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;Asa&#39;s comment was in response to an event we held last Tuesday. We brought 100 current students up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://foursquare.com/&#34;&gt;FourSquare&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;along with 100 of our CS alums for a mixer. Other than the fact that we aren&#39;t a department, I&#39;m hoping he was spot on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: x-small;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: x-small;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;tr-caption-container&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8sE0kCWEeMU/T3cKj8o5GrI/AAAAAAAAG2A/4Ygwoo9qnfI/s1600/P1010793.JPG&#34; imageanchor=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; src=&#34;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8sE0kCWEeMU/T3cKj8o5GrI/AAAAAAAAG2A/4Ygwoo9qnfI/s320/P1010793.JPG&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;tr-caption&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Stuy CS from 1976 to the present&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A couple of months ago, I started to try to organize the graduates I&#39;ve had the&amp;nbsp;privilege of teaching over the years. I put out some feelers and the response has been great. So far we have about 400 members. I like to refer to us as the Stuy CS family since I&#39;d like to think there&#39;s a stronger bond than that typical between a teacher and his students.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;I&#39;d also like to think there&#39;s a common thread across the years that ties the older and younger graduates together.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To kick things off, I thought it would be a great idea to get the alums together with the current students. We&#39;ve got people all over the tech map, from giant companies to startups. I started putting a list together&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://family.stuycs.org/pbs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it would be great to expose our current students to the range of possibilities that await them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Immediately, the family came through.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/noah_weiss&#34;&gt;Noah&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/whizziwig&#34;&gt;Dave&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;volunteered FourSquare as host for the event. They provided the food and the site. The alternative would have been to have the event at Stuy. This would have cost us and would have been somewhat mundane. Just being at a place like FourSquare seemed to really excite the current crop of Stuy students.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The evening of the event, I was a little nervous -- about 100 alums signed up, but would they show. I&#39;ve been told that general alumni events can typically have a very high no-show rate, particularly when the event has no cost and registering is as easy as an email.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The kids and I arrived early -- school lets out at 3:30 and the event didn&#39;t start until 6:00. As 6:00 approached, the alums started to dribble in. By the time we started, we had a packed house!!! It was great seeing everybody again.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We had alums from every year. From 1995, my first set of&amp;nbsp;graduates, to last years senior class. We also had a few older alums, including me and &amp;nbsp;my classmate and friend Steve from &#39;84 and Gerry (&#39;76) , who I met when he volunteered to help Stuy CS back in the 90&#39;s. He&#39;s become a good friend to both me and the program in the years since.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For my part, I was extremely touched that everyone showed. As a teacher, you&#39;d like to think you&#39;ve had enough of an impact that your students would give back, but we rarely get any evidence as to the effects we&#39;ve had. I&#39;ve been fortunate enough to be in contact with a number of my alums through the years and a number of them have been kind enough express gratitude (often times more than I deserve) but to see everyone show up en masse really meant a lot to me. The only down side was there was so much going on, I really didn&#39;t get to spend time with anyone -- it was like hosting a wedding or bar mitzvah -- everyone&#39;s there, but you don&#39;t get to see anyone. I hope we can remedy this with more events and smaller events in the future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If any of the &#34;family&#34; is reading this, you&#39;ve also got to give me some props -- even though I haven&#39;t seen many of the alums in years, I recognized almost everyone and remembered far more names than I probably deserved to.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We spent the evening mixing students and alums and the FourSquare crew threw in tours of the facilities. Afterwards, many of the alums stayed back to discuss how to move Stuy CS forward. How the alumni community can help Stuy CS&amp;nbsp;and it&#39;s current students and how it can become a resource for fellow alums. I think there are a lot of things we can do as a community, and I&#39;m excited about what&#39;s to come in the near future for us as a group.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For the students, feedback has been terrific. I&#39;ve gotten comments like:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;I was wavering between whether or not I would continue CS in college and as a career, but now I&#39;m fairly certain.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;I really enjoyed the compsci&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;il&#34; style=&#34;background-attachment: initial; background-clip: initial; background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); background-image: initial; background-origin: initial; color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;, it was very helpful to talk to alumni because they reminded me that there is life after college. I also liked the community within a community feel of the&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;il&#34; style=&#34;background-attachment: initial; background-clip: initial; background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); background-image: initial; background-origin: initial; color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222; font-family: arial, sans-serif; font-size: x-small;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;The students pretty much universally loved the event and &amp;nbsp;I really think they got a lot out of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.917969); color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;We had parent conferences last Thursday and Friday and parent after parent confirmed this. Just about every visitor I had mentioned how much their son or daughter got out of meeting the &#34;family&#34;. People &amp;nbsp;who were in their shoes a few short years ago and are now doing great things in the tech community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222; font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;From what I can tell, this was a unique event, at least to Stuy, no one&#39;s ever done anything like this before in any subject area. It looks like it was a slam dunk, at least with respect to value to the students.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Now the &#34;family&#34; just has to decide where we can go from here.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#39;1&#39; height=&#39;1&#39; src=&#39;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/468689896075458340-6020489050963401462?l=cestlaz.blogspot.com&#39; alt=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Student</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-01-15-my-favorite-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-01-15-my-favorite-student/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;

&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;tr-caption-container&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-jER9_A86OtU/TxMfvZAQI5I/AAAAAAAAGtQ/8zSaqDnUe-U/s1600/Screenshot+at+2012-01-15+13%253A48%253A37.png&#34; imageanchor=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;228&#34; src=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-jER9_A86OtU/TxMfvZAQI5I/AAAAAAAAGtQ/8zSaqDnUe-U/s320/Screenshot+at+2012-01-15+13%253A48%253A37.png&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;tr-caption&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Fred Wilson and me at #SOTC2012&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Last week I was given the honor of attending the State of the City address. The mayor was announcing a new school for the fall. An Academy for Software Engineering. This has been in the works for a while and has a long way to go but the announcement was a major step. The project really got its start a couple of years ago. I&#39;d been working hard for years prior trying to get the city to help me grow the program I developed at Stuyvesant, but until Fred got involved, there was no movement. Fred has to receive much of the credit for any good that we do as a result of this and I&#39;d like to&amp;nbsp;publicly&amp;nbsp;thank him. If you don&#39;t follow Fred, you can read his post on the school&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.avc.com/a_vc/2012/01/the-academy-for-software-engineering.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It was pretty neat to be on stage for the announcement, but those of you who know me know that I&#39;m not a self promoter and these types of events aren&#39;t &#34;me.&#34;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;What I found really special, were the emails and tweets I got from my former students over the next day or so. As a teacher, we&#39;d like to think we are in some way a &#34;force for good&#34; in our student&#39;s lives and we rarely get to really see what impact we do or don&#39;t have. To hear from so many and such gracious comments brought tears to my eyes. Thanks guys.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I&#39;ve been thinking a lot about my career as a teacher recently. I decided to leave industry over twenty years ago. As teachers, particularly teachers with technical backgrounds we leave a financially lucrative field to enter one with very few financial rewards. It&#39;s also a field very much under attack, particularly in recent years. The current line of thought seems to be that teachers are to blame for everything bad in education and government and private interests, everything good. As a senior teacher, I&#39;m particularly worthless, at least according to what I&#39;ve heard on the radio over the past year.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So, what do I get out of the deal?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Well, when I hear form my graduates, I know that I&#39;ve made a difference.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Also, the friendships I&#39;ve developed over the years.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;tr-caption-container&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;eq&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; src=&#34;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-d1KZ2LtyNbs/TuPud4EM8hI/AAAAAAAAGq0/9M__1ubQhWI/s400/IMG_20111210_184233.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;tr-caption&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Stuy &#39;84, &#39;95, 2013, 2015 and families&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A few weeks ago, we were catching up with a few of the Stuy &#39;95 crew. We do it far too infrequently. They were students, they&#39;re now friends. I&#39;ve had the privilege of seeing many young people grow to adulthood, get married, have children and in a small way I&#39;ve been able to share in their lives. This is the upside of my career choice.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Maybe this is a result of being a computer science teacher who tries to keep a foot in the tech world. Maybe something else.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;From the college student who stops by just to say hello to the graduate living across the country who drops a line to say how they&#39;re doing. That&#39;s the upside of the teaching profession.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Recently I thought it would be a good idea to organize the Stuy CS family. Collect email addresse and get a network going. I posted on facebook and sent out a few emails two days ago. So far, 240+ signups.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A while ago someone asked me who was my favorite student?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;They&#39;re the ones that I&#39;m still in touch with many years after they graduate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#39;1&#39; height=&#39;1&#39; src=&#39;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/468689896075458340-1213107704301509869?l=cestlaz.blogspot.com&#39; alt=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talking Shop</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-06-talking-shop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-06-talking-shop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my first few years teaching computer science, I frequently felt isolated. As pretty much the only CS guy I really didn&#39;t have any one to &#34;talk shop&#34; with. It&#39;s hard to bounce pedagogical ideas off of your colleagues when they teach subjects that are tangentially related, at best. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I now consider myself extremely fortunate that I have four terrific friends and colleagues teaching CS with me. Now we have the same advantage that other teachers have enjoyed for years.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I started one of my favorite topics in my AP classes, recursion. Our students have already done recursion during the scheme unit of our intro class so today was at some levels, a review. Most of the students were fine with the basic concepts, but I wanted to make sure they had a solid foundation before we moved to more advanced problems. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I realized even though I &#34;got&#34; recursion back when I was starting out as a CS student those many years ago, no one ever really explained how the call stack worked. When you&#39;re calling functions and methods all over the place, how does the system know to return to the right place at the right time. It was alluded to when we expanded a recursion: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;fact(4) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 4*fact(3) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 3*fact(2) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 2*fact(1) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 1*fact(0) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 1 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;but never in the general sense of function calls. I thought it might make sense to try to &#34;demystify&#34; the computer and explain how things really worked.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I outlined a basic memory layout, stack, heap, data segment and roughly defined a stack frame (storing parameters, local variables, and a return address). We then looked at a code snippet such as: &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;pre class=&#34;src src-Java&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;a()&lt;br /&gt;{&lt;br /&gt;  b();&lt;br /&gt;  c();&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;b()&lt;br /&gt;{&lt;br /&gt;  c();&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;c()&lt;br /&gt;{&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;main()&lt;br /&gt;{&lt;br /&gt;  a();&lt;br /&gt;  b();&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;    &lt;p&gt;and traced through the stack. We then did this with a couple of simple recursive examples. Only time will tell if this was helpful, but I think it was worth the time. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I particularly enjoyed was later that day when I was talking shop with my fellow AP teacher. He wasn&#39;t planning on explaining the stack in this kind of detail but he liked the idea and planned to use that part of my lesson. I look forward to hearing how it went. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have likewise borrowed ideas from his and our other colleagues classes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any CS teachers out there, I&#39;m sure we&#39;d all love to hear classroom techniques that have and haven&#39;t worked. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;blogger-post-footer&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#39;1&#39; height=&#39;1&#39; src=&#39;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/468689896075458340-4999548631085910659?l=cestlaz.blogspot.com&#39; alt=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>