<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>online on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/online/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (online)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 11:48:20 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/online/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Online -  Day 01</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-online-day-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 11:48:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-online-day-01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I taught my first two online classes this morning. The first one from
8:10 - 9:25 and the second from 9:45 - 11:00.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Toolset:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Zoom meetings
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs (yes, not just an editor)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First up Zoom.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I want a video camera on policy. All my students should have
laptops with working cameras. Some students might have issues with
showing even a small bit of what&amp;#39;s behind them so I don&amp;#39;t want to make
it required but I really wish they&amp;#39;d also have cameras on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To get some level of visual feedback and interaction. Having made over
60 &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs/&#34;&gt;Emacs videos&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;m used to talking to my own screen but when you know
you&amp;#39;ve got a live audience that you&amp;#39;re working with it&amp;#39;s different. If
I&amp;#39;m just talking to a bunch of black boxes with names in them I don&amp;#39;t
feel any connection with my students. If I see them I feel we&amp;#39;re
together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was also an issue when I went to screen sharing. Now Zoom handled
the screen sharing terrifically.  You can share either one specific
window, a virtual whiteboard or your whole screen. When sharing,
though, instead of seeing a bunch of small windows with lots of people
in them you only see around four which isn&amp;#39;t representative of the
whole class. Better than nothing but I wish I had a long line of boxes
that could easily scroll.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another thing with the screen sharing - it worked great but this is
also where two monitors would be helpful. I went from two 30&amp;#34; monitors
to one 43&amp;#34; 4K monitor. I love my current setup but it seems with Zoom
you share all or nothing. I&amp;#39;m guessing with two monitors I could share
one monitor and use the other for notes and staging. With one big
monitor I can&amp;#39;t do this - I have to share the whole screen. Not a huge
problem but makes things a bit less smooth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is where Emacs comes in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a decent part of the lesson, I&amp;#39;d share my Emacs window. Since I
can split the window and quickly jump between buffers (screens) I
could bring up a variety of things. I had a shell in one buffer so I
could run terminal stuff, a source code buffer, one in org-mode for
outlines and table work and one in artist mode for rudimentary
diagramming. I think it worked reasonably well for a first shot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we also used the Zoom chat. Some students would mic on and
off to take part but more used the chat. It was a bit weird at
first. I&amp;#39;d talk, they&amp;#39;d write but both classes got into a pretty good
tempo after a while. I think it could work. Interesting though was
that my first class had a bunch of cross class chat in the general
(public) chat during the lesson. Silly remarks back and forth. Truth
be told, I liked it. My second class didn&amp;#39;t although there might have
been some of that in private chats.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I asked the classes to share what their other instructors are doing
and using and I&amp;#39;m really interested in hearing. I&amp;#39;m also hoping that
they&amp;#39;re open with me in terms of what&amp;#39;s working and what isn&amp;#39;t. I want
this to be the best experience for them that we can create and I&amp;#39;m not
so proud as to think I know how to do it and that they don&amp;#39;t know
better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now to plan for the next one.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching online - a test run</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/online-testrun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 16:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/online-testrun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s classes are still on hiatus while we figure out how we&amp;#39;re
going to deliver instruction remotely. I have it easier than
most. First, my students all get laptops as being part of the Daedalus
program. This doesn&amp;#39;t mean they have great internet access or access
at all but it does mean they have a device that can run everything we
need them to run. I don&amp;#39;t yet know if they all have adequate internet
access but I&amp;#39;m hoping it&amp;#39;s either not an issue or one that we can
easily figure out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, software. Again, I&amp;#39;m lucky. Zoom seems to be the best of breed
for synchronous stuff and as faculty in the school of education, I
have an account. The rest of the CS faculty don&amp;#39;t. The rest of Hunter
has to use some combination of Blackboard based tools and freely
available stuff. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today, we tested everything out. I had about 10 students volunteer. We
did a Zoom meeting and tried all the feature: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
public and private chat
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
screen sharing
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
whiteboards
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
breakout rooms
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The breakout rooms were the big thing I wanted to check out. They&amp;#39;re a
little clunky but overall pretty nice. It&amp;#39;s a bit kludgey when someone
joins the conference after breakout rooms are formed but overall it
worked well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For async stuff we&amp;#39;ll mostly stick with the same tools - email, GitHub
and GitHub classroom but I think we&amp;#39;ll also give Slack another go. My
problem with Slack is that it didn&amp;#39;t seem to work well within the
students day. It may work for a professional in front of their screen
most of the day but students are in and out of class and other
obligations. They&amp;#39;ll miss the real time flow and then have to navigate
through a muddy thread stream to catch up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now with everyone working from home Slack might be a better fit. We&amp;#39;ll
see.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thursday I go live. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think the lesson I&amp;#39;m planning for my CS1 translates pretty easily to
online but might have to work my CS2 plans. In any event we&amp;#39;ll see how
it goes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure the rest of the semester will be challenging for all of us
but I also know it&amp;#39;s okay if we fumble through and make mistakes. &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/focus-to-feel-normal/&#34;&gt;It&amp;#39;s
not all about the content&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Would love to hear from my fellow teachers how it&amp;#39;s working with
them. Alfred Thompson has already been blogging about &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2020/03/teaching-from-homeday-1.html&#34;&gt;his experiences&lt;/a&gt;
with going remote so we&amp;#39;re getting play by play from a rural private
(Catholic) high school. I&amp;#39;ll add the NYC public college
experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want to share how it&amp;#39;s going for you but don&amp;#39;t blog, send it as
a long comment or do a guest post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll all be more isolated physically over the next few weeks so let&amp;#39;s
share more in the digital world.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing to teach Online</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/preparing-for-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 23:54:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/preparing-for-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been seeing some tweets over the past couple of days about the
wonders of online teaching. How it&amp;#39;s at least as good or better than
in person or how we should have been doing it all along. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rubbish.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you say that online is better than in person that says more about
the (low) quality of your teaching than it does about the quality of
online tech teaching resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mean, it&amp;#39;s pretty clear that anything you can do online you can do
in person since you can still avail yourselves of the same tech tools
while you can also do the in person live stuff. Online you&amp;#39;ve only got
online.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking at it another way, is an online show, concert, or sporting
event (weather notwithstanding) ever better than the live thing?
There&amp;#39;s something about in person even when you take away the
connection between teacher and students and students and students that
makes it special.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While online isn&amp;#39;t better there are times where it&amp;#39;s necessary or can
be used to complement or enhance in person. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter hasn&amp;#39;t made any announcements about any closings due to COVID19
but it would be foolish not to prepare. I also want to figure out if
some of my CS Teacher Certification program can be offered remotely as
not all interested teachers can get to campus. For these reasons and a
few more, I think I&amp;#39;d like to try to do at least a couple of my
classes remotely over the next few of weeks (sooner if it&amp;#39;s forced
upon us).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Technology shouldn&amp;#39;t be a problem - all my students get a laptop as
part of the Daedalus program. The only questions are will they have
sufficient bandwidth if they&amp;#39;re joining from home and if they have a
suitable location from where they can connect in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As part of Hunter&amp;#39;s School of Education I can use Zoom and that has
the video conferencing, chat, screen sharing and whiteboarding. The
only thing I have to workout  is how to use the breakout room features
for group work and to see if that can flow nicely in the class. I&amp;#39;ve
got a couple of lessons that should work pretty well as first time
experiments so overall it should be pretty easy to give it a go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will it be as good as live? No. Will it be better than nothing?
Absolutely. Is it worth burning a live class to learn a bit about
online - to see what can be done without extensive training and class
prep and to see what can be leveraged in a pinch? I think so.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If it happens, I&amp;#39;ll report back.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>