<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>policy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (policy)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 08:18:21 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reopening Schools - de Blasio and Carranza throw kids and teachers under the bus.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reopening-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 08:18:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/reopening-schools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Bill de Blasio and Richard Carranza unveiled their open the
schools in the fall plan. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The plan is perfectly consistent with de Blasio and Carranza&amp;#39;s
education policies and efforts in general - tone deaf, ineffective,
and in this case, unsafe.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know we were told that part of this came from survey results but we
all know that surveys are super easy to fix. I mean, ask any teacher
or parent &amp;#34;do you want schools to be open and in person in the Fall?&amp;#34;
and everyone will say &amp;#34;yes.&amp;#34; Of course, there&amp;#39;s the implication that
it&amp;#39;s safe and I bet that part didn&amp;#39;t make it in to the surveys.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t watch the news conference live, but I was told that while
principals, parents, and children were mentioned over and over as
consulted constituents when forming the plan, somehow teachers never
came up. Typical.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The basics of the plan is that students could go all remote or hybrid
and under the hybrid model, they&amp;#39;d be in the schools some days and not
others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does this address health concerns? Doubtful. They&amp;#39;re talking about a
third to half the students attending at a time. Take a look at any
school on opening and closing - it&amp;#39;s wall to wall from the school to
the subway. It&amp;#39;s a mess. Many schools are already split schedule -
they have their kids entry and egress staggered into halves or thirds
and the beginning and end of days there are &lt;strong&gt;STILL&lt;/strong&gt; wall to wall for
blocks not to mention the subway platforms and cars. Even 1/3 isn&amp;#39;t
going to do it and the more you stagger, the more you lengthen the
school days and this affects both staff and families. What good is
having a kid go to school so you can work if they don&amp;#39;t start until
mid day?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s assume, although I don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s a safe assumption, that you
can get the kids to and from school safety. How big are the
classrooms? I heard that some Stuy teacher&amp;#39;s measured them and they
could safely accommodate something like 9 -  12 people. That&amp;#39;s in line
with what DbD said but what about transfer between classes? Some
schools - particularly those in converted spaces have TINY halls or
limited stairwells. What about bathrooms? None of this has been
addressed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about cleaning? Teachers have regularly begged for basic
supplies. Schools go without necessities like toilet paper and the
Mayor&amp;#39;s saying that we&amp;#39;ll have sufficient masks and cleaning supplies?
Good luck with that! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even if we have the supplies, will they be used and used correctly and
often enough? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about compliance? For years, schools had a &amp;#34;no hats&amp;#34; policy but
rarely are there no hats. Even when the policy works, usually it&amp;#39;s a
result of teachers continually asking students to remove their
hats. How did those cell phone bans work? Do we really believe we can
get 100% compliance from students, teachers, and staff? What about the
younger grades? We really expect them to comply with adult
protocols?????
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even if everything is implemented, will it keep everyone safe?
Unlikely. Professional and big time college sports have extreme
incentive to &amp;#34;open up&amp;#34;, boatloads of money and everyone pulling in the
same direction. They test all the time, have all the space they need
and can implement whatever protocols they want. Even with all this we
keep hearing about new cases in those populations. If they can&amp;#39;t do it
how can underfunded schools?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With all of this, even if it&amp;#39;s safe and even if schools can manage
reasonable schedules, students will only be going to school a couple
of times a week - will this really help parents? Maybe not. I remember
when we had Batya. We were looking for child care for just a couple of
days a week. Five days was easy, no days was easy but just a couple -
not so much. What about the shifted days? Large schools might need 4
shifts. Kids either start and end super early or super late. Will that
help parents who work &amp;#34;regular time&amp;#34; jobs?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, let&amp;#39;s get to the education side of things. High school
teachers teach five classes a day. Around 34 kids in a class. Given
room size restrictions that  means we have to split into threes. If
one teacher has to deal with this then it&amp;#39;s a HUGE increase in
work. If kids come to school on different days they&amp;#39;ll get different
live lessons - for each class teachers will have to make at least one
in person lesson and at least one corresponding remote lesson and I&amp;#39;m
over simplifying. Since you&amp;#39;re now &amp;#34;teaching&amp;#34; 10 or 15 classes instead
of 5 I don&amp;#39;t see how you can meet with them in person and deliver
synchronous remote instruction which means you&amp;#39;re only actually
interacting with your students once or twice a week and there&amp;#39;s no way
teachers will be able to actually develop materials, assess students,
and maintain meaningful contact unless someone finds a whole lot of
hours to the day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if the teacher just does the in person and another
or other teachers do the remote you&amp;#39;ll have multiple teachers teaching
a single class without any real coordination  - this is yet another
recipe for disaster.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get it - we all want to get back to normal. I want to be with my
students but I want to be with them safely. I also get that some
students are not doing well in isolation and that remote school is
both less effective than in person and a hardship all around but when
we open it has to make sense both in terms of safety and in terms of
education. de Blasio and Carranza&amp;#39;s plan is neither.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why are police held to such a lower standard than teachers?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 12:36:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-police-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
My friend Neal Zupancic, actually former student, friend, and long
time teacher Neal Zupancic posted this on Facebook. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s 100% spot on. I&amp;#39;d add my two cents but Neal captured it better
than I ever could. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take a minute to read it:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my ten years of teaching, I&amp;#39;ve dealt with a number of situations
that could have potentially turned dangerous.  I&amp;#39;ve taught in public
schools and private; urban schools and rural.  I have de-escalated
every last one of those situations.  I have never once used force.  I
once broke up a fist fight using only my voice and my presence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never felt the need to announce that before, because it&amp;#39;s just a
part of my profession.  Every teacher knows it and most of the public
knows as well.  And there are teachers who have been in far more
dangerous situations than I have.  Teachers who deal with gang
activity, drug dealers, kids who bring weapons to school with the
intent to use them, kids who fight and don&amp;#39;t necessarily stop when you
show up.  I know teachers who have been assaulted by students.  I know
teachers who have been threatened by students, including with deadly
weapons.  Every teacher is expected to deal with every one of these
situations without using force or violence.  Some of us are
well-trained, and some of us are thrown in and just go on instinct.
But we de-escalate.  We calm.  We soothe.  We help.  We repair and
restore the community.  We heal people.  We build an environment in
which those we are responsible for can thrive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I keep seeing people ask &amp;#34;who would want to be a cop if you could get
fired for doing your job?&amp;#34;  But literally any teacher could do that
job without killing people.  Literally any teacher would have had the
patience to talk George Floyd into getting into that police car
instead of tossing him on the ground and murdering him.  Literally any
teacher would have let Rayshard Brooks get away rather than shooting
him dead, knowing that the system would provide accountability for his
resisting arrest and that you didn&amp;#39;t have to be his executioner.
Literally any teacher knows that by the time you are in a power
struggle with a student, you have already lost.
Literally. any. teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I hear these cops whining on social media and it sickens me.  They
wouldn&amp;#39;t last a day teaching.  And of course we see that when we see
how often cops in schools arrest kids for routine behavior problems
that teachers could have solved peacefully.  We already know cops
can&amp;#39;t handle teenagers without resorting to force.  We already know
cops in schools exacerbate racism and inequality - just like they do
outside of schools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And the reason for that is that we fire teachers who can&amp;#39;t control
their tempers.  We fire teachers who use force rather than let them
stay on the job and keep escalating that force until they kill
someone.  We &lt;strong&gt;weed out&lt;/strong&gt; the bad apples.  And no teacher would ever
dream of protesting or walking off the job in support of someone who
got fired for assaulting a student.  Are you kidding me?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m reading posts in teacher&amp;#39;s groups about going back to school in
fall - or in some cases, in July or August to extend the school year -
without adequate protection from coronavirus, without enough room in
their halls and classrooms to socially distance, without funding for
hand sanitizer or wipes or masks, without training or PD on blended or
distance learning, without promised raises because municipalities have
lost tax revenue because of corona - and then I see cops who walk
around in body armor and work for departments that own tanks, whining
about how hard their jobs are because they&amp;#39;re finally catching flak
for shooting people, and it&amp;#39;s like - what are your priorities?  Where
is your perspective?  What kind of society do you expect to raise into
the next generation when you&amp;#39;ll fund a militarized occupying force
with impunity for homicide but you won&amp;#39;t buy teachers masks and
sanitizer during a pandemic?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And teachers never, ever, ever whine like these cops do.  My
&lt;strong&gt;students&lt;/strong&gt; don&amp;#39;t even whine like these cops do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Seriously - where do they find these people?  Our job is a hundred
times harder and if we mess up even once the way cops do every day,
we&amp;#39;re out in a heartbeat.  And yet if I whined about it the way cops
whine about it, people would say &amp;#34;hey man, maybe you should stfu and
find a different job.&amp;#34;  And they&amp;#39;d be right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So to all the cops out there who think they have it rough: You ain&amp;#39;t
nothing compared to a teacher.  STFU and find a different job.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future consequences of today&#39;s grading policies</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/grading-consequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 07:08:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/grading-consequences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
How are we going to deal with grades? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This has garnered a lot of attention since COVID-19 struck.  Over on
the AP side people wonder if colleges will give credit? Do the tests
mean anything? What about the material they won&amp;#39;t be testing? We also
have had standardized tests canceled and a variety of grading
policies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m going to stay away from AP this time around - you all know my
feelings about the college board. I will leave you with a couple of
good posts though that share many of my views (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insidehighered.com/admissions/views/2020/05/26/ap-courses-do-not-deserve-college-credit-opinion&#34;&gt;AP Courses don&amp;#39;t
deserve college credit&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;https://jd2718.org/2020/05/18/retiring-advanced-placement/&#34;&gt; Retiring Advanced Placement&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The bottom line is that student and teachers lives have been severely
disrupted  since early March. In NYC public schools that means three
to four months which is a considerable chunk of the semester. In
college the percent is slightly less but it&amp;#39;s still a good chunk. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some students have done fine but many have had difficulty and I&amp;#39;d
venture a guess to say most won&amp;#39;t end the semester in the same place
they would have under normal circumstances.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about this as a result of Hunter&amp;#39;s policy and I
don&amp;#39;t really have a good answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter decided that instructors would award grades as they normally
would. Each instructor would follow their own counsel on how to
grade. Should they be super lenient due to circumstances? Extra hard
because of perceived cheating (don&amp;#39;t get me started on this), same old
same old or some other method. Once grades were awarded, students have
the ability to change any or all classes to pass/fail. Normally if a
student takes a class pass/fail it can&amp;#39;t be used as a prerequisite or
to fill a major requirement but for this past semester, it can. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I like this policy - it gives the students most of the control
and they don&amp;#39;t have to decide on anything until after the fact. The
bad part comes in though with the any passed class counting as a
prerequisite of for the major. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s say I have a student in CS1 who was doing well but really
struggled at the end after we went remote. Maybe that student was
doing A or B work up to the switch but basically got nothing out of
the rest of the semester. I wouldn&amp;#39;t want to fail the student. Under
normal circumstances, we make the false assumption that the grade is
entirely the result of the student and factors surrounding the
student&amp;#39;s environment. Even if that assumption were 100% true the Covid
Curve Ball was not the students fault and the negative impact to their
studies could not only be due to their circumstances but also due to
actions of the college or the way the instructor reacted to the
circumstances. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With Hunter&amp;#39;s policy, I could award any passing grade - even a D and
the student could convert it to a Pass and move on to CS2. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The danger here is that the student might not be prepared for CS2. We
cover memory pointers, memory management, and classes at the end of
CS1. So much of CS2 is built on pointer based programs that a student
who missed out on that in CS1 is going to struggle mightily. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You might say that the kid could have retaken CS1 but there&amp;#39;s a wrench
in the works. If the kid failed CS1 they could retake it. With a Pass
they can&amp;#39;t. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A student could, with the permission of some instructor audit the
missed parts of CS1 or self study but we know that won&amp;#39;t always
happen.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The alternative is to award a failing grade to the student which would
then hurt their GPA and force them to retake the entire course.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You might say that the school could just adjust the curricula for next
year but it&amp;#39;s not that simple. In high school most students progress
in lockstep. In college there&amp;#39;s more variation. Next semester&amp;#39;s CS2
will have students who completed CS1 this past semester under the
cloud of COVID-19, students who completed it on the Fall, some from
summer and some from other places. This is where curricular
consistency is somewhat more important.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I do like Hunter&amp;#39;s policy and I do think it&amp;#39;s on the side of the
student but I&amp;#39;m not happy about this loophole.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This probably won&amp;#39;t affect a huge number of students but some will
fall through the cracks. As I said, I don&amp;#39;t have a good answer but it
is something I&amp;#39;m really concerned about.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest Post - Missing out on a great opportunity in education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:53:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Preamble
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve never accepted a guest post before but when my friend and long
time colleague JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver said he had something to say I
was all for it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JonAlf&amp;#39;s one of the best teachers I know - he started at Brandeis HS and
has been at Stuy forever. Really sharp guy, great teacher, and really
perceptive. When he has something to say it&amp;#39;s 100% worth listening
to. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To JonAlf - since I know this is one of my blog posts you&amp;#39;ll actually
read - you should set up a blog of your own. The community would be
all the better for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Missing out on a great opportunity in education
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
By JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the wake of the COVID-19 crisis, educators across the nation are
adapting to remote learning. I’ve watched my colleagues work hard
putting together plans on how to deliver content, engage students and
assess their learning. Some, like myself, are combining multiple tools
in order to achieve these goals while others are using a single
platform for it all. I count myself lucky that the administration in
my school has given its teachers the leeway to select their own tools
instead of forcing a single platform on us. Last week, as I was
thinking through what my plan was going to be, a particular thought
kept nagging at me:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We are facing an amazing opportunity in the world of education. Think
of how many lessons, worksheets, notes, examples, etc. are being put
out in some electronic form.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students will (hopefully) have access to the materials for their
classes, and teachers in the same school may also be able to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will never be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about the teacher three states away that’s struggling to find good resources or new problems?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will never be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about the student in a different district, perhaps one that has
shut down entirely, who just wants to learn and do some work in order
to help fill the days?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
How much of this work will never be seen?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The internet gives us the ability to put all of these resources out
there to the public, and it pains me to think about how much of this
work is going to be hidden behind one platform or another. So many of
the educational technologies make it very easy to post work for your
class and very hard, if not impossible, to share it with other people
(you’re school doesn’t also have a license for XYZ?, sorry).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, there are many teachers out there that have no choice, they
are being mandated to use whatever the school decrees. There are
others, perhaps the less technically savvy, that are going to use
whatever they can get trained on quickly. We’re all running a 2 minute
drill and working with what we have. I get that, and it is not a
teacher’s job to provide materials for everyone. That being said, If
you have the knowhow, or would like to learn, there are ways to make
your work publicly available. Last summer Mike and I ran a session at
the CSTA conference on using GitHub for just this purpose, and hope to
run a workshop on it this summer (For those interested, I made a brief
tutorial about how to do this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KzSE_H3rfMs&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KzSE_H3rfMs&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For my part, I’ll be putting everything on my class websites, if you
need any ideas for intro to cs in python here’s my class:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/intro1-dw/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/intro1-dw/&#34;&gt;https://www.stuycs.org/intro1-dw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. If your’re looking for advanced cs,
I’ve got a computer graphics class here:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/graphics-dw/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stuycs.org/graphics-dw/&#34;&gt;https://www.stuycs.org/graphics-dw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Thomas Friedman&#39;s editorial on the College Board&#39;s Two Codes left me concerned</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 10:20:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-boards-two-codes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There was some buzz over &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/12/opinion/college-board-sat-ap.html&#34;&gt;this editorial&lt;/a&gt; about the College Board last
week. The two codes every child needs - Coding and the US
Constitution? Who could argue with that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not going to disagree. Civics and CS are important and can&amp;#39;t wait
until college. The thing that left me chilled though was that nobody&amp;#39;s
paying attention to the fact that the College Board - a private entity
with its own interests has so much influence over American education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the piece, Friedman states:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So rather than have SAT exams and Advanced Placement courses based on things that you cram for and forget, they are shifting them, where they can, to promote the “two codes.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In 2016, the College Board completely revamped its approach toA.P. computer science courses and exams. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nothing wrong here but the AP program is supposed to offer &amp;#34;college
level&amp;#34; work in high school. Back when the program started, from 
best I can figure, they offered exams based on courses that were
essentially HS implementations of college classes. Now they&amp;#39;re
flipping the script. They&amp;#39;re dictating what they think should be
taught at the high school level and, oh by the way, it&amp;#39;s college level
because it has the AP designation. The editorial goes into some
details. Now, I&amp;#39;m not against what they&amp;#39;re doing with AP US Gov, it
sounds like a really good idea. I&amp;#39;m against their overall influence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest concern I had though was with this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides revamping the government course and the exam on that subject, Coleman and Sanford in 2014 made a staple of the regular SAT a long reading comprehension passage from one of the founding documents, such as the Constitution, or another important piece of democracy, like a great presidential speech. That said to students and teachers something the SAT had never dared say before: Some content is disproportionately more powerful and important, and if you prepare for it you will be rewarded on the SAT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we put this on the SAT, schools will teach it so the kids will do
better the SAT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This should be chilling to everyone. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No, I&amp;#39;m not against the details but it&amp;#39;s frightening to have a private
entity with so much influence on public policy like
education. Ultimately, it can&amp;#39;t be good. Just because what the College
Board&amp;#39;s pushing in terms of civics jives with me doesn&amp;#39;t mean they
should be able to influence and manipulate curriculum across the
nation to such a degree. The College Board is pretty much accountable
to nobody. As long as students are told to take AP classes and the
SAT, particularly with politicians and boards of education agreeing to
pay the college board with taxpayers money, the public has very little
say. Sure, more better civics and CS is good but who&amp;#39;s to say the next
initiative will be in the public&amp;#39;s interest?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The same can be said for any of the major education players - for and
non profit alike both in and out of CS. We have to be more aware,
vigilant, and vocal when the power players accomplish things by being
the 800 pound gorilla even when we agree with what some of those
things are.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a big reason why I frequently speak out against the College
Board and other power players, some of whom I greatly like, respect,
and admire, and feel that others should feel obligated to do the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>