<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conferences on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/conferences/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (conferences)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/conferences/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeland 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codeland-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent today at &lt;a href=&#34;https://codelandconf.com/&#34;&gt;Codeland&lt;/a&gt;, a one day conference in NYC designed for
developers in the early stages of their careers. Just as at CSTA, I
was there with the GitHub contingent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Codeland had talks and a keynote in a common auditorium, smaller
breakout workshops and a couple of small vendor areas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent most of the morning upstairs in the GitHub lounge so I onl
caught part of one morning talk. Up in the lounge we, along with the
other vendors - IBM, Flatiron health, and Command Line Hero were
available to talk shop and hang out with conference goers. To be
honest, not too many people came by. I attribute that to the fact that
we were up on the ninth floor and the elevators didn&amp;#39;t work very
well. We were in a nice space with plenty of areas for conference
goers to relax, schmooze, get a snack and even play games but it was
too much of an effort to get to us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also decided not to attend any of the workshops and stayed up in the
lounge. The workshops were targeted at new devs early in their career
so while some looked interesting to me, I didn&amp;#39;t want to take up a
seat from anyone who really could benefit from them,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, I relocated to the downstairs vendor area. That was much
better. Since it was right near both the snacks and the main
auditorium there was much more foot traffic. I also got to hear and
see all the afternoon talks since audio and video were available right
near where I was set up. They were pretty cool. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, the best part of the conference was the ability to talk with
the conference attendees. On the one hand, I was there to talk GitHub
but I also had the chance to talk general tech with them. I got to
talk to people at all stages on their coding journeys. There were
undergraduate students studying CS, second career people either in
code schools or self learning, Former CS students who&amp;#39;s lives had gone
in other directions but now they&amp;#39;re looking to get back into tech and
more. I got to hear about the excitement of their adventures and tried
to give advice and encouragement to those having a hard time breaking
in to tech. Having shepherded so many people from neophytes to
professionals I&amp;#39;d like to think I could provide some guidance to some
of the people chatted with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if there are any other conferences like Codeland but if
there aren&amp;#39;t there should be. It can be hard to break into tech and
Codeland created both a safe environment for tech newbies and also
provided really valuable content. I wasn&amp;#39;t familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codenewbie.org/&#34;&gt;CodeNewbie&lt;/a&gt;,
the organization behind Codeland before but now I&amp;#39;ll have to see if I
can have a sit down with them to talk shop and tech ed.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2019 - Using GitHub as a CMS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 12:09:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2019-github/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
With ISTE ending, the next big event for CS treachers is the annual
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.csteachers.org/page/2019conference&#34;&gt;CSTA Conference&lt;/a&gt;. I first attended two years ago in Baltimore. Last
year the conference, in Omaha was bigger and better in every way
imaginable. I expect this year to be the best yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t go to a lot of conferences so I don&amp;#39;t have much to compare
CSTA with but I like the fact that it&amp;#39;s is about half the size of
SIGCSE. At about 1000 attendees it still feels small enough to be
intimate but at the same time large enough so that there&amp;#39;s something
for everyone and plenty of people to learn and share from and with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just like last year, I&amp;#39;ll be spending a lot of time at the GitHub
booth so if you want to talk about how to use GitHub to support your
students make sure to stop by and say hello.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll also be giving a session with my long time partner in crime
JonAlf. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of us know that Git is a version control system and that
GitHub is pretty much the industry standard platform for using
Git. Many of us also know that GitHub for Education has a great
toolset to support using GitHub with your classes. Tools that help
organize, distribute, collect, and assess assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fewer people know that GitHub can be used to really easily create a
web presence and as a way to distribute class material and you don&amp;#39;t
even have to use the command line if you don&amp;#39;t want to. I use GitHub
as a lightweight CMS with my classes, to host full blown web sites,
and also to host this blog.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Come join JonAlf and me on Tuesday at 11:15 in West 106C and we&amp;#39;ll
show you how you can use GitHub as a web presence as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also want to briefly mention that my better half, Devorah, is going
to be with us at the GitHub booth running a really cool
knitting/crocheting for  charity project (thanks to both CSTA and
GitHub for facilitating this). I&amp;#39;ll write more about it in a day or so
but if you&amp;#39;re going to be at CSTA2019 and you knit or crochet or want
to learn, you can check the project out here:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (note that the site is hosted on
GitHub and the source is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/blanketstatementproject/blanketstatementproject.github.io&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
GitHub is also holding a pre-conference reception on July 7 from
5:30 - 8:00. You can sign up &lt;a href=&#34;https://csta-github-meetup.confetti.events/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope to see many of you in a couple of weeks in Phoenix.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB World 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 19:35:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
For those of you who don&amp;#39;t know, MongoDB is a very popular NoSQL
database. NoSQL  is an overarching term describing databases that
are not relational and don&amp;#39;t implement Structured Query Language
(SQL). In a relational database your data is stored in tables with
columns - think spreadsheet where each row of the table is a record in
the database. You link tables together via a common field or row
name. NoSQL databases work differently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
MongoDB is a document store. In MongoDB a document is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://json.org/&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;
object. Essentially a Javascript (or Python) dictionary. As a result
you do things differently. I plan to write up something more on the
differences between SQL and NoSQL in the near future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been using MongoDB on and off for a number of years. I use it for
personal projects and also in the software development course I taught
at Stuy. The community edition is free and easy to install and it&amp;#39;s
very easy for a beginner to get started.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s say you wanted to store information about a students. You might
create this dictionary:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  student &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; { &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Last&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Hugginkis&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;First&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Amanda&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;ID&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1245&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Homeroom&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;5A&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,
              &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Schedule&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; : [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Eng&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Math&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Gym&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;CS&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Lunch&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Physcis&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Band&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;]}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You add this to your database like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;db&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;students&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;insert(students)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later, you can query for all the students in Homeroom 5A:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;db&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;students&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;find({&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;Homeroom&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;5A&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Super quick and easy. It also comes with a nice REPL - essentially a
Javascript interpreter -  to play with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve spent the last two days at MongoDB World 2019. A great conference
if you want to get up to speed on MongoDB. I left reminded of a number
of great MongoDB products that I hadn&amp;#39;t really used and a few new ones
they&amp;#39;re just launching:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Atlas
This is their DB as service. Don&amp;#39;t want to administer your own
installation? Just spin up an Atlas cluster. The free tier is plenty
generous and you and your students can get up and running in under
10 minutes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Compass
Back in the day you either interacted with MongoDB pragmatically
using a language driver or used their REPL shell. Compass is a
complete fully functional GUI. It can connect to your database, a
remote one, or an Atlas cluster. A game changer for database
management
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Charts
This is really cool. You link MongoDB charts to an Atlas cluster and
then can interactively build dashboards and visualizations. You can
then embed the visualizations into your own web projects. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Field Level Encryption
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Encrypting passwords for storage and similar practices are important
but can be aslog. MongoDB now takes care of this for you. You can, for
instance, tell your database to encrypt the password fields and your
done. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Data Lake
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This blew me away. Basically, it can take your AWS storage and let you
query it as if it were a MongoDB database. It works with a variety of
file formst - JSON, XML, CSV and more. Basically it transparently
turns cloud storage into a database. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Stitch
This allows for the building of serverless apps. Similar to Firebase
but it looks to interact with all the other MongoDB goodness I&amp;#39;ve
mentioned. .
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were a few other neat things I learned about MongoDB and related
products but those were the highlights.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, I left the conference energized.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&amp;#39;t use MongoDB check it out for yourself and your
students. In addition to being a great product, it&amp;#39;s also a great
company.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>