<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>csed on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csed/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (csed)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 09:08:57 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csed/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Math isn&#39;t always fun but you can do fun things with math</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/math-not-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 09:08:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/math-not-fun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Garth Flint recently wrote another &lt;a href=&#34;https://gflint.wordpress.com/2019/06/25/programming-and-math-danger-will-robinson/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; talking about some of the PD
going on in his neck of the woods. Garth talks about the disconnect
between the professors putting on the PD and what goes on in the K12
classrooms of the attending teachers. Here&amp;#39;s the money quote:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
“Why do all college CS profs think everyone loves math? Want to turn
kids off to programming? Throw math at them.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To a certain extend it makes sense - professors are content
specialists. Getting a doctorate and doing research are deep dives
into specific subject area specialties. What&amp;#39;s more, once you get
beyond teaching early for-major classes, you&amp;#39;re also teaching a
population that&amp;#39;s just as passionate about the subject as the
professor is. While it&amp;#39;s true that there are plenty of non-major
courses and non-majors who take higher level courses, college
educators live much more in a subject specific echo chamber than K12
educators.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the high school level, it&amp;#39;s very different. Years ago my principal
sat in on a lesson. I have no recollection of the lesson but
afterwards she commented that at one point I mentioned something that
I found cool. &amp;#34;So what&amp;#34; she said. How does that make it cool for the
kids. While it&amp;#39;s true that our passion can be infectious she was
right. It has to be cool for them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since so many CS Profs and even HS CS teachers have strong math
backgrounds and really like math, that becomes a frequent fall
back. Truth be told, although I&amp;#39;m not a math guy, I&amp;#39;ve fallen back on
that myself. I&amp;#39;ve done the quadratic formula, correctly derided in
Garth&amp;#39;s post and the traditional mathy recursion problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m guilty of this but not apologetic. It&amp;#39;s ok to do some mathy stuff
becuase there isn&amp;#39;t a single magic bullet. Some kids will indeed love
math, some games, some text processing, some art, some music and some
other. There are a lot of domains in which we can apply programming
and CS solutions and it make sense for us to use as few or many as
necessary to best reach our kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math, though, is a little different than domains like games or
music. We don&amp;#39;t need games or music to program up solutions to
problems but we sometimes do need math.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what do we do?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At least we should try to use math when there&amp;#39;s a point to it. Maybe
it won&amp;#39;t be loved but at least there&amp;#39;s a chance at it being
appreciated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at the quadratic formula:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Given a quadratic equation in the form: \(ax^2+bx+c=0\)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can find the roots using the quadratic formula: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
\begin{equation}
x = \frac{-b\pm \sqrt{b^2-4ac}}{2a}
\end{equation}
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s so cool about that? How about the discriminant? That&amp;#39;s the
\(b^2-4ac\) part. What&amp;#39;s the point?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t really appreciate either until much later when I studied
computer graphics. In computer graphics, there&amp;#39;s a technique called
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_tracing_(graphics)&#34;&gt;Ray Tracing&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s typically results in very shiny surfaces and
historically, ray traced images have included lots of spheres. When
you see an add with really smooth shiny stuff, particularly ones
with bright specular highlights, it&amp;#39;s probably ray traced. I believe the movie
&amp;#34;Cars&amp;#34; was the first movie that was entirely ray traced.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wouldn&amp;#39;t do ray tracing with a class until it had at least pre-calc
level math maturity but for an advanced group, it&amp;#39;s very
approachable. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The process involves tracing rays form the viewers eye through each
point on the screen and seeing what object it hits first. Once it
figures that out, it spawns rays from that point to each light source
and sees what light sources it hits. It also spawns rays for
reflection and refraction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s say you have a 1000x1000 screen. That would be 1,000,000 rays
but since you might actually &amp;#34;supersample&amp;#34; - that is, subdivide each
pixel on the screen into 16 subpixels and trace each of those rays and
average the result. That&amp;#39;s a lot of rays to trace and it can be crazy
slow. I wrote my first ray tracer in the mid 90s. It didn&amp;#39;t super
sample and was pretty simple.  I started a render the night I finished
it. By the next morning, it had only completed three lines. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since for each ray you have to figure out which object it hits first,
you&amp;#39;ve got to do a lot of math to figure out ray/object intersections. It
turns out that the easiet is probably the ray/sphere intersection. It
might seem that intersecting a box might be easier but intersecting a
box is actually a lot of work. You have to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that a box is really 6 sides each being on an independent plane
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Figure out which plane the ray hit first
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Figure out if that intersection point is bounded by the four sides
of that face of the box.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a sphere, you have to go through a bunch of substitutions and
simplifications but you end up with a single simple equation to solve.
A quadratic equation and for this you can use the quadratic formula. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You&amp;#39;re still left with a huge number of rays to compare
with a huge number of spheres. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is where the discriminant comes into play. The discriminant tells
you the nature of the roots of the equation. For example, if the discriminant is
negative, you have complex roots. Geometrically, if the discriminant
is negative, it means the ray you&amp;#39;re testing misses the sphere
entirely. Here are the possibilities;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Discriminant&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Means for a sphere / ray intersection&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt; 0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ray misses the sphere&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;= 0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ray is tangental to the sphere&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;gt; =&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ray intersects the sphere at two points&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since most rays will miss most spheres it means that instead of
solving a bagillion quadratic equations with the square root and the
division, you just do the discriminant and throw most of them away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, your solutions also tell you something useful:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Roots&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Means&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;double root&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ray hits sphere at one point&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;both negative&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ray is behind the viewers eye&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;both positive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ray is in line of sight - choose the smaller root for intersection point&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;one negative one positive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eye is inside the sphere&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was the first time I really &amp;#34;got&amp;#34; how useful something like both
the quadratic formula and the discriminant in particular could be. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While this isn&amp;#39;t a lesson for newbies, there are a number of areas
where we can do something neat that uses math rather than doing math
for it&amp;#39;s own sake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-07-rot13-gateway/&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about using the distance formula for recommendation
systems and an intro to decryption. Also using &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/who-played-spiderman-3/&#34;&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; for question
answering. Other approachable programming projects that can make math
more interesting would be clustering or a Bayes based classifier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we look, we can find lots of places where teaching and using math
makes sense. This way, the math and the CS both support and reinforce
each other. Much better of a way to do it than merely because I
thought it was &amp;#34;cool.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teacher PD at Grow with Google</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-at-gwg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 08:12:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-at-gwg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday we held our third monthly Professional Development session
for teachers of &amp;#34;APCS-A, Similar, and Beyond.&amp;#34; It&amp;#39;s great to see that
we&amp;#39;re starting to form a core of a community of CS teachers teaching
some of the more advanced classes as there is a core group that keeps
coming back for more. Even better is the fact that we&amp;#39;re gaining a
couple of new teachers at each session.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last time, we were at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;, a cloud provide that has been
very involved in education since their creation  and has been a
tremendous boon to my education projects over the years. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This time we were hosted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://events.withgoogle.com/grow-with-google-in-nyc/#content&#34;&gt;Grow with Google&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s new New York City
space. It&amp;#39;s a great space on the first two floors of Google&amp;#39;s main
building in Chelsea - 111 8th avenue. GWG looks like it will be a
terrific resource for New Yorkers with workshops ranging from coding,
resume writing, digital skills, and more. They also have offerings for
both kids and adults. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They were also great hosts, providing a great room for us to run our
session as well as a nice dinner to keep the teachers fueled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, we had two major themes for our PD. First the pedagogy. My
former colleage Topher started with a pair programming workshop. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/gwg-topher.jpg&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pair programming is a pretty common technique but it&amp;#39;s deceptively
difficult to do well. It&amp;#39;s not as simple as &amp;#34;work in groups of two&amp;#34;
and it can be a challenge to make sure both students are engaged and
progressing while using this practice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Topher ran the group through a pair programming exercise and led a
discussion as to some of the strategies he uses and some of the
challenges he&amp;#39;s face. I found it very helpful. Even small suggestions
like when he has each pair draw their &amp;#34;team flag&amp;#34; on a piece of paper
which they&amp;#39;ll hold up if they want to ask for help. In the discussion
after the workshop I mentioned that I&amp;#39;ve had more success with pair
programming when I relate it to a series of code review lessons I&amp;#39;ve
been doing and that if people were interested I&amp;#39;d talk about those
lessons at a future session.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then we had dinner after which I did the content piece.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/gwg-z.jpg&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We first look at a bit of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ccl.northwestern.edu/netlogo/&#34;&gt;NetLogo&lt;/a&gt; for image procesing mostly so I
could introduce the participants to NetLogo since it&amp;#39;s really an
underused, underappreciated environment. Then we talked a bit about
the APCS-A image lab. This led to the meat of the content piece. We
took a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6NcIJXTlugc&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=44&amp;amp;t=0s&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; on seam carving. When I first saw it, I was
blown away. Now it&amp;#39;s an old technique but I&amp;#39;m still blown away by how
it can be used as both motivation and a a platform to teach some
dynamic programming. We then did a brief overview behind the basic
ideas of dynamic programming and then developed the dynamic
programming algorith that&amp;#39;s used in Seam Carving. I&amp;#39;ll probably write
all of this up in more detail in a future post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall it was a great event. We have one more PD scheduled for May
and then we&amp;#39;ll start it up again in the Fall.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s great to have amazing partners like Google and Digital Ocean to
help support our CS teachers and I&amp;#39;m looking forward to work with both
of them for years to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing A Textbook</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/choosing-a-textbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 10:41:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/choosing-a-textbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now and again there are requests on the assorted CS Education forums
asking about which text book to use. These requests are usually for
APCS-A. There are usually a number of &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m very happy with …&amp;#34;
replies but I thought I&amp;#39;d take a bit of a deeper dive into what
teachers might want to consider when evaluating a textbook.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was never an issue when I started as a math teacher. The choice was
generally already made and the school had one book for each subject
level. Sometimes there were two if the school was transitioning from
one book to another.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The older books were in general more rigorous and at the same time
more terse. The newer ones were more accessible but never seemed to
give enough guidance for kids to approach the harder
problems on their own. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In general, most teachers I know used them primarily as a source for
homework problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the CS world, it seems like we have more options. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first starting teaching APCS-AB at Stuy we had to buy new books
as the enrollment had just shot up. There weren&amp;#39;t many books that
covered both the programming and the data structures but I found one
nad it was a good one:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pictures.abebooks.com/isbn/9780314933072-uk.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://pictures.abebooks.com/isbn/9780314933072-uk.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://pictures.abebooks.com/isbn/9780314933072-uk.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was both accessible and was thorough. It wasn&amp;#39;t a great source of
exercises but it was no worse than the other options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we moved to C++ it was pretty easy as the same book was still
available, albeit now in two parts:
&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_right&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/31pkP2rZj5L._BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/31pkP2rZj5L._BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/31pkP2rZj5L._BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/51BS6W1XRRL._SX394_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/51BS6W1XRRL._SX394_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/51BS6W1XRRL._SX394_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;150px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
When we went to Java we couldn&amp;#39;t find a book that covered both the
programming and the data structures but settled on this one: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ebayimg.com/images/g/N4oAAOSw4bVTmzOV/s-l1600.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://i.ebayimg.com/images/g/N4oAAOSw4bVTmzOV/s-l1600.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://i.ebayimg.com/images/g/N4oAAOSw4bVTmzOV/s-l1600.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, particularly with data structures no longer being in issue
at most high schools there are many more choices and even back then
there was more to consider than I&amp;#39;m sure I realized.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we recommend books to our colleagues we&amp;#39;re probably not being as
helpful as we can when we say &amp;#34;we like ….&amp;#34;&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s important to think about how the text book is going to be
used. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some text books weave a project, toolkit, or theme throughout
the chapters. That&amp;#39;s great if the teacher&amp;#39;s going to align the course
closely with the textbook. If you don&amp;#39;t however, it can make later
chapters harder on the students. If the text book develops, let&amp;#39;s say,
a graphics library in the early chapters and the teacher doesn&amp;#39;t do
the same, when the later chapters rely on this library students will
find themselves in a bit of trouble. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some textbooks develop these large projects or libraries but do so as
add ons to each chapter. For most teachers that&amp;#39;s probably a better
bet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does the textbook have a rich set of problems, questions, and
examples? I haven&amp;#39;t found many that are great but then it&amp;#39;s probably
not as important these days with resources like &lt;a href=&#34;https://codingbat.com/java&#34;&gt;Coding Bat&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does the textbook present material in a way similar to the teacher? If
it is, is that a good thing or not? On the one hand, it might make the
book easier for the student that&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;getting it&amp;#34; in class and then the
book and the class reinforce each other. On the other hand, if I&amp;#39;m not
connecting with a student, it&amp;#39;s probably better if the textbook takes
on a different voice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are more questions one should ask themselves when desciding on a
new textbook but I think you get the idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For my classes, I&amp;#39;ve never strictly used the textbook. It&amp;#39;s more meant
as a reference and alternate resource for the kids. For this reason, I
like a book that is more on the tutorial side. I generally don&amp;#39;t use
them for assignments but if the book has good ones, so much the
better. As we cover a unit in class, I want the book to be available
for the student who might need extra support. Nowadays, with so many
free resources out there I try to leverage them as well. For my
beginners at Hunter, I&amp;#39;ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://automatetheboringstuff.com/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and am pretty happy with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what am I missing? What else should we be considering more so than
just &amp;#34;I like the book.&amp;#34;
&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapting A Nifty Assignment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 08:20:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/adapting-a-nifty-assignment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/samples/animation/Animated_325.gif&#34; alt=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/samples/animation/Animated_325.gif&#34; title=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/samples/animation/Animated_325.gif&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Nifty Assignments&lt;/a&gt; session at SGICSE is always a popular one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;the site&lt;/a&gt; and you&amp;#39;ll find links to all the assignments presented
from 1999 to the present year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, it&amp;#39;s a great resource. On the other, the assignments
vary in nifty-ness depending on one&amp;#39;s personal taste. To me, there
seemed to be a run of nifty assignments that were really just &amp;#34;take a
generic assignment and fancy up the graphics&amp;#34; mixed in with one&amp;#39;s that
I found really cool. There&amp;#39;s also no way to really tell if an
assignment scratches your fancy without clicking through and reading
all of them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I&amp;#39;d talk about one of the assignments presented at this past
SIGCSE. I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;ll have an opportunity to use it directly but
I did find it pretty nifty. I also thought I&amp;#39;d share some tweaks I&amp;#39;d
consider if I were to use it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The assignment is Jeffrey L. Popyack&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://nifty.stanford.edu/2019/popyack-nifty-post-it/&#34;&gt;Post-It Pandemoniim&lt;/a&gt; assignment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first glance, or rather at the start of the presentation it seemed
a pretty lightweight assignment - kids make a pixelated image by
putting colored postit notes on a grid. That&amp;#39;s a simple, nice
intro to 2D arrays but not all that nifty. The nifty part came when
you drilled down into the details. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The assignment starts with a GIF image. First you process it  with a program
provided hich produces sheets describing a 3x5 section of the overall
image. These sheets are ultimately distributed to the students
perofming the activity. This still doesn&amp;#39;t sound tremendously deep but
the activity also lets you talk about file formats with color
palettes. The idea that instead of storing the rgb triple for each
pixel you store an index into a palette of 256 colors that&amp;#39;s also
embedded into the file. This is a great way to introduce indirect
lookups. Another feature Poplyack spoke about was compression. He
mentioned the project lending itself to Run Length Encoding. The idea
that if the image has a run of adjacent pixels of the same color,
let&amp;#39;s say 9 reds in a row, instead of encoding them as &amp;#34;RRRRRRRRR&amp;#34; you
would use something like &amp;#34;9R.&amp;#34; Add this all together and it&amp;#39;s pretty
nifty. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I did have a problem, though with the compression part. During the
talk, Poplyack talked about Run Length Encoding which is pretty simple
and approachable to beginners. GIF, however, as far as I know uses
Lempel-Ziv compression which is much more complex.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I were to use this assignment, I&amp;#39;d probable make a few changes. I&amp;#39;m
not sure which of the following I&amp;#39;d actually do but here&amp;#39;s what I
would think about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First I would consider using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm_format&#34;&gt;NetPBM&lt;/a&gt; formats. Some of these formats
are simple ASCII. You can see some examples on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm_format&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
page. This lets them go directly from the file to the poster. You also
have binary encoded versions of the format which adds a layer of
complexity if desired.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second thing I would consider is using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PCX&#34;&gt;PCX&lt;/a&gt; files instead of
GIFs. PCX is a pretty simple format. It uses a color palette and also
RLE compression so while it&amp;#39;s no longer as well known as GIF I think
it might present a more accessible way of getting to a format with Run
Length Encoding and a palette.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not sure of the exact direction I&amp;#39;d go in with this assignment but
these are the additional things I&amp;#39;d think about. It&amp;#39;s pretty nifty as
is but as with a lot of nifty assignments, part of the fun is
customizing it for your situation.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March PD for CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 15:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Back in December we ran our first &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/&#34;&gt;PD session for CS teachers&lt;/a&gt;. This was
to address the need for professional development for teachers who were
more experienced in terms of computer science - we aimed this at people who were ready to
teach APCS-A, similar, or beyond and also to start to build a
community for these teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had trouble setting things up for February but we&amp;#39;re good to go for
March, April and May.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just as with our first session, each session will consist of a content
piece, a pedagogy piece, and will overall be driven by the
participants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next session is set for Thursday, March 14 from 5:00 - 8:00 and
will be hosted by Digital Ocean. The sessions will earn you 3 CTLE
hours and dinner will be provided.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you or a CS teacher you know is interested in this, they can sign
up here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/forms/DCXqPtwYS47Ooo8j1&#34;&gt;https://goo.gl/forms/DCXqPtwYS47Ooo8j1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use A Real Language</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 15:08:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/use-a-real-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why can&amp;#39;t we use a real language!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This topic has been coming up a lot recently. Now I&amp;#39;m not talking
about the Drag and drop vs textual language thing. Let me be clear. To
me a Drag and Drop language can certainly be a real language and many
are. I also think they&amp;#39;re terrific when used correctly. I just think
they&amp;#39;re frequently misapplied in later grades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No, I&amp;#39;m talking about people asking things like &amp;#34;Why do we have to use
Java in our class, why can&amp;#39;t we use a real language like &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#34; Or
at Hunter, I might get &amp;#34;Why do we have to use C++, why can&amp;#39;t we use
Java.&amp;#34; Back at Stuy I&amp;#39;d get the same question about Scheme and
Netlogo. It actually doesn&amp;#39;t really matter what language you
use. Someone else, usually a non-teacher always knows better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this reminded me of when I was young. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started with BASIC and then in high school programmed Fortran IV
using punch cards on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_1130&#34;&gt;IBM 1130&lt;/a&gt;. At the time BASIC was considered a
toy language and Fortran IV not to mention punch cards were
yesterday&amp;#39;s technology. I also took APCS the first year it was offered
and that&amp;#39;s where I learned Pascal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then went to NYU - The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. There
we also used Pascal as the core language. That was the language used
in CS1, Data Structures, and Algorithms. It was also the default
language for other classes. That is, unless the class lent itself to
a specific language such as Lisp for AI you&amp;#39;d probably use
Pascal. I learned C early on in my college career and also took
classes that used Ada, and 8088 Assembly. I mostly tried to stick with
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was the hot language at the time and all the cool kids were
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
using it. Some kids continued to use Pascal but it was universally
derided. It wasn&amp;#39;t a &amp;#34;real language.&amp;#34; Nobody used it for anything
serious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Senior year it was time to look for a job. I ended up going  to
Goldman Sachs and developed for PCs running Windows 2.1 in C. They
also hired a bunch of college grads to program the Stratus systems in
PL1 and Cobol programmers for the mainframes. This was
around 1989. Goldman and most other big companies started you in a
training program. I already knew C but they ran a crash course for my
group. They did the same for the Cobol kids although most of them had
learned it in their business schools. The PL1 kids were grouped in
with the C and Cobol groups and had to figure out PL1 on their own
once they were assigned teams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My story tough, isn&amp;#39;t about Goldman. It&amp;#39;s about another big bank I
interviewed with. I won&amp;#39;t name them but it&amp;#39;s a big firm that still
exists today. I think they had at least a whole big building down on
the street back when I interviewed but I don&amp;#39;t remember. The interview
process was tough and thorough. We talked about the firm, what they
did, the platforms they developed and of course they drilled me on
what I brought to the table. The funny thing was that their entire
PC platform was built in, yep, you guessed it, Turbo Pascal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here was a really respected financial firm doing really interesting
tech and they were using that fake toy language that no kid would ever
use for real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it. All this &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s not a real language&amp;#34; stuff is
largely nonsense. If it can solve your problem it&amp;#39;s real. If it can
teach your concept it&amp;#39;s real. The rest is nonsense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a side note, my first programming gig was in the mid 1980s for a
ticket printing company - Arcus Simplex Brown. I worked on a computer
ticket printing system for them. It was in BASIC and ran on a little
PC running CP/M with a big line printer. Best I could figure they were
still using the same system in 2012.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/ticket.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, don&amp;#39;t get caught up with someone else&amp;#39;s opinion of what&amp;#39;s a real
language just make sure your students are getting what they need.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code, Data Structures, and Hidden Complexity</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 15:17:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/aoc-data-structures-hidden-complexity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since 2015, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ericwastl&#34;&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt; has gifted us each December with &lt;a href=&#34;http://adventofcode.com&#34;&gt;Advent of
Code&lt;/a&gt; - a 25 day programming competition that I very much enjoy. This
year I haven&amp;#39;t been able to get to too many of the problems. I only
completed the first two days on the day they were released, problem
three a day late and then I didn&amp;#39;t get back to the problems until
almost 12/25 - the final day of the competition. I&amp;#39;ve spent a bit of
time over the break working through the problems. I&amp;#39;m currently
through 9. I started working through the problems in Clojure - part of
my yearly attempt to dive into the language but then did a few in
Python just to speed up my progress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I did &lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018/day/9&#34;&gt;question 9&lt;/a&gt; which I found interesting as a teacher -
so much so that I think I&amp;#39;ll assign at some point in the future.
At the core of the problem you have to maintain a list of items
inserting and deleting items at assorted locations. I threw together
this solution:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;num_players &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;431&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# 9&lt;/span&gt;
last_score &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;70950&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# 255&lt;/span&gt;
players &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; range(num_players&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)]

player&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
board&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;]
next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; last_score:
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#regular insert&lt;/span&gt;
        L &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; len(board)
        index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;L
        index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;L
        board&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;insert(index,next_marble)
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
        players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; next_marble
        index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;len(board)
        players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;players[player]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;board[index]
        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; board[index]
    player&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;(player&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;num_players
    next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; next_marble &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;(max(players))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It worked and I got my first star. This unlocked part 2 which changed
the number of marbles in the game from 70950 to 70950&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;00&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. This
brings me to my first observation - hidden complexity. Seeing my input
I knew my part 2 would be crazy slow. The solution requires you insert
and delete into a list over and over again and I did it using a Python
list and a Python list is backed by an array. This means that every
insert and delete will be linear and I had a whole bunch of them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s another great simple example of hidden complexity. Students and
beginners use Python lists as if they were linked structures with
direct indexing - the best of all worlds. It&amp;#39;s great if you&amp;#39;re dealing
with small data sets but unless you&amp;#39;re careful things can get very
slow very fast. It&amp;#39;s important that students learn about this and it
appears that many don&amp;#39;t. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I knew the program would take forever to run it was my bed
time so I started it on part two and turned in for the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I woke up I had an answer to part 2, entered it and earned my
next star. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course I knew that the solution should really be written using a
doubly linked list. The funny thing is that if you&amp;#39;re comfortable with
creating dynamic data structures like linked lists, writing a solution
using a doubly linked list and running it on part 2 actually takes a fraction of
the time of writing the original solution and running it. To make
sure, I did it. I decided to code it up in Java since I might assign
something like this to my students in C++. You can check it out &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/advent2018/tree/master/java&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second take away was that it&amp;#39;s actually beneficial for students to
be able comfortable with pointers and dynamic memory and while
creating a linked list let alone a tree can be tricky at first, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/it-gets-easier-advent19/&#34;&gt;it
does get easier.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With all the debate going on over coding vs computational thinking vs
CS it&amp;#39;s things like this - thinking about things like this that marks
one of the ways a computer scientist is different from a programmer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting schools and talking tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Back in September I talked about embarking on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/&#34;&gt;Fall 2018 HS CS Tour&lt;/a&gt;.
Since then I&amp;#39;ve visited about a dozen schools. I&amp;#39;d like to thank my
friends who helped connect me to schools - particularly &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aankit&#34;&gt;Aankit Patel&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt&#34;&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though the original motivation for the visits was to get the word
out about Hunter CS and the awesome things we&amp;#39;re doing in the Hunter
CS Honors program I always tried to make my talks about something that
would be relevant for the entire audience and not just the few that
were great fits for my program. I think I&amp;#39;ve done a pretty good job at
that. All this said, doing these visits is incredibly draining. I&amp;#39;m
usually up at the crack of dawn and end up taking the subway or
sometimes subway and bus way out into the five boroughs. Actually four
this year since I wasn&amp;#39;t able to get a date to visit any Staten Island
schools. It takes a lot of time and effort and while I love
talking to students and there some ancillary things I enjoy about
getting out into the neighborhoods of the city I&amp;#39;m extremely happy
that I can now rest for a few weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reflecting on all of this I&amp;#39;m realizing how important these visits are
and not because they&amp;#39;re recruiting trips.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spoke about some of the specifics I talk about in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;
but arguably more important is that for many of them it&amp;#39;s the first
time for them to hear about the possibilities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While many students are excited about what they&amp;#39;re doing in their first
CS classes it turns out that few have any idea where it will
lead. They may have heard that computer science can lead to a high
paying job. They might know they can get a job at Google but they
don&amp;#39;t really know what that means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I saw this at Hunter when I started three years ago and now a lot of
hard work later students are much more in tune with the New York Tech
community and all that it means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students don&amp;#39;t realize that there are many programming careers beyond
Google and their are many CS careers beyond programming. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They don&amp;#39;t realize they can combine computer science with almost any
other field or interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They don&amp;#39;t know that the same algorithmic approach behind Amazon,
Netflix, and Spotify recommendations can be used by companies selling
cloths, cosmetics, or anything else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s just the tip of the iceberg. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now I&amp;#39;m not saying that teachers aren&amp;#39;t telling their students about
the possibilities but rather that sometimes it has to come from an
outsider. When I started at Stuy, before I had a reputation (good or
bad) I&amp;#39;d tell students things and they wouldn&amp;#39;t buy it. Later I&amp;#39;d have
a friend from the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; come in. Frequently they&amp;#39;d touch on
points I addressed in class and all of a sudden I was worth listening
to. Sometimes you need an outside voice to empower and authenticate the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying that I&amp;#39;m a super motivational speaker or anything like
that. I&amp;#39;m not. I&amp;#39;m an ok speaker with content worth listening to. I&amp;#39;m
just realizing more and more how important this small self imposed
corner of my job is. Not so much for Hunter but for the kids of NY. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jut this past week I&amp;#39;ve started to work to connect some of my current
students to &lt;a href=&#34;http://tealsk12.org&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; volunteers. If you read this blog you know I&amp;#39;m a
big fan of TEALS and have wanted to encourage my students to get
involved for a while. Once we get some of our Hunter CS majors into
schools around the city to help teach CS perhaps they can help spread
the message of the possibilities to even more students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development - APCS-A, similar and beyond</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A while ago I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/&#34;&gt;our plans&lt;/a&gt; at Hunter to run professional
development for CS teachers. Specifically, running once a month
sessions for teachers who teach APCS-A, similar and beyond.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea started as a joke but morphed into a legit idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was talking to some friends about CTLE hours and how ridiculous the
system is. NY State teachers need 100 hours of CTLE credit (PD hours)
every so many years. It&amp;#39;s something of a scam for a few
reasons. First, two of the biggest providers are the NYC DOE and the
UFT, the teacher&amp;#39;s union. I&amp;#39;ve been told they both charge money for
many CTLE credit bearing activities. That certainly doesn&amp;#39;t seem
kosher – your boss and your union set up a system to charge you to keep your
job. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, it turns out that Hunter is certified to issue CTLE credits so
we joked that we should get dinner and hang out once a month and call
it professional development. We were only half joking - whenever you
get a bunch of teachers in a room they talk shop and that is actually
the best PD there is. Upon talking among ourselves and also to other
teachers we realized there was a legitimate need for PD for teachers
who were beyond the basics and so we turned this silly idea into the
real deal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday we had our first session. We had about 25 attendees for
a three hour session.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#39;t tell you if it was any good - you&amp;#39;ll have to ask the
participants, I can tell you what we did and what we plan moving
forward.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started with a content piece. I ran through &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-who_won_the_election-quadratic_to_linear_time/&#34;&gt;this lesson&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/&#34;&gt;this
one&lt;/a&gt;) where the students find the mode of a list, realize it&amp;#39;s a slow
(n^2) algorithm and then refine it to a linear solution. The key idea
is to give the students an intuitive feeling for run time issues and
also to introduce them to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-17-hidden-complexity.html/&#34;&gt;hidden complexity&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After this we had dinner, provided by our friends at Google. Over
dinner the teachers talked shop. In addition to getting to know each
other, their programs, and their classes we also asked them to
consider these three items:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What are things that cause you difficulty that you&amp;#39;d like us to
cover?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What are things you wish you knew about that you&amp;#39;d like us to
cover?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What are things you&amp;#39;re comfortable with that you&amp;#39;d be willing to
share with the group?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After dinner we circled up and JonAlf presented the way he set up
student note taking in his class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/pd-apcs-a.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we discussed next steps - specifically what we came up with
for those three bullet points above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like the idea of having at least one short content piece, one short
pedagogy piece and a deeper dive at each meeting. For the first one,
JonAlf and I had to guess as to what might be useful and at the
appropriate level. We advertised for teachers who did APCS-A, similar,
or beyond but I&amp;#39;m sure we had teachers for whom the mode lesson was a
bit too advanced to do without scaffolding and also some for whom it
was way to simple. As we continue to meet, we&amp;#39;ll nail down the right
level and the right activities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The real hope is that many of the participants will become regulars
and together we&amp;#39;ll turn this into both an amazing once a month
activity and also a community of teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Right now, I&amp;#39;m looking for companies who want to feed us and possibly
provide space so if you know of any, hook me up. We&amp;#39;re also collecting
feedback and ideas from the attendees. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re targetting February for our next session followed by March,
April, May and possibly June.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime, stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Sorting</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 20:04:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-sorting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today I saw a facebook post asking for thoughts on teaching
sorting. The question was specifically not  about motivations like
having the class act out sorts or sort cards but rather about the
coding. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been meaning to write about this since last summer when I
attended Owen Astrachan&amp;#39;s talk on the same subject.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Early in my career when teaching sorting I developed the n^2 sorts as
standalone routines just as they&amp;#39;re presented in most books but as I
gained more experience as a teacher, I changed it up to build the
sorts (at least some of them) from existing concepts. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at the selection sort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can demonstrate it by arranging an already dealt hand. Find the
smallest card place it all the way at the left. The next smallest,
next to it. Repeat until done.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is actually a very easy algorithm to develop using code the kids
have already written.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By the time we do sorting, students have already written the code to
find the smallest or largest in a list time and time again. We&amp;#39;ve also
used that concept in developing other algorithms like the one I wrote
about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/2013-03-23-who_won_the_election-quadratic_to_linear_time/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Assuming we&amp;#39;ve covered the ArrayList, We can easily code
up a sorting type algorithm (excuse any little Java errors, I&amp;#39;ve been
teaching this in C++ for the past 3 years):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  ArrayList&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;Integer&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;sort&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;ArrayList&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;Integer&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
      ArrayList&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;Integer&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; result &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; ArrayList&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; min_index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; value&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 0&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;++)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          min_index &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; findMinIndex&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
          value &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;min_index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
          a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;remove&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;min_index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
          result&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;value&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; result&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This won&amp;#39;t be efficient due to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-17-hidden-complexity/&#34;&gt;hidden complexity&lt;/a&gt; but it&amp;#39;s very easy to
write and understand the algorithm
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From here it&amp;#39;s a simple matter to code this algorithm in place -
swapping the next smallest item each time. This time coded with an array::
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; min_index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; value&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 0&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;++)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      min_index &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; findMinIndex&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// find min excluding what&amp;#39;s sorted so far
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;      value &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;min_index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      swap&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;a&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;min_index&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want, you can then break out the findMinIndex routine and the
swap so that kids see all the code in one place but regardless, this
is an easy, incremental way of teaching selection sort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can do something similar with insertion sort. Start with the code
to insert an item into an already sorted list. Write that as a routine
and then put a loop around it to complete the sort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Developing routines like this incrementally has a number of
advantages. The code is simpler, it reinforces old concepts, and it
gives students additional practice in composing more complex solutions
from building blocks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can use a similar approach to coding the more advanced sorts but
I&amp;#39;ll save those ideas for a future post.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globals Breaks And Returns, oh my</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 15:48:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/globals-breaks-and-returns/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Never use global variables
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Never break out of a loop
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These are two &amp;#34;best practices&amp;#34; that are frequently touted in early CS
classes both at the high school and college level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They came up a couple of times yesterday. Once in the Facebook APCS-A
teachers group and once on &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/10/if-you-are-using-global-variables-you.html&#34;&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s blog.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alfred post was topically on global variables. Actually it was deeper than just global
variables. It&amp;#39;s also about how students progress - what they can figure
out at various stages of progress and how what seems like a good idea
early on the path to computer science doesn&amp;#39;t seem so great later on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The discussion on the APCS-A group started with a discussion of this
code and its &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; statement as opposed to having the loop&amp;#39;s exit
condition in the boolean up top:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// do stuff
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;condition&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These two &amp;#34;best practices&amp;#34; - not using globals and not breaking out of
loops are frequently taught to students at a point when reasons for
the best practice aren&amp;#39;t always clear. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Actually, these aren&amp;#39;t even universally best practices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking at the while loop, You might have event driven code with a
while loop acting as a dispatcher:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// do stuff
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;some event&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; that event&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;some other event&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; that event&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;// etc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;exit event&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nothing wrong with that structure. It&amp;#39;s clean, easy to read and easy
to reason about. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve seen loops that use extra variables and crazy boolean expressions
so as to avoid using a &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; statement so that they follow the &amp;#34;best
practice&amp;#34; but end up with much messier code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that you should always use &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt; for that matter but rather that the best practice should be to
consider if it makes the code cleaner, easier to read, and more
maintainable or not. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the global front things are also not so clear. Sure, storing
information in globals  and then using them indiscriminantly in
assorted methods or functions is both bad form and dangerous but there
are times when using globals make sense. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in &amp;#34;the day&amp;#34; I was a C programmer. I used single C source files
along with their matching .h include files to enable &lt;strong&gt;object typed&lt;/strong&gt;
programming. Each file was a singleton object. Functions in the file
were methods using some naming convention to demarcate public vs
private, and variables that were global to the file as class variables
(or instance variables but there was only ever one instance of any
given class). Technically I broke the rules but the technique was very
effective and allowed me to write large maintainable systems. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More recently I&amp;#39;ve been playing with &lt;a href=&#34;https://vuejs.org/&#34;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; for front end
development. Vue uses a central data store - Vuex to maintain
state. Basically a place for global variables to manage the state of
your application. Again, technically global but with rules and
protocols to make things work without the usual danger associated with
globals.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A great comment on the Facebook thread &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-reference&#34;&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;footnote-reference-1&#34; href=&#34;#footnote-1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; included this Hal
Ableson quote:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Programs must be written for people to read, and only incidentally for machines to execute.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and noted that this is particularly true on the AP Exam and after all,
the original question was posed on a forum about APCS-A. With this in
mind, you shouldn&amp;#39;t &lt;strong&gt;try&lt;/strong&gt; to use globals or cleverly or creatively 
use &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt; but they do have their places.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve used globals in both professional and personal work when
appropriate and I don&amp;#39;t shy away from &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt; and use
them regularly. The real &lt;strong&gt;best practice&lt;/strong&gt; is that you consider why you
are or aren&amp;#39;t using these constructs and make a choice that makes
sense for you, your group, or your team. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Footnotes
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr class=&#34;footnotes-separatator&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnote-definitions&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnote-definition&#34;&gt;
&lt;sup id=&#34;footnote-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#footnote-reference-1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnote-body&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I will identify sources when they publish content publicly on ablog or Twitter, since
the Facebook group is semi-private, I don&amp;#39;t feel it&amp;#39;s appropriate to
state the names of commenters without asking]
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the students know more than the teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 16:07:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/students-know-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ve heard it many times with computer science - &amp;#34;the kids know more
than the teacher.&amp;#34; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, the truth is that this isn&amp;#39;t so much the case. Kids
might use computers all the time but they don&amp;#39;t necessarily know
much about them or about computer science (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/keyboarding-dig-divite/&#34;&gt;link 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-15-kids-know-nuttin.html/&#34;&gt;link 2&lt;/a&gt;). Then
you have students who think they know all about CS but really
don&amp;#39;t. They might have picked up a bit of coding somewhere but more
often than not, the knowledge is pretty superficial.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, you do have some cases where the students or a
subset of them do know more than the teacher. As K12 CS Education is
fairly nascent many of our teachers are brand new to the subject
matter. You might have kids who&amp;#39;s parents have a background and teach
them, kids who&amp;#39;s previous school had a solid program or you might have
some kids that are in that minority of people who can do it all on
their own. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In some cases, this problem will work itself out over time. States are
starting to require certification to teach computer science. Some of
these states have requirements that when met will result in teachers
who have a solid background in CS. In these cases, the problem will
eventually mostly be solved. Of course this will take years if not
decades and in states with weaker requirements the issue will never
disappear.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The issue of having students knowing more than the teacher isn&amp;#39;t
always a problem. A solid teacher can make sure a kid that&amp;#39;s ahead of
the class doesn&amp;#39;t dominate and intimidate the rest of the class and as
long as the teacher adds some value to that student things can work
out. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, I was thinking earlier today that as our subject area
gains traction and starts to mature, perhaps we can learn from other
fields where students knowing more than teachers is not that uncommon.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The subjects that come to mind for me are art and music. Even though
NY has decimated it&amp;#39;s programs, there are still a few out there. When
I grew up and also through my children&amp;#39;s years in school there were
always students in all our music classes that were exceptional and well
beyond their respective teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I never gave it much thought until now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know that the disciplines are different but I wonder if there&amp;#39;s
something us CS teachers can learn from music and art teachers in
terms of dealing with this issue.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just some food for thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve written before about why &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/&#34;&gt;Hunter College CS is so important&lt;/a&gt; for
NYC and I&amp;#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors
CS program -  a program in which students receive a scholarship along
with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS
education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/&#34;&gt;made a lot of
progress&lt;/a&gt; over the past two years and each year I roll out new
special activities and events for my honors students. Still, a major
challenges is getting the word out and building our reputation. Anyone
who takes a close look at what we&amp;#39;re doing can see we&amp;#39;re growing
something special but we still have to convince students and parents
who may not even realize that Hunter offers a CS degree to come to us
instead of going to more well known albeit much more expensive programs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To that end I try to visit as many high schools as I can during the
Fall semester to speak to high school seniors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Friday at Packer Collegiate.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Great to have &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt; come by and talk to juniors and seniors in the advanced CS about the tech sector and options for study including the amazing program at Hunter &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ubHNfyt8Y9&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ubHNfyt8Y9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; saber khan (@ed_saber) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber/status/1045768969519542272?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was invited by my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber&#34;&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; who runs the weekly twitter
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first started doing school visits I had a tough time figuring
out exactly what to say - I&amp;#39;m no salesman - I&amp;#39;m not good at it and I
don&amp;#39;t like doing it. Fortunately, I didn&amp;#39;t have to be a salesman. I
decided I&amp;#39;d talk to the students about questions they should be asking
themselves as they consider where to go after graduation. I talk about
school location, community, and culture. I also talk about majors - BA
vs BS, Major vs Minor, niche majors, and possible career paths. I also
talk about tech sectors - how NY might be different from Sill icon
Valley might be different from Seattle or Boston.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also tell them the truth about the undergraduate experience - how
you can get a great CS background at all sorts of schools. How
Algorithms is Algorithms and no matter where you go you&amp;#39;ll probably
use the same text and how while I have many former students at the
Googles and Facebooks of the world that  have gone to MIT and CMU I
also have plenty who end up at those companies or similar going to
Stony, Oberlin, Tufts, and yes, Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the talk I spend a few minutes talking about Hunter and
my honors program but it&amp;#39;s only a small part of the talk. I figure in
any given class there will be a few kids who could be a fit for my
program and I want the time spent to be worthwhile for the entire
class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes guidance people sit in when I talk to the students and
almost always they tell me how valuable it was for the students to
have someone like me come in and talk frankly about the college
application and acceptance process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s going to take time to build our reputation at Hunter but I think
that going around to students and talking honestly about college and
not giving the hard sell helps build trust and our reputation and over
time, people will realize the value we&amp;#39;re bringing to the table and
come to us. It&amp;#39;s already happening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, the only other challenge is to get more high schools to bring me
in. Next week I&amp;#39;m visiting NEST+M and Brooklyn Tech and I&amp;#39;ve got a few
more on the calendar in upcoming weeks but would love to get to a
bunch more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re at a NY area High School and you think there&amp;#39;s a fit -
hit me up - I&amp;#39;d love to visit and meet and talk with your kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS vs CT vs Coding</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-ct-cc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s been a lot of buzz recently concernting Computational Thinking
(CT) vs Computer Science (CS) vs Coding / Programming on the
interwebs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the questions and concerns that I&amp;#39;ve seen recently include:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What is CT??
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will rich schools get CS and poor only CT?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will rich schools get CS and poor on coding?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first question is a big one and as a community we haven&amp;#39;t answered
it yet. I think about it as including things like algorithmic
thinking, decomposing problems, iterating, pattern recoginition and the like 
but I&amp;#39;m hardpressed to come up with a succinct formal definition. This
is somewhat related to the bigger problem of &amp;#34;what is CS?&amp;#34; A problem
the CS community is still dealing with. There seems to be an editorial
or letter in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cacm.acm.org/&#34;&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/a&gt; every few months talking
about this. &amp;#34;We&amp;#39;re an enginering discipline. No, we&amp;#39;re a science. No
we&amp;#39;re an artistic endeavor&amp;#34; and on and on. It&amp;#39;s no surprise that the
rest of the world doesn&amp;#39;t understand what we are when we haven&amp;#39;t
figured it out ourselves. It&amp;#39;s also no surprise that this problem also
extends to CT.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing seemed clear on the twitter threads and posts I read is that
people seem to believe that CT and Coding are potentially overlapping
subsets of CS but you can do CT and Coding without CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While there&amp;#39;s probably a lot to say on the CT without CS or rather CT
without programming but today let&amp;#39;s look at the programming without CS
side of things.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is probably of particular concern to me as a high school and now
college guy. There&amp;#39;s no doubt to me that there&amp;#39;s a big difference
between a kid learning coding/programming and computer science. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Coding can be a useful skill but without at least some computer
science it&amp;#39;s of limited value. Look at code schools as examples. Many
code schools work to prepare their customers for entry level tech
jobs. Usually, this includes the fundamentals of programming on top of
a typical business toolset. Examples would be a node.js backend,
Mongodb, and React.js. Another, albeit older one so probably not
taught as much now would be Ruby on Rails. Upon completing the
program, one can create a formulaic full stack applicationand knowing
that formula can make you employable in our current tech sector. The
downside though, as I&amp;#39;ve heard from countless employers, is that code
school graduates, by training, can&amp;#39;t break out of that formula. They
just don&amp;#39;t have the context, nor the problem solving ability - they
lack the CS. I&amp;#39;m sure many go on to learn the CS but that&amp;#39;s another
story. I was talking to a code school founder a few years ago about
this and asked &amp;#34;what happens when the formula chages.&amp;#34; The answer I
got was &amp;#34;that&amp;#39;s ok, we&amp;#39;ll just bring them back for a new bootcamp.&amp;#34; Of
course that will cost the kid another 10K or whatever bootcamps are
charging these days.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now of course some code schools try harder than others and some
attempt build some CS into their programs but while there are always
outliers who can learn a great deal in a short period of time, and
often on their own, real education takes time and effort and a short
term bootcamp just doesn&amp;#39;t have that time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to schools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start coding is easier to teach than CS. It can be formulaic and
there are lots of resources out there to assist teachers without a CS
background. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also easy to test and show off. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was at the NYTM once and they were celebrating a code school
project. The idea was really a good one - automatic sensing of heat in
low income apartments. I had a couple of questions about getting their
data out to the authorities but thought that if they figured that out
it could really do some good. On the other hand there was practically
no CS. As the project was described - it sets up it&amp;#39;s own mesh network
and communicates heat readings etc etc., I said to my neighbor in the
audience - sounds like an arduino with an XBee shield and yep, when
they showed the case, it was the exact form factor to hold an arduino
and xbee. That told me there was no CS. The mesh networking is
automatically done by the XBee so all they had to do was take the
sample arduino code to read the heat sensor and instead of sending it
to the serial port as the sample code does, send it to a particular
XBee node. Pretty much no CS and almost no programming. Just a great
idea and gluing some components together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve seen the same with student projects that have been highlighted at
events with funders and politicians and in the media. I won&amp;#39;t describe
them as they are student projects and wouldn&amp;#39;t do that to a student
but the projects really had no CS under the hood. Nice ideas or even
more importantly nice stories around the kid but it was glue and
simple basic programming not CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teaching real CS is harder to do, harder to assess and harder to show
off which makes teaching coding so enticing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that teaching coding without CS doesn&amp;#39;t have
value. I believe it does but it also leads to another problem – it
can be assessed improperly either with showy projects that are merely
gluing a theme on a fixed pattern or by tests that allow for
memorization and this at times has led to students being given too
much too early.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ve seen this with algebra and physics. Students end up taking these
subjects before they&amp;#39;re ready for them. They can pass the
standardized test  because they can plug numbers into formulas or can
recognize what form to use because there are a limited set of problem
patterns on the exams but they don&amp;#39;t really &amp;#34;get&amp;#34; the subject. This
leads to problems later on but of course that&amp;#39;s another teacher&amp;#39;s
problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also happens in coding classes. While it&amp;#39;s usually pretty clear
when a kid isn&amp;#39;t getting a CS concept, I&amp;#39;ve seen programming
experiences where the student at first or in the short term can appear
to pass the assessments but later on it&amp;#39;s revealed that they weren&amp;#39;t
ready and they didn&amp;#39;t really learn what they were supposed to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a problem. Just as we might have some students exposed to CT
without CS I think a major problem will be kids getting Coding without
CS. This will particularly be a danger in poorer schools and
communities but possibly across the board.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just another thing we have to really be on guard for as we try to
achieve CS for all.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>