<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hardware on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hardware/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (hardware)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 17:10:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hardware/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Pinebook Pro update</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 17:10:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since posting about my new &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook/&#34;&gt;Pinebook Pro&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;ve gotten a few questions as
it pertains to teaching CS so I thought I&amp;#39;d give a quick update.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of software here&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;ve actually gotten working: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
libreoffice (comes preinstalled)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
C/C++ toolchain (manjaro package install)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Java (manjaro package install)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs (built from scratch and manjaro install)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NetLogo (had to customize the startup script as per the NetLogo
FAQ)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Racket (had to compile from source)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also heard the VSCode works with no issues.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also manjaro which is a little different from Ubuntu which is
probably more well known. I installed a program named &lt;a href=&#34;https://computingforgeeks.com/yay-best-aur-helper-for-arch-linux-manjaro/&#34;&gt;yay&lt;/a&gt; for
package management which also gave me access to the community packages
(like extra repos for Ubuntu). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest difference I&amp;#39;ve had between Manjaro and Ubuntu is with
Ubuntu I&amp;#39;d search for packages with &lt;code&gt;apt-cache search package&lt;/code&gt; and
install with &lt;code&gt;apt-get install package&lt;/code&gt; while with yay it&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;yay -Ss
package&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;yay -S package&lt;/code&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a little more nuanced but it
isn&amp;#39;t harder, just different.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other difference is that the Pinebook is set up with Manjaro
running KDE plasma which is a different interface but all common
windowing interfaces are fairly similar.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A final point I want to mention is that the Pinebook Pro price of
$200 represents the cost of the unit. The Pine64 people don&amp;#39;t make any
money on this. It&amp;#39;s about getting the units out there and building a
community. First, this means that you won&amp;#39;t be able to go online and
order class sets of these (at least I don&amp;#39;t think you&amp;#39;d be able to do
so) and that if a device such as this were made by a tradional vendor
it would cost at least a bit more so that they could make a hopefully
fair profit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, this is a very functional Linux laptop for around $200. It
proves what you can do and After a few days use I highly recommend it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
$200
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinebook Pro - an $200 Linux Laptop</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 17:24:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing this on my new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pine64.org/pinebook-pro/&#34;&gt;Pinebook Pro&lt;/a&gt; - a $200 ARM based Linux
laptop. The Pinebook Pro comes from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pine64.org/&#34;&gt;Pine64&lt;/a&gt; project. As you could
figure out, they do the Pine64 which is similar to a Raspberry Pi and
they&amp;#39;ve got some cool projects. In addition to the Pinebook pro
they&amp;#39;ve also got the Pine Tab and Pine Phone and more. Now, you&amp;#39;re not
going to be able to go to their site and say &amp;#34;I need 30 of these for
my class&amp;#34; - at least not for the Pinebook pro but it is a pretty cool
proof of concept and hobbyist machine and it shows that we could have
affordable devices for our schools and less afluent students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got the PbP out of curiousity and also to see if I could find a low
cost solution for Hunter College students. All of my honors students
get laptops but the rest of Hunter CS is on their own so a low cost
device is pretty attractive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The specs are pretty decent - 1080P 14&amp;#34; screen, 4GB of memory, 64GB
mmc (upgradeable), USB-C, long battery life and more. They claim that
it can drive an external 4k monitor but I haven&amp;#39;t tested this yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, does it deliver?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall yes but with a few caveats. It&amp;#39;s still on the side of a
tinkerer/hobbyist device.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Out of the box it seemed DOA - it wouldn&amp;#39;t boot. I found in the forums
that there&amp;#39;s an emmc enable switch inside that sometimes ended up in
the off position. I had to take out the eight screws from the bottom,
pop the case and flip the switch. Seems like that&amp;#39;s something that
could have been caught before they closed the cases but it wasn&amp;#39;t too
big of a deal. It is, however a deal breaker for a novice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there it booted fine. Right into Manjaro Linux running
KDE. Everything seemed to work. Next I tried to boot of an SD card -
Debian this time. Worked like a charm though the distribution kept
dropping WIFI.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to Manjaro. Being a Linuxmint user and having not used Manjaro in
about two years it took a bit of time to get the lay of the land but
just about everything worked. I installed syncthing which I use
instead of dropbox, zsh, and built Emacs from source. It took forever
but worked. Well, worked with some font problems. I ended up installing
Emacs 27 from the Manjaro repositories and everything went
seemelessly. Even though I ended up not using the source built Emacs
it did show that the G++ toolchain all worked well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also tested Java and Clojure. No problems though starting Clojure
seemed to take a day and a half. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other tests included installing the Cinnamon and Mate desktop
environments. The only thing I haven&amp;#39;t been able to install
succesfully has been a VPN. On the battery front, I haven&amp;#39;t used it
long enough in a sitting to put a dent in it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, at $200, this isn&amp;#39;t going to be a speed demon. My default config
does a bunch of things so even opening a terminal with zsh has some
lag. Once loaded though things are smooth. I would have loved more
memory but 4GB seems sufficient for day to day stuff and student work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will his become my day to day laptop? I don&amp;#39;t know. I think if I can
slim down some of my config it might.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re looking for an innexpensive Linux laptop and are comfortable
tinkering and reading some forums check out the Pinebook. If it was an
option, I&amp;#39;d love to get these for my students instead of the
overpriced Dells we have to get them every year.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 17:38:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_right&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/monitors.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Got a new monitor today and wanted to share.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My old one was a 27&amp;#34; Hanns G. Actually, the old ones - my old set up
was 2 of them side by side. When I started at Hunter, I was given a
piddly small monitor so I tried to buy my own 27&amp;#34; Hanns G to bring in
but they were no longer available. The 27&amp;#34; jobs available then were
much more expensive so my work monitor situation has been sadly
lacking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The 2 27&amp;#34; setup worked pretty well but then I read &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/the-best-display-for-programming-8aad0be4227d&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post and did a
little research. It turns out that Costco has a great deal on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.costco.com/LG-43UD79-B-43%2522-Class-Ultra-HD-4K-IPS-Monitor.product.100378322.html&#34;&gt;LG
43&amp;#34; 4K&lt;/a&gt; monitor so I took the plunge. I also had to pick up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/EVGA-GeForce-Passive-Graphics-02G-P4-6332-KR/dp/B073VPKV26/ref=sr_1_3?keywords=gt+1030&amp;amp;qid=1552171987&amp;amp;s=gateway&amp;amp;sr=8-3&#34;&gt;cheap
video card&lt;/a&gt; to drive it since I was just using onboard video and my
setup is pretty old.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s HUGE. I love it but am now working to figure out how best to set
things up. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The added bonus is that I can now bring one or both of the 27&amp;#34;
monitors to work!!!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re on the  market for a new monitor I have to say that I&amp;#39;m
really happy with the LG. Just wanted to share.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chromebooks in K12</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/chromebooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/chromebooks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The discussion today over on &lt;a href=&#34;http://avc.com&#34;&gt;AVC&lt;/a&gt; was &lt;a href=&#34;http://avc.com/2016/10/chromebooks-in-k12/&#34;&gt;Chromebooks in K12&lt;/a&gt;, a title I
conveniently lifted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the comments, I was asked my thoughts on chromebooks vs Linux on
low end hardware so, here they are.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Chromebooks are cheap, near instant on, and, if you&amp;#39;re using Google
Apps for education, little to no administration necessary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a HUGE win for schools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are some issues. School WiFi, for example, is frequently
insufficient which can be a problem for a device that&amp;#39;s meant to be
connected to the cloud. People might think that schools are well
connected but I know multiple schools that keep kids off the WiFi to
keep it from being overloaded. This is a problem and I don&amp;#39;t know if
it&amp;#39;s really being addressed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also worth noting that DOE pricing is also a far cry from &amp;#34;lowest
bidder.&amp;#34; We keep seeing sub $200 chromebooks on the market but buying
through the DOE approved vendor looks to cost about $300 per unit or
more. Of course this is better than the equally inflated PC/Mac
prices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, the price and easy of deployment and administration seem to
make chromebooks the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to other issues, first, you have to buy in to the Google platform
– email, docs, classroom, etc. This isn&amp;#39;t necessarily a problem. I
personally like most of Google&amp;#39;s offerings. My big concern is giving
away student data. I have mixed feelings on the whole privacy thing
but it&amp;#39;s more clear cut when it comes to minors in public schools -
schools shouldn&amp;#39;t be sharing their data and schools shouldn&amp;#39;t be
forcing them to share their data. Google Suite for Education is FERPA
compliant but what about all the other Google services the kids might
be using? I haven&amp;#39;t looked at this carefully but we&amp;#39;ve already given
too much power to private interests over education (see the College
Board or Pearsons) so, at least to me, this is a concern.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My only other issue is a selfish one. As a CS educator, I look to
coding tools and environments. While there are online platforms like
cloud9 or &lt;a href=&#34;http://repl.it&#34;&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;, they don&amp;#39;t have the same power and flexibility of
using local installs. I&amp;#39;ve been using repl.it and it&amp;#39;s a great tool
but I think it&amp;#39;s best used as a stepping stone to a local install and
then afterwards for some of it&amp;#39;s specific value added features. I&amp;#39;m
also a big believer in teaching &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/shell/&#34;&gt;operating system as tool box&lt;/a&gt;,
something you can&amp;#39;t currently do with a chromebook.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/willykaram&#34;&gt;Willy Karam&lt;/a&gt; commented over at AVC about using cheap hardware running
Linux. This is something I&amp;#39;ve done for years and it&amp;#39;s been a
lifesaver. CSTUY&amp;#39;s entire laptop collection consists of really old
laptops running Linux.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a CS class, this works well. Even for a non CS class it can work
well. Modern Linux distributions run pretty much the same as Windows
and MacOS. Use the mouse to click on menus and icons. It doesn&amp;#39;t give
you the power of the command line but it means it&amp;#39;s a suitable
alternative for the masses that use the operating system as a program loader..
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The downside of Linux for the general population is the administration
and maintenance. At Stuy, we set up NIS and NFS. Both horrible but
probably easier and better than most alternatives. I was never able to
come up with a better way to do authentication and file sharing and
the NFS stuff would have killed our wifi (we only used it in wired
labs). Customizing software installs is also a real problem. We made
it work but it took far too much time and effort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#39;re in a situation where you can do a stock install and then
give the machine to the student for the semester, then Linux can work
really well. If you&amp;#39;re talking about shared machines with custom
installs, it&amp;#39;s harder to justify over chromebooks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A final note on chromebooks is that last year, I played with putting Linux on a
chromebook. It worked pretty well. Almost the best of both worlds. Low
end hardware with good battery life and a full operating system. This
is something I have to play with on the current generation of chromebooks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, where do I stand on this? The cloud isn&amp;#39;t there yet in terms of
teaching computer science. It&amp;#39;s fine for a gentle introduction but
eventually, you&amp;#39;ll need the power of a full blown OS and local
installs. We may very well get to where a cloud OS is just as
expressive, we&amp;#39;re just not there yet. On the other hand, for general
computing in schools, chromebooks are a big win.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It would be wonderful if schools had sufficient infrastructure,
support staff and training so that technology was just there and just
worked and we didn&amp;#39;t have to make these sort of decisions and
compromises. Somehow I don&amp;#39;t thing that will be happening any time soon.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robots platforms and practicalities</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/robot-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/robot-survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I received an email from a friend the other day asking me about a
particular robotics platform she recently saw.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve played with robotics on and off over the years ranging from
building them from (not using) scratch using Atmel chips and programming them in
assembly to using Arduino based platforms to using pre-built robot
platforms. They&amp;#39;re really cool and since they interact with the real
world you can do all sorts of interesting and motivational things with students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve done these on my own as a hobbyist and also with students either
individually or in small groups, but never as part of a class I had
been teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why not?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest reason is that the classes I&amp;#39;ve taught are already so
packed full of CS goodness that we can&amp;#39;t even get everything done
that&amp;#39;s theoretically on the syllabi.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other has to do with practical concerns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Equipment costs - Let&amp;#39;s say we can get our platform at $100 a pop. I
just can&amp;#39;t see a public school with 34 kids in a class getting one per
student or one for every two.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s the robot to student ratio and how much actual access do
the kids get? If they&amp;#39;re designing  building, do they all get to
design and build? Same question with coding and operating.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there&amp;#39;s space – if we&amp;#39;re talking about a mobile platform as
opposed to something that sits on the desk and is near stationary, we
have a problem. The classrooms I&amp;#39;ve taught in can barely hold the
students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also issues with breakage, loss, theft and long term
maintainability - will we be able to or even want to fill in with
compatible units in a few years as needed or will we have to reboot
the program from scratch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All that to deal with before we even get to the fun of teaching and learning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m really curious about the experiences of those of you who do teach
using robots and similar platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you are such a teacher, could you please fill out this form or
leave a comment for anything that the form doesn&amp;#39;t cover?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1FlppDbeiK8uPxh_RkXoCbbdE_UDY_4qXmZWbXlZ0gGg/viewform?embedded=true&#34;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1FlppDbeiK8uPxh_RkXoCbbdE_UDY_4qXmZWbXlZ0gGg/viewform?embedded=true&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;760&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;500&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34; marginheight=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34; marginwidth=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Loading…&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>