<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>guest speakers on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/guest-speakers/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (guest speakers)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 07:00:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/guest-speakers/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Proof By Authority</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/proof-by-authority/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 07:00:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/proof-by-authority/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
No,I&amp;#39;m not talking about&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argument_from_authority&#34;&gt;Argument from Authority&lt;/a&gt; - something that very
much plagues CS Education and education in general where an annointed
few who may, or may not really know what they&amp;#39;re talking about are
given creedence because they&amp;#39;ve been there the longest, work for the
companies with the biggest names, have the economic backing  or
otherwise have been given the stage. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m talking about Proof by Authority which I fondly remember from
those silly &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.hmc.edu/~fleck/proof.html&#34;&gt;Proof techniques&lt;/a&gt; lists that went around in the
day. Techniques like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Technique&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proof by Intimidation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proof by example&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The author solves for n - 2…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proof by funding&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How the Bill Gates Foundation be wrong&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and many many more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proof by authority was basically &amp;#34;I saw Dr. Gershon in the elevator
and she said….&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What made me think og this was this Tweet by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/b0rk&#34;&gt;Julia Evans&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;i&amp;#39;m not
sure if this advice is too obvious/basic but I really like to approach
confusing debugging situations by first looking at where my
understanding of the system is fuzzy, not by immediately trying to
tackle the bug&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🔎Julia Evans🔍 (@b0rk) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/b0rk/status/1143313949640810498?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June
25, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know Julia personally, but we have mutual friends and I&amp;#39;ve been following
her online for a while. She makes cool &amp;#34;zines&amp;#34; and interesting blog
posts about a variety of tech type topics leaning towards the systems
side. Her latest post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://jvns.ca/blog/2019/06/23/a-few-debugging-resources/&#34;&gt;debugging&lt;/a&gt; is well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What caught my eye was &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m not sure if this advice is too
obvious/basic…&amp;#34; It isn&amp;#39;t. As an educator I&amp;#39;ve found that to others,
what&amp;#39;s obvious to us is not always obvious or clear to others. What I
also got to thinking about was the fact that if a student follows Julia,
they&amp;#39;re, in many cases, more likely to listen to her rather than her
teacher because Julia&amp;#39;s a known and respected expert in the field and
a teacher is well, just a teacher. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This further reminded me of something that happened early on in my
career. I was a reasonably popular teacher but I didn&amp;#39;t have that much
of a reputation being fairly new. I would try to add real world  best practices to
my classes but I could tell that many of the students weren&amp;#39;t really
buying it. Mid semester, a friend came to town. He was a long time
Microsoft employee. He started right after college in the late 80&amp;#39;s
and had been there ever since. He gave a guest talk in my classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I remember Danny saying in the class was that &amp;#34;Stuy
wasn&amp;#39;t special because of the teachers, but rather because of the
students.&amp;#34; He was right, but I, um &amp;#34;Thanks, Danny, you know, I&amp;#39;m a
teacher and right here in the room :-)&amp;#34; On the other hand, in later
talks he always did say to listen to what I had to say. I guess during
the first talk he didn&amp;#39;t really know what I brought to the table as a
teahcer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other thing is that Danny talked about a number of best practices
both in his talk and during Q&amp;amp;A. In all cases, what he said mirrored
what I had been telling my students all year and none of it was
planned.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not only did the kids pay more attention to what Danny had to say than
what I had previously tried to say but from that point on, they paid
more attention to my asides on what is done in the &amp;#34;real world.&amp;#34; I had
been authenticated by a top level Microsoft engineer. Proof by
Authority.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since those early days, I&amp;#39;ve developed my own reputation. My students
graduated and went on to success both in and outside of CS. They
both provided the information I needed to know how best to prepare my
students and also verified that I was doing it. Over time I needed
outside verification less and less but was able to get and rely on
outside information more and more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I saw Julia&amp;#39;s tweet it made me think that having respected
industry people share their thoughts on what works for them in clear
concise ways is not only valuable directly but can also be of value
indirectly when used wisely by teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>