<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PD on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/pd/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (PD)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 12:29:06 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/pd/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching CS  - all the educators to all the grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-cs-in-all-the-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 12:29:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teaching-cs-in-all-the-grades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m kicking off a couple of exciting summer projects next week and
it&amp;#39;s been pointed out to me a couple of times that I&amp;#39;ll be working
with educators at every level to help them to deliver CS instruction
to students at every level. What an opportunity to be a part of and
learn from - working with every level of teacher for every level of
student. I&amp;#39;m part of the teaching teams but I think I&amp;#39;m also going to
learn a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, how is this happening? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One project I&amp;#39;m working on, entering its second year is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; on
computational thinking in the early grades. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yadavaman&#34;&gt;Aman Yadav&lt;/a&gt; and I, with the
support of the Robin Hood Foundation will be working with primary
grade teachers to develop experience that both teach computational
thinking and use CT to support the core subject areas. As we had last
time, we&amp;#39;ll have both working teachers and pre-service teachers - that
is, Hunter students close to earning their teaching degrees and
certifications. In the Fall, the pre-service teachers will student
teach under the supervision of the working teachers in our
program. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Based on what we did last year I&amp;#39;m convinced that this years cohort
will get a lot out of the experience but I&amp;#39;m also convinced that the
workshop still faces the limitations of any professional development
style training - short duration, one shot, and no long term
support. PD can be valuable but I&amp;#39;m 100% convinced it&amp;#39;s not the answer
in terms of preparing CS teachers. At the end of the workshop, our
teachers will have learned something about CT, be more comfortable
with it, and have designed some lessons that they&amp;#39;ll deliver in the
Fall. It&amp;#39;s a start but it&amp;#39;s not the end. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The game changer brings me to the other group of people
participating - four full time Hunter Faculty members. They all teach
in our School of Education. The aim is to see where we can add CT to
our pre-service classes. This moves the needle. If we do it right,
soon enough, every Hunter College primary grade teaching candidate
will be learning about Computational Thinking in their required Ed
classes. That&amp;#39;s how you do it - get it into pre-service.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that has me working with pre-service and in-service teachers as
well as full time research faculty. That&amp;#39;s a lot of levels of
educators but it&amp;#39;s not all the grades.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the other project we&amp;#39;re kicking off on Monday and one that I
plan to write a lot about over the next month and into next year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re finally kicking off our Computer Science Teacher certification
program. We&amp;#39;ve got a cohort of a little over 20 teachers that will
take part in a month long intensive followed by more coursework in
the Fall. When they&amp;#39;re done, they&amp;#39;ll be among the first certified
computer science teachers in New York State. The cohort consists
mostly of High School teachers but we&amp;#39;ve got some middle school in
there as well. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This too is a game changer. We&amp;#39;re not giving a curriculum to follow or
scripts to copy but rather we&amp;#39;re teaching serious CS and how to teach
it. Of course it doesn&amp;#39;t hurt that the cohort is comprised of strong,
experienced teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there it is - all the levels of teachers to all the levels of
students. I&amp;#39;m super excited to be part of both of these game changing
projects and can&amp;#39;t wait for Monday when we get to work.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Problems</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 08:12:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/interesting-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I organize a monthly professional development session for CS
teachers. It&amp;#39;s targeted at teachers who are beyond the beginner stage
and don&amp;#39;t want yet another hello world blinky arduino scratch
workshop. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, given the need for CS teachers we need
plenty of beginner workshops but we also need to take teachers to the
next level. I refer to my workshops as being for teachers of APCS-A,
similar, or beyond. Participants get three hours of CTLE credit and
thanks to our gracious hosts at &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; get to use a great space
and enjoy a free meal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly enjoyed last weeks workshop for two reasons. One is
that we talked about &amp;#34;interesting problems.&amp;#34; This in itself is
interesting because different teachers find different things
interesting. For me, this time around, I was thinking of problems that
could be approached by beginners but had some interesting insight that
allowed them to look at the problem differently and solve it more
efficiently. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second reason I liked this session is because I wasn&amp;#39;t the only
one presenting!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started the session talking about the Happy Ladybugs problem - a
Hackerrank problem I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then passed off to Justin who talked about finding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull&#34;&gt;convex hull&lt;/a&gt;
bounding a set of points. Justin talked about how you can relate this
abstract geometry problem to real world problems like bounding
neighborhoods as well as how this can be graphically motivated and
then moved to discussing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull_algorithms&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;. Students can pretty easily come
up with a in inefficient O(n^4) solution and then Justin talked about
incrementally guiding them through alternate solutions ending with
something that runs in O(nlgn). At the end of the day we had a problem
that could be done in a variety of ways with students at different
levels of experience. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then moved to Barry&amp;#39;s presentation of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baphl.org/20/&#34;&gt;puzzle hunt&lt;/a&gt; problem he
adapted. It involved decoding, translation, number bases and Barry
uses it as a platform to work with stacks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I finished the evening talking about three problems but we didn&amp;#39;t look
at solutions. These were teasers for next time when we also hope to do a
SIGCSE recap.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 1 - cleaning the data</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 16:18:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I run periodic professional development sessions here in New York with
my partner in crime JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver. I call them PD for &amp;#34;APCS-A,
similar or beyond&amp;#34; and they&amp;#39;re designed to fill a professional
development gap. We try to run them once a month but it&amp;#39;s a little
less frequent than that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The NYCDOE has taken on the monster task of CS for all and since
they&amp;#39;re trying to get to everyone they have to run a bazillion
sessions but all at an introductory level. Beyond that, most PD is
tied to a curriculum, program, or product. We decided to run sessions
for teachers who are ready for more both pedagogically and content
wise while not affiliating with any specific provider. We&amp;#39;re just
about the CS and the teaching of CS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday we had our first session of the year and the content topic
was text processing. Along the way, we used it as an opportunity to
highlight subgoal labeling as a teaching technique.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a lot you can do in both CS0 and CS1 with text and document
processing. By the end of yesterday&amp;#39;s session we had discussed a bunch
of possibilities based on the text processing technique known as a
&amp;#34;bag of words&amp;#34; which basically takes a text and just considers all the
words it contains. What are the words and how many times does each
word occurs. No consideration of order, grammar, or anything else. Just
words and counts. We also talked a bit about more advanced possibilities
like playing with an inverted index. I&amp;#39;ll talk about both of those in
a future post. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For today, let&amp;#39;s talk about what we have to do before we even begin -
preprocessing the data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We grabbed a bunch of texts from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gutenberg.org/&#34;&gt;Project Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically, &amp;#34;Moby
Dick&amp;#34;, a translation of my favorite play &amp;#34;Cyrano de Bergerac&amp;#34; and the
Book of Psalms from the Bible. I also made a copy of the first chapter
of &amp;#34;Moby Dick&amp;#34; so we had a shorter corpus to play with and typed up
the first scene of &amp;#34;Macbeth&amp;#34; - all thirteen lines of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s easy enough to read in the data in a language like Python:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;f &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; open(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;cyrano.txt&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
raw_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; f&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;read()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but if you&amp;#39;re using a bag of words you&amp;#39;ve got to do some cleaning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, all Project Gutenberg texts contain a whole bunch of front
and back matter with lots of words. If you don&amp;#39;t get rid of them
you&amp;#39;ll get extra words in your bag. I forgot to do this and was a bit
surprised to see phrases like &amp;#34;Pay a trademark license&amp;#34; in the Book of
Psalms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s easy enough to just cut the tops and bottoms of each file off
with an editor and that&amp;#39;s when we can read our data into our program
and the fun begins.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First we had to turn everything into lower case;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; raw_data&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;lower()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and then the big part - we want to get rid of all the punctuation. We
first tried something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;stuff_to_remove &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;.:;&amp;#39;0123456789&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_letters &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; stuff_to_remove]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join(cleaned_letters)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second line is a list comprehension. It iterates through each
letter in lower_data and copies it into the resultant list only if the
letter is not in our stuff_to_remove list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if we had &lt;code&gt;lower_data = &amp;#34;abc123def g&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt; we&amp;#39;d get a result
of &lt;code&gt;[&amp;#34;a&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;b&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;c&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;d&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;e&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;f&amp;#34;,&amp;#34; &amp;#34;,&amp;#34;g&amp;#34;]&lt;/code&gt;. We then use the join in line 3
to turn it back into a string &lt;code&gt;&amp;#34;abcdef g&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This worked pretty well but we found that there were problems. There
were characters that we didn&amp;#39;t account for like long dashes that
connected words and we didn&amp;#39;t have an easy way to put them in our
removal string.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This led to take 2. Instead of deciding what to throw away, let&amp;#39;s
decide what to keep;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;stuff_to_keep &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;abcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyz &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\t\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_letters &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; lower_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; stuff_to_remove]
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_string &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join(cleaned_letters)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This worked better (and yes, I know I could have used isalpha() but I
didn&amp;#39;t remember it at the time) but still had problems. We had words
that were formerly separated by punctuation with no spaces that were
now combined into new invalid words. We also had things like chapter
headings in our text and other stray words that we probably wanted to
get rid of.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this led to rich conversation among the teachers present and
can do the same in class. What do you clean? What do you keep? Is it
worth the effort to write all sorts of cleaning code to get rid of a
couple of stray bits of bad data or can we get the results we want by
leaving it in? There&amp;#39;s no universally right answer and that&amp;#39;s part of
the beauty of doing things like this with a class - it&amp;#39;s something
that can make them think.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we made our final cleaning decisions it&amp;#39;s a simple matter to
convert the long string of text into a list of words:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;wordlist &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; cleaned_string&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we&amp;#39;re ready to start building our bag of words but that&amp;#39;s a post
for another day.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Thinking  in Primary Grades</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 17:54:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ct-in-primary-grades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last week I spent a couple of days as part of a team running
professional development for a
group of pre and in service elementary school teachers. Two days
talking about computational thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wait a minute - elementary school teachers? I&amp;#39;m a high school guy
pretending to be a college guy. My extensive experience with
elementary school education is that I raised two kids and I don&amp;#39;t
think I messed them up too much. I don&amp;#39;t know anything about
elementary education!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How&amp;#39;d I ever get myself into this???
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
About a year ago my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt&#34;&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt; was encouraging me to apply for a grant to
explore computational thinking in elementary schools with the Robin Hood Foundation. I was
hesitant since elementary school is not my bag but since I also knew some
of the Robin Hood players I figured let&amp;#39;s see where things go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, coincidentally, I started talking to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yadavaman&#34;&gt;Aman Yadav&lt;/a&gt;. I had followed Aman
online for a number of years and was hoping to find an opportunity to
meet him somewhere down the line. Long story short, the two of us
decide to apply to for the Robin Hood Foundation grant together. I
felt much more comfortable than going solo since Aman had already done
some great CT work with Detroit teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, in spite of my insistence of not knowing primary ed,
Robin Hood decided to support our efforts. Last week, Aman and I,
joined by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/saraevogel&#34;&gt;Sarah Vogel&lt;/a&gt; who has also done some good work with CT in
primary grades and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CSEdPhil&#34;&gt;Phil Sands&lt;/a&gt; who is currently doing grad work with
Aman we ran two days of PD for 10 pre service and 10 in service
teachers. It was a mix of activities to explore concepts such as
debugging, decomposition, abstraction, and brainstorming on how the
teachers could bring these concepts to their classrooms in support of
core academic areas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Towards the end, I was sitting in on one group of teachers
energetically discussing how they could share what they learned with
their school. I then moved to another group where they were discussing
how core ideas from our exercises could be adapted to support teaching
writing. Really inspiring.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aman and I will be getting together with the pre and in service
teachers again in late August with the plan of developing concrete lessons
that both draw out CT concepts and support core subjects. I&amp;#39;m not
sure if Phil will be able to come out to join us but he&amp;#39;ll be involved
in the project for the long haul. We&amp;#39;re hoping Sara can also be as
involved moving forward but Sara&amp;#39;s very much in demand and very
busy so here&amp;#39;s hoping that her schedule permits it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the end the plan is to make everything the teachers develop
available to the greater CS Education community but we&amp;#39;re going for a
bigger win. If all of this works, the plan is to get some of these
practices into Hunter&amp;#39;s required pre-service classes. Given the number
of teachers we prepare at Hunter, that could really move the needle.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Working with elementary school teachers is new to me and I&amp;#39;m having
fun with all of this. Super appreciative to have partners like the
Robin Hood Foundation, Aman, Sara, and Phil as well as the teachers
who took time out of their summers to come down to Hunter and work on
this with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning For CSTA 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 17:26:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/planning-for-csta-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to flying out to Phoenix for CSTA-2019 Saturday
morning. The conference doesn&amp;#39;t officially start until Sunday, Monday
for me since I&amp;#39;m not doing any of the pre-conference workshops. We&amp;#39;ll
have most of Saturday as long as we&amp;#39;re up to it, Sunday, and Monday
morning. Actually, there is the GitHub reception on &lt;a href=&#34;https://csta-github-meetup.confetti.events/&#34;&gt;Sunday evening&lt;/a&gt; so
that&amp;#39;s kind of official conference stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As to the conference, I&amp;#39;m super looking forward to it. To me CSTA is
 a people conference. SIGCSE by contrast is more of a sessions
conference. SIGCSE is bigger and less intimate. I have a great time
there catching up with friends from across the country and when my asocial
self manages, making new ones but for me it&amp;#39;s more content/session
driven. There are always a bunch of sessions where I say to myself &amp;#34;I
really should go to that.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CSTA is more intimate so it seems easier to meet and talk to new
people, even for asocial me. On the other hand, I find fewer &amp;#34;must
see&amp;#34; sessions. This makes sense though. I no longer
teach K12 and I had already designed and taught complete course
sequences going from beginner through college level before the first
CSTA conference.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. There are lots of great sessions. It&amp;#39;s more that
many of the sessions I&amp;#39;m interested in are more &amp;#34;that looks cool&amp;#34; or
&amp;#34;interesting&amp;#34; rather than, &amp;#34;I really need to see that for what I&amp;#39;m
doing or where I&amp;#39;m at in my career.&amp;#34;  Maybe it&amp;#39;s just that it&amp;#39;s really
hard for the sessions to match the value added from CSTA&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;hallway
track&amp;#34; which I think is through the roof.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are the sessions I&amp;#39;m zeroing in on:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On Monday, the &amp;#34;Creativity in the K-12 Computing Classroom&amp;#34; BOF looks
interesting so I&amp;#39;ll probably try to hit it. On Saturday, I&amp;#39;m curious
about the &amp;#34;Advanced CS Concepts in High School: One Tool to Rule Them
All&amp;#34; session. Based on the description, I&amp;#39;m curious how much is about
advanced concepts and how much about tooling and resources that let
you get to interesting data and applications. The &amp;#34;How to teach AI
across K-12&amp;#34; session could also be interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JonAlf and I will be doing our session on using GitHub in the next
block so I pretty much have to be there :-).  In the afternoon, I&amp;#39;m
looking at the &amp;#34;You can teach Machine Learning to HS students&amp;#34; mostly
because I&amp;#39;m curious as to how the presenter&amp;#39;s thoughts on the subject
can add to what I&amp;#39;ve done in my classes. Actually, that&amp;#39;s also why I&amp;#39;m
interested in the earlier AI session. I&amp;#39;m also intrigued by Ed Campos&amp;#39;
Bootstrap Data talk but I won&amp;#39;t directly be going down that road in
any classes soon so have to prioritize. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the last block, I&amp;#39;m intrigued by the Embroidery talk but Nifty
Assignments will probably win out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t looked over Wednesday&amp;#39;s schedule yet - I&amp;#39;ll leave that for
Tuesday evening. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;ll be going to most of these sessions, I&amp;#39;ll probably
spend a good amount of time at the GitHub booth hopefully talking shop
with my fellow educators. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides, when I&amp;#39;m at the GitHub booth I also get to hang out with
Devorah (my wife). Did I mention, she&amp;#39;s doing a very cool
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blanketstatementproject.com/&#34;&gt;knitting/crocheting for charity&lt;/a&gt; project that you all should check out?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope to see all my old friends and meet many new ones in a few
days!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog For Self Professional Devleopment</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blog-for-pd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 07:12:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/blog-for-pd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Lat day of the 2019 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncwit.org/summit/2019-ncwit-summit-women-and-it&#34;&gt;NCWIT Summmit&lt;/a&gt;. Got up crazy early, got back from
my run and saw this when I checked Twitter:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;A1: CSTA,
Twitter chats like this one, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@guzdial&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alfredtwo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@alfredtwo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s
blogs among others. In all cases because those places start from
assuming I&amp;#39;m a CS teacher, rather than starting from assuming
I&amp;#39;m a teacher who is better at teaching something else. &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/csk8?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#csk8&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://t.co/6DO77fzq0j&#34;&gt;https://t.co/6DO77fzq0j&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash;
Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1128829652145979392?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May
16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async
src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t usually participate in Twitter chats. The format doesn&amp;#39;t
really work for me. I do frequently lurk though and while I didn&amp;#39;t see
this tweet until the morning after, another &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Todd_Lash/status/1128816582048673793&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; by my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Todd_Lash&#34;&gt;Todd Lash&lt;/a&gt; caught
my eye and I&amp;#39;ll probably comment on that at some point in the near
future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On Sarah&amp;#39;s tweet I&amp;#39;ll say that CS teachers should certainly frequent
Alfred and Mark&amp;#39;s blogs. I subscribe to and enjoy both. I&amp;#39;ll add
something that I&amp;#39;ve said before and that is if you&amp;#39;re a CS teacher you
should also blog.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get it - it takes time, it&amp;#39;s hard to put yourself out there and if you&amp;#39;re a
relatively young teacher you might feel like you don&amp;#39;t have much to
say but I say so what.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been blogging on and off for nine years now. I have no reason to
believe I have anything more than a small readership but I do
periodically get surprised at a conference with a &amp;#34;hey, I love your
blog.&amp;#34; Comments are few and far between and from &amp;#34;the usual
suspects&amp;#34; but as I sad above, so what.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pick a lesson you just did and describe it. That&amp;#39;s all it takes. Try
something different a week later? Write it up. Rinse and repeat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why have I found writing a blog to be good self-PD?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Writing the experience or the lesson makes me think through it
again. What worked, what didn&amp;#39;t.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I do a similar lesson in the future, I can look back on what I
did. It helps in iterating towards becoming a better teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get to see how I&amp;#39;ve evolved as a teacher over time. You don&amp;#39;t get
this immediately but blog for a few years and then reread some early
posts. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could get some comments. I don&amp;#39;t get a lot but the ones people
have left have proven useful to me. Some of the ones from people who
disagree have been the most useful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On top of this, some other new teacher might discover something you
wrote up and find inspiration from it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, jump in and try it. Blogging for self-PD. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD in NYC</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 19:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pd-in-nyc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent this past Saturday morning up at the Microsoft building in
Times Square. What was I doing there? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aankit?lang=en&#34;&gt;Aankit Patel&lt;/a&gt; invited me to check
out the professional development that he and his team organized for
the teachers involved in the assorted CSforAllNYC programs that his
office runs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of great things going on. I was only able to stay for a couple of
hours but I spent some time in two rooms run by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tealsk12.org/&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, a room of &lt;a href=&#34;https://bjc.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;BJC&lt;/a&gt;
teachers, a group working with &lt;a href=&#34;https://p5js.org&#34;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;, one doing physical computing and
a bunch more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While there was good content all around I was really impressed with
the sense of community in many of the rooms. One of the hardest parts
of being a computer science teacher in K12 is that you&amp;#39;re frequently
the only CS teacher in your school. That can be an awfully lonely
existence. It&amp;#39;s hard to be the only teacher. No one to bounce lesson
ideas off of or to debrief with and if you leave your school they&amp;#39;re
left in the lurch. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s simply amazing that all these NYC teachers have opportunities
like this past weekends PD and the communty it provides. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, teachers who are not part of city programs like
SEP or TEALS don&amp;#39;t have these opportunities and at Hunter we&amp;#39;re trying
to do our piece to help solve that problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few months ago I wrote about our plans to roll out once a month
professional development sessions for CTLE hours specifically aimed at
teachers who are ready for the next step. Those who are already
comfortable with the first courses and student experiences. I&amp;#39;m
describing the sessions as being for high school teachers teaching
APCS-A, similar or beyond.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Were hosting our first session on December 13th. There will be a
couple of presentations or activities to get us started but the bulk
of the time will be about planning the rest of the sessions which will
run until the end of the school year and the hope is that we will
cover both content beyond the basics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re a public school CS teacher in NYC (and need CTLE hours)
and you&amp;#39;re ready for something more advanced than the usual PD
opportunities, why don&amp;#39;t you join us. Just sign up &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/forms/FJDyCx7qFec1yPjr1&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Space is
limited so if we fill, we&amp;#39;ll add you to the waitlist and we&amp;#39;ll work on
trying to find a bigger space to acomodate more teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to getting this thing started!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development beyond Scratch</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today was Election Day. One of the few days each year when students
stay home and teachers spend all day attending what is generously
known as professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Years ago I was in a room with a few colleagues when my friend Dave -
one of the best math teachers I know said &amp;#34;you know, every time we
have a PD day in NJ and my wife and I have to scramble to take care of
the kids I get a little annoyed but then think I shouldn&amp;#39;t get annoyed
since they&amp;#39;re spending the day doing all sorts of valuable PD.&amp;#34; He
then said &amp;#34;but then I realize that their PD is probably about as
useful as our PD and I get really angry.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There you have it. This is not to say that there is no good PD but it
seems that the professional development opportunities provided by our
schools have over the years ranged from useless to insulting with
maybe a small bright spot here and there. Historically it&amp;#39;s been worse
for CS teachers because we get lumped in with math teachers and have
to spend the day learning about tools and techniques we&amp;#39;ll never use
or discussing curricula we never teach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, when I spoke to JonAlf about rescuing the Stuy teachers for the
day and hosting them at Hunter, he and the other CS teachers were
pretty excited. It wasn&amp;#39;t as though I had the magic PD answer but I
was going to provide a space and we&amp;#39;d figure out together what would
be productive and valuable for them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, I&amp;#39;ve been spending a good amount of time these past
few weeks visiting high schools to talk about Hunter CS and when I was
at Bronx Science the topic of Election Day PD came up and I thought
that it would be nice to get the Bronx Science and Stuy teachers
together. After thinking about it more, I recalled that there were few
good PD opportunities for CS teachers who taught advanced classes as
opposed to all the CS PD floating around these days at more of a
beginner level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought that we could change this. In the end, I hosted PD today and
had teachers from Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, Brooklyn Tech, and the
Manhattan Hunter Science High School in attendance. I invited teachers
from a few more schools but in the end we had those four schools and
seventeen teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The original agenda was:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
09:00 - 10:00 : Each school describes it&amp;#39;s program and courses
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
10:00 - 11:00 : An intro to Git and GitHub for the classroom
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
10:00 - 11:45 : Sharing neat lessons
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
11:45 - 12:00 : Presentation by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chicktech.org&#34;&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
12:00 - 01:00 : Lunch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
01:00 - End   : Small group lesson and curriculum work
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Oh boy did I mess up on the timing. The description and
discussion of school programs took all morning. It was interesting to
hear how each school&amp;#39;s program evolved and how they fit into the
school&amp;#39;s culture. Brooklyn Tech, for instance is a school where
students declare majors. This has a big impact on what classes kids
have to take and are able to take. This is very different from Stuy or
Science where kids programs are more open ended or MHSHS which is a
much smaller school and has restrictions related to size. It was also
interesting to note Brooklyn Tech&amp;#39;s decision to have every student
take APCS-P. Interesting because Brooklyn Tech is one of the country&amp;#39;s
largest high schools and most of them should have done well on the
exam. That gave NYC around 1,400 passing AP scores in one shot. On
the other hand none of the other schools present today offered APCS-P
but did have their own intro CS class that students took prior to
APCS-A.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We finished the morning with a visit by Heather from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://chicktech.org&#34;&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;. ChickTech is a non-profit dedicated to retaining women in
Tech. It works with both girls in K12 and also those in industry. My
hope was to get a conversation started and see if there were some
potential avenues of partnership between the organization and the
schools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, the group decided that we should do the Git/GitHub
workshop and JonAlf obliged.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the day was a success.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My hope is that today&amp;#39;s attendees can form a core group of CS teachers
who teach more advanced courses and we can form something of a support
group for each other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I plan to try to facilitate future meetings and hopefully we&amp;#39;ll be
able to attract more teachers to our group.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all I&amp;#39;m very happy with how the day went.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Awesome Cs Revisited</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Saw this tweet the other day so I though I would try to plug the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education&#34;&gt;Awesome CS Education&lt;/a&gt; list I started on GitHub:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/csteachers?src=hash&#34;&gt;#csteachers&lt;/a&gt;...didn&amp;#39;t I see a list of CS teacher blogs here recently?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Pam Whitlock (@PamWhitlock1) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PamWhitlock1/status/910662628757864448&#34;&gt;September 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To answer the tweet, the closet thing I know to a list is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alfredtwo&#34;&gt;Alfred
Thompson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s blog roll which is actually a post he wrote on his blog
in 2012. Unfortunately his list can be hard to find and is somewhat
out of date.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea of an &amp;#34;awesome&amp;#34; list is publicly hosting a simple site that
is community driven and anyone can suggest additions and edits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I put up a starter &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and a few people have contributed but I&amp;#39;d love
to get more people involved. Awesome lists have a number of advantages
over other repositories.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unlike blog posts, the site is easy to find.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unlike private mailing lists or Facebook, anyone can see the content.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyone can suggest additions (although you need to create a Github
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
account).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyone can download or fork the site.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s essentially plain text and is easy to edit (just read the
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org&#34;&gt;contribution guide&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there you have it. If you have a blog or resource to share please
submit a pull request. Over time this could be a terrific single
starting point for educators to get to a wealth of resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>