<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>curriculum on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/curriculum/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (curriculum)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 07:08:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/curriculum/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A new book on teaching CS in K12 - and I wrote a chapter!!</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/in-a-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 07:08:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/in-a-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was involved in a really exciting project a few months ago and now
that it&amp;#39;s available, it&amp;#39;s time to tell everyone about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a new book on teaching CS in K12 - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shuchigrover.com/atozk12cs/&#34;&gt;Computer Science in K12&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got an email a few months ago from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/shuchig&#34;&gt;Shuchi Grover&lt;/a&gt;. Okay, actually a
DM over twitter. I hadn&amp;#39;t officially met Shuchi although I&amp;#39;m pretty
sure we&amp;#39;ve been at the same table or group in a conference or two but
I did know her from reputation. Shuchi was putting together a book on
teaching CS in K12 and asked if I was interested in contributing a
chapter. I was flattered and honored and since I&amp;#39;ve never written a
chapter in a book I agreed. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The book&amp;#39;s made up of 26 chapters with a who&amp;#39;s who of authors
including teachers, professors, researchers, and other CS Ed adjacent
professionals. Check out the full &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shuchigrover.com/atozk12cs/authors/&#34;&gt;cast of characters&lt;/a&gt;. It was cool to
see many friends involved in the project. It should be a welcome
addition since I don&amp;#39;t think there&amp;#39;s anything like in currently out. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t read the full book - I&amp;#39;m anxiously awaiting my copy to
arrive but with chapter titles ranging from concepts like &amp;#34;Data Structures&amp;#34; and
&amp;#34;Repetition and Recursion&amp;#34; to techniques like &amp;#34;Questions and Inquiry&amp;#34;
and &amp;#34;Guided Exploration Through Unplugged Activities&amp;#34; it should be a
really valuable resource to teachers rather than just a book to use in
a class and keep on the shelf.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I worked on the chapter on functions. Once again I was paired with my
long time partner in crime JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver. Jens Monig, whom I
hadn&amp;#39;t known prior also worked on the chapter contributing the drag
and drop material - something that neither JonAlf nor I felt
particularly comfortable with doing ourselves.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One weird thing, though it makes sense, was that I never interacted
with most of the other authors - just my chapter co-authors and
Shuchi. Nothing wrong with it but given the number of friends working
on the book and a chance to meet new friends it would have been great
to have something like a meetup at SIGCSE had it happened. On the
other hand, working with Shuchi was terrific. This not only gave me a
chance to contribute to a book but it also got us together and now I
look forward to future collaborations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other big take away for me was that writing the chapter was
fun. I&amp;#39;ve been playing with the idea of writing a book on teaching CS
but wasn&amp;#39;t sure I&amp;#39;d enjoy the process. Now I think I might and I might
get started in August when I think I&amp;#39;ll finally have some project
time. What do all of you think? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For now, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shuchigrover.com/atozk12cs/&#34;&gt;Computer Science in K-12&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just released on Amazon in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Computer-Science-K-12-Z-Programming/dp/1734662700/&#34;&gt;Color&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1734662719/&#34;&gt;Black and White&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When does a new course really get developed</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/when-does-a-new-course-get-developed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 08:49:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/when-does-a-new-course-get-developed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Following up on my last post I thought I&amp;#39;d talk a bit more about
course development. According to most powers that be it&amp;#39;s all done
ahead of time. Organizations and companies with curricula to sell
package it all up ahead of time lesson by lesson unit by unit. When
I create a new course at Hunter, they demand a sample syllabus during
the approval process with a week by week outline, assignments reading
and more. When I created CAPE for Google back in 2010 even though the
programs man advocate knew the real deal he and I spoke many times
about needing something on paper to satisfy the higher ups. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me most of this is nonsense. When I create a new course I have an
idea and a direction but little else. Of course there&amp;#39;s much work to
be done between idea and implementation but for me  a detailed
curriculum that early is mostly a waste of time. Why? Because it all
changes once you get in the classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll do the bare minimum to get by the gatkeepers. If they want a week
to week, I give them a week to week but I won&amp;#39;t stress over it. I
then get to work on what I feel I need prior to running a course. A
framework and the first few lessons in detail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Developing the framework means:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
understanding enough of the content to teach the course. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
deciding on how you will teach or run the course
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
developing rough outlines for units, possible assignments etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
finding and understanding resources like possible texts and tools
and also things like data sources mentioned in my previous post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And of course there&amp;#39;s more. I&amp;#39;ll also work out the first unit in day
by day detail. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another important aspect is that this framework design is where you
put in your safety nets. What&amp;#39;s the backup plan if unit 2 takes too
long or students just aren&amp;#39;t getting unit 3. Another important aspect
is to prepare too much material. In my experience it usually takes
longer to teach something than you originally plan but I still think
it&amp;#39;s better to plan too much rather than too little.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why do I only plan out the first unit in details? Because i know
things will change once the rubber hits the road. Even if it doesn&amp;#39;t
change, developing specific lessons without regard to your current
students seems rather odd. It reminds me of how &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bill-irwin.com/&#34;&gt;Bill Irwin&lt;/a&gt; learned his
role in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eight_Men_Out&#34;&gt;Eight Men Out&lt;/a&gt;. Irwin&amp;#39;s amazing but apparently never played
baseball. He played Eddie Collins, the White Sox second
baseman. Having not played himself, his action scenes were
choreographed like a dance. The director would yell action and he&amp;#39;d do
his dance. If the ball happened to go where it was supposed to you
ended up with a bang bang play. If not, cut, retake. It worked for the
movie but it&amp;#39;s not a great idea for a teacher. How can you plan day 5
of a class when the first four days and all the richness of the live
classes and time between hasn&amp;#39;t occurred. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course this means a lot of work under the gun but no one ever said
that developing a new course was easy. It&amp;#39;s reassuring that I&amp;#39;m not
the only one who does the real class development in real time:
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-conversation=&#34;none&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Building the course as the semester goes, but the barebones syllabus is here. Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/guzdial?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@guzdial&lt;/a&gt;, we are using GP as the main language. Reading things like Pattern on the Stone, chapters from Constructionism book by Harel &amp;amp; Papert.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/CNgEQfcO1Z&#34;&gt;https://t.co/CNgEQfcO1Z&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Aman Yadav (@yadavaman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yadavaman/status/1082280379153829888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;January 7, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally having survived the first run through it&amp;#39;s time to &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.c2.com/?PlanToThrowOneAway&#34;&gt;throw it
away&lt;/a&gt;. Not really but it&amp;#39;s time to take lessons learned and work them
into the class. From there, it&amp;#39;s incremental improvements.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it, a summary of my approach to course creation.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Owning The Curriculum</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/owning-the-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 19:41:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/owning-the-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent a couple of days last week hunkered down working designing a
CS Ethics course and of course it got me thinking about designing
courses in general. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the topics I&amp;#39;ve ranted on is my disdain for canned
curricula. I&amp;#39;ve never been a fan. This isn&amp;#39;t to say I don&amp;#39;t want to
leverage other people&amp;#39;s work. I&amp;#39;ll take sample curricula, lessons, and
all the resources I can get my hands on but I&amp;#39;d never just deliver
them as is. Even back when I started as a math teacher and I had the
NYCDOE lesson plan books to use as samples, I&amp;#39;d use those lessons as
sources to develop my own.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded why I do this as I was developing my ethics course. I
want the course to have a significant amount of programming and for
some of the projects US census data and the NYC data mine look to be
good sources of data. I was led to these sources from some project
ideas I found online but those projects provided the data pre
processed. Had I been using these sources as a canned curriculum
things would be fine until something changed. Either the resource went
away or the direction of the class required something different. In
either event, had I been happy to merely use someone elses canned
materials I wouldn&amp;#39;t be prepared.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that you&amp;#39;ve got to do some digging before you can
effectively use a resource like the US census data. Maybe you can use
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://factfinder.census.gov/faces/nav/jsf/pages/index.xhtml%5D&#34;&gt;American Fact Finder&lt;/a&gt;. With it you can download a refined data set
as a CSV but you&amp;#39;ll still have to figure out how to use the tool and
which data sets you need. Another approach is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/acs/data/data-via-ftp.html&#34;&gt;download the data via
FTP&lt;/a&gt; but then you have to figure out how the files are arranged. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that you can&amp;#39;t just go to census.gov and
trivially get what you need and you certainly can&amp;#39;t just send students
there and say &amp;#34;good luck.&amp;#34; I spent more hours that I&amp;#39;d care to admit
last week figuring out the ins and outs of a variety of data sources
and I&amp;#39;ve got many more hours ahead. It&amp;#39;s taking a lot of time but at
the end of the day, I&amp;#39;ll own the knowledge. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day the first time you offer a course most of your
pre planning is going to go out the window. You need a framework, a
direction, and a start but first time through you don&amp;#39;t know how or
where things will really go. If you&amp;#39;re using someone else material,
good luck when things take an unexpected turn. If you own the course,
you&amp;#39;ll be prepared.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>