<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>outreach on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/outreach/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (outreach)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:25:17 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/outreach/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>School Visit Update 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/school-visit-update-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 12:25:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/school-visit-update-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been spending a lot of time at area high schools this fall. Today
I was at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franklin_Delano_Roosevelt_High_School_(New_York_City)&#34;&gt;FDR High School&lt;/a&gt; in Broooklyn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg/330px-FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg/330px-FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg/330px-FDR_HS_20th_Av_jeh.jpg&#34; /&gt;&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;500px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I only learned about FDR HS a little over a year ago when I met their
CS teacher &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jhans404&#34;&gt;Josh Hans&lt;/a&gt; at a NYC PD event. I visit last fall and then
again today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whenever I visit a school it&amp;#39;s a different experience. Sometimes I
speak to the CS classes, sometimes at an event like a CS Week
hackathon, once I even got to address an entire senior class in an
auditorium. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really loved how Josh and FDR set things up for me today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before I get to the arrangement, let&amp;#39;s talk about the talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I meet with a room of seniors, even a room full of CS students, I
know that only a few students are going to end up with me at
Hunter. A room of 30 seniors should probably end up in something like
25 different colleges. I also know that even in a CS class many of
the students will end up pursuing other majors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s right for me to take a full class period and
talk just about Hunter and my Daedalus program so instead I start by
talking about college choices. I try to share things that I&amp;#39;ve learned
over my career as a student, teacher, parent, and now someone reading
applications with my audiuence. Things I&amp;#39;ve learned from both my
experiences and through my relationships with former students. At the
end we talk about Hunter, Hunter CS and the Daedalus program.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been told that the approach has been really valuable to the
majority of students I&amp;#39;ve delivered it to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were a few things that Josh set up today that made it a lot of
fun. First, we were in the auditorium. I had Josh&amp;#39;s APCS-A class but
he also invited a couple of others. I also had APCS-P students and
also a class of Calculus students. This was a big deal. Just like
everyone, I&amp;#39;m working hard to build a program with a diverse
population and sometimes outreach is difficult. Specifically, if a
school only allows me to speak with their APCS-A students, I
frequently end up with a pre-culled group. If a school, for example,
has a very low percentage of women in their APCS-A class and that&amp;#39;s
where I&amp;#39;m speaking, I&amp;#39;m not going to be able to convince many women to
look into what we&amp;#39;re offering. By having the calc sutdents in the
audience I had a more diverse audience and also almost certainly had
the chance to expose some students to CS in a new and different
way. Now, don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. Given the nature of my program, I really
love talking to APCS-A students and going with probability, they&amp;#39;re
the most likely the ones to want my program but I love casting the
wider net.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other think Josh did was he gave me two periods. My talk usually
takes most of a period with little time for discussion. It should take
less but I tend to go into yammer mode and start telling
stories. Sorry - it&amp;#39;s just what I do. With two periods we had plenty
of time for discussion afterwards. What&amp;#39;s more, after most of the
students left, I was left with about 6 students who wanted to continue
to talk. I really enjoyed that. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once I was done I did what I usually do - went to the local bakery to
bring home some baked goods. I stopped at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/18th+Avenue+Bakery/@40.6212881,-73.9847415,17z/data=!4m8!1m2!2m1!1sbakery!3m4!1s0x0:0xd4dca91422790dec!8m2!3d40.6217849!4d-73.9877902&#34;&gt;18th street Bakery&lt;/a&gt;. An
Italian place and got an assortment. Also had a great chat with the
lady at the counter. It reminded me of when I&amp;#39;d go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yelp.com/biz/moishes-kosher-bakery-new-york&#34;&gt;Moishes Bakery&lt;/a&gt;
before they closed albeit Italian rather than Jewish. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I pointed to a pile of cookes and asked &amp;#34;what are these?&amp;#34; and she
merely said &amp;#34;No!!!!!&amp;#34; We joked back and forth and she explained that
they were on the older side and didn&amp;#39;t feel right selling them and was
going to throw the rest of the batch out. They&amp;#39;d bake new ones for
tomorrow. I was disappointed not to try a new cookie but glad that I
wasn&amp;#39;t sold stale goods. It was like at Moishes when I once asked
about the Babka and was told &amp;#34;that was made  on Wednesday, you don&amp;#39;t
want it. This is what&amp;#39;s fresh. New Babka tomorrow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, then, on the way home, thinking about Moishes and realizing that
there were  also Jewish bakeries in the neighborhood I decided to see
if I could find &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kichel&#34;&gt;Kichel&lt;/a&gt; - one of Devorah&amp;#39;s favorite cookies. I
sometimes make them but haven&amp;#39;t in a while. I found some at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Korn&amp;#39;s+Bakery/@40.630628,-73.9799457,17z/data=!4m9!1m3!2m2!1sbakery!6e5!3m4!1s0x0:0xf6f303e4b6cd6dfe!8m2!3d40.6308331!4d-73.9764149&#34;&gt;Korn&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt;
Bakery and then it was back into Manhattan.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, overall a succesful day. I got to talk to a bunch of great High
School cookies and got tasty neighborhood baked goods. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve hit a bunch of schools already this fall as I work to spread the
gospel about CS and about Hunter&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.huntercs.org&#34;&gt;Daedalus&lt;/a&gt; program and am still
looking to get more on the schedule so if you know a school that&amp;#39;s a
good fit a visit, hit me up.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>