<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>java on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/java/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (java)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/java/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Java IDES for teaching teachers.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 13:29:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-ides/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Since Hunter uses C++ as it&amp;#39;s core language, I haven&amp;#39;t used Java much
in the past three years. That&amp;#39;s going to change pretty soon. Once we
start offering our CS teacher Certificate and Masters programs I&amp;#39;ll
once again start teaching with Java as that&amp;#39;s one of the langauges
that we want to prepare our teachers with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That means deciding on a set of tools and so I&amp;#39;ve been spending time
evaluating Java programming environments with an eye on the
beginner since not only do the teachers I work with have to be
comfortable with the tool but more importantly they will have to be
able to support the tool for all of their students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One tool we&amp;#39;re likely to use is &lt;a href=&#34;https://repl.it/&#34;&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;#39;s an online environment
for Java and a bunch of other languages. There&amp;#39;s a lot to like about
it and teachers might go with it or a similar cloud based option in
their classes but it&amp;#39;s important that we also prepare teachers to
build programs locally.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, here&amp;#39;s my criteria and here&amp;#39;s what I found.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The tool has to install easily on all platforms
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started with my desktop Linux machine. I&amp;#39;m running LinuxMint which
is pretty mainstream and I installed the Java tools using Mint&amp;#39;s
package manager. The packages are openjdk-11 and it looks like running
Java 10. If the IDE or editor I installed  didn&amp;#39;t work off the bat it
was no good. If it installed and I liked it I&amp;#39;ll pass it off to
friends who use Windows and Macs to see if the install there is
equally seamless.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
The tool has to be easy to run 
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After install you have to be able to run it easily. No fancy &lt;code&gt;java
-jar blah blah blah&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not looking for a professional tool
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Professional tools can be too compex and do too much for students. I
was looking for the sweet spot of giving a nice amount of support but
not giving away the store.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are the tools I looked at (and you can debate if something
belongs in the other category in some cases):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Editors
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Gedit
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Vim
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sublime Text
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Atom
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jedit
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
IDES
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Eclipse
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DrJava
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Geany
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
BlueJ
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
IntelliJ
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
VSCode
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JGrasp
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Editor vs IDE
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The line between editor and IDE is a blurry one. I tend to think of an
editor as multi-purpose and multi-language where an also useful for
non programming text realted tasks whereas an IDE comes with more
programming bells and whistles. The truth is, though. that some IDES
can do well with non programming tasks and many editors are pretty
close to IDEs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, for a teacher, there&amp;#39;s something to be said for keeping
it &amp;#34;close to the metal&amp;#34; and have them use an editor to edit source
code and compile from the command line. This doesn&amp;#39;t mean they
shouldn&amp;#39;t also see IDEs and perhaps use them with their students but
a teacher should know a little more about what&amp;#39;s going on than just
load a program, write some code, and click run. If a teacher is that
limited you end up in situations similar to that common comment from
people who finish a beginner course on Codecademy - &amp;#34;I finished the
course and I can program in their environment but I don&amp;#39;t know how to
actually make something anywhere else.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
The Editors
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here the idea would be start as I mentioned above. Edit files adn then
compile on the command line. Eventually, though, many of these tools
can be used as IDEs
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
Emacs
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/&#34;&gt;https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve got to start with my tool of choice although I can&amp;#39;t really be
unbiased. I think it gets a bad wrap because it&amp;#39;s old and out of the
box looks plain but, yes, you can use your mouse and it does have
menus. The upside is that it can do everything an IDE can do and a
thousand times more. I do email, read rss feeds, maintain my calendar
and more in Emacs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The downside is that it doesn&amp;#39;t do Java well out of the box and kids
like shinier objects. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;d start the teachers with Emacs but I&amp;#39;d probably shift
my instruction to using it at some point and show some of the cooler
features (many highlighted in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs/&#34;&gt;Emcacs videos&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-9&#34;&gt;
Gedit
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Gedit%0A&#34;&gt;https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Gedit%0A&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a plain simple editor. You can bucket in notepad+ and whatever
the basic Mac editor is in here. Nothing special and nothing
fancy. It&amp;#39;s easy enough to load, edit a file and save but not much
more. I&amp;#39;d be fine using it were it not for better options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-10&#34;&gt;
Vim
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vim.org/&#34;&gt;https://www.vim.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-11&#34;&gt;
Sublime Text
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sublimetext.com/%0A&#34;&gt;https://www.sublimetext.com/%0A&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was the hotness for a while and it&amp;#39;s a pretty slick editor. I
can&amp;#39;t recommend it for teachers though for two reasons. One is that
it&amp;#39;s not free (although it isn&amp;#39;t expensive). The other is that it&amp;#39;s
not open source. There were other hot editors before sublime and when
their companies folded or sunset the editor all those plugins and
customizations had to be redone on a new platform. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-12&#34;&gt;
Atom
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://atom.io/&#34;&gt;https://atom.io/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Atom&amp;#39;s an editor I want to like. It&amp;#39;s open source and looks pretty
neat but it seems more focused on the JS ecosystem. I couldn&amp;#39;t find
enough Java related plugins to make it better than Gedit although it
was easy to theme and customize the keys. Were I not an Emacs guy I&amp;#39;d
probably use Atom for much of my non-Java development but it doesn&amp;#39;t
seem like a great fit for Java
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-13&#34;&gt;
Jedit
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jedit.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.jedit.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This looked like the strongest contender for Java. Not too
complicated. Nice syntax highlighting out of the box. It doesn&amp;#39;t do
completion but that&amp;#39;s arguably a good thing when teaching
programming (incidentally, Emacs doesn&amp;#39;t do completion out of the box
but it can be added so you can up the tools ability as the class moves
along). From my limited explorations you can install plugins like a
Java Linter and you can run a console from inside JEdit which means
you can actually type things like &lt;code&gt;javac file.java&lt;/code&gt; and then run the
program all from within the editor.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jedit also has some nice builtin macros for boilerplate code like
setters and getters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-14&#34;&gt;
IDEs
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-15&#34;&gt;
Eclipse 
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.org&#34;&gt;https://www.eclipse.org&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve used eclipse before and as a Java environment, it&amp;#39;s actually
pretty nice. You can customize the keys so I set mine to Emacs. It has
a lot of plugins, you can compile and test your program from within
the IDE and do tons of other things. It&amp;#39;s a VERY nice professional
tool.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t like it for teaching for three reasons. First, it does too
much. By giving too much professional support kids rely too much on
the tool. Second, it&amp;#39;s made for big projects using build systems not
small AP class programs consisting of one or two files where you run
javac manually. Yes, you can do this in Eclipse but it seems more
awkward. Third, becasue there&amp;#39;s so much going on you need a HUGE
screen and kids and schools might not have enough screen real estate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s also a fourth reason which is that I installed Eclipse using
LinuxMint&amp;#39;s package manager and it crashed when running. If I&amp;#39;m going
to recommend a teacher roll out a tool that all of their students are
going to install at home on their own, at the very least it has to
install and run seamlessly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-16&#34;&gt;
DrJava
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drjava.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.drjava.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like Eclipse, I&amp;#39;ve used DrJava before. It&amp;#39;s similar to DrRacket (nee
Scheme) and Dr. Python. It&amp;#39;s close to perfect. You get highlighting,
helpful error finding, can run your program from within Dr. Java and
more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The killer problem is that I can&amp;#39;t get the latest version to
run. Actually the first problem is that it&amp;#39;s just a jar file so you
have to run it with &lt;code&gt;java -jar drjava.jar&lt;/code&gt;. Beyond that, it didn&amp;#39;t
work out of the box. It loaded but compilign and running didn&amp;#39;t After
some mucking around, I got it to compile but it doesn&amp;#39;t run the
programs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is too bad because when it runs it&amp;#39;s a terrific learning
environment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-17&#34;&gt;
BlueJ
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bluej.org/&#34;&gt;https://bluej.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is another tool that was DOA. I tried the debian package as well
as the jar file. Couldn&amp;#39;t get it working. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have used an older version so I&amp;#39;ll describe that instead just
remember things might be different in the current version.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
BlueJ does one thing very well - objects. It visually shows object
creation and relationships. I recall that you can create an opject,
click on it&amp;#39;s box in a visual graph pane, inspect it, instantiate new
ones and in general explore and expirement. If you&amp;#39;re big on OOP and
like Object First by all means check BlueJ out. It&amp;#39;s probably best in
class for that approach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it&amp;#39;s a one trick pony. If you, like me, are not all
in on OOP or an Objects first and all the time approach it&amp;#39;s probably
not the tool for you. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-18&#34;&gt;
Geany
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geany.org/&#34;&gt;https://www.geany.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I hadn&amp;#39;t heard of this one before but it looks like a contender. It
has a  pretty clean interface and it worked out of the box. I
installed it using the package manager.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/geany.png&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Class browser on the right, files on the left and console (terminal),
compiler status etc on the bottom. It supports some level of
autocomplete but it doesn&amp;#39;t do everything. I&amp;#39;m not sure yet but it
might hit the completion sweet spot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It says it does snippets but I haven&amp;#39;t figured that out yet. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-19&#34;&gt;
IntelliJ
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/&#34;&gt;https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
IntelliJ is fro JetBrains. They make a bunch of IDEs each focussed on
a different toolset but all with the same look and feel. You can also
add plugins to each to make them multi-modal. I believe the editor at
the core is JEdit. I&amp;#39;ve used their IDEs in the past and as far as
professional IDEs go I like them. They&amp;#39;re more lightweight than say
Eclipse and don&amp;#39;t need the real estate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, I think it&amp;#39;s too much for a beginner. For example, you can
in theory run your program from the build menu but, much like Eclipse,
it takes you to a configuration screen. I was pretty lost and I&amp;#39;m not
a beginner. Much like Eclipse it&amp;#39;s made for projects not small class
programs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I found the Python version of JetBrains IDEs more approachable
probably because the ecosystem is much simpler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-20&#34;&gt;
VSCode
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://code.visualstudio.com/&#34;&gt;https://code.visualstudio.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one shocked me - I actually found myself liking a Microsoft
product. I guess this really isn&amp;#39;t your father&amp;#39;s Microsoft.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/vscode.png&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Much like Geany it has a clean interface and like Geany you don&amp;#39;t need
a whole Java build system. It does more completions out of the box
which you may or may not like as well as snippets. A single key will
compile and run your program and on top of all that it has en &amp;#34;Emacs&amp;#34;
setting for keybindings.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not sure if I like Geany or VSCode better but I think both are
really good options. I&amp;#39;d probably lean towards Geany due to the less
robust completions. Were I writing code for real rather than teaching,
I&amp;#39;d probably go the other way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-21&#34;&gt;
JGrasp
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/vscode.png&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JGrasp feels much the same as the other contenders - Geany and VSCode
but the interface just looks a bit clunkier to me. I know that&amp;#39;s
purely subjective. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest difference I&amp;#39;m seeing out of the box is that JGrasp
doesn&amp;#39;t do completions so depending on where you fall with that you
might want Jgrasp for none, Geany for some, and VSCode for all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;[EDIT]&lt;/strong&gt; JGrasp has a very cool visualizer built in that will animate
 your proram. Here&amp;#39;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wuQowTV0o6s&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; of it in action. I&amp;#39;m going to have to
 play with this a bit and see if it pushes JGrasp up over the top for
 me. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-22&#34;&gt;
Processing
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://processing.org/&#34;&gt;https://processing.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not going to talk about processing but I felt that it would be
negligent not to mention it at all. Processing is a IDE, wrapper and
graphical library that&amp;#39;s essentially Java under the hood (although
there are Processing bindings in many other languages probably the
most well known now is &lt;a href=&#34;https://p5js.org/&#34;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;). It&amp;#39;s great if you want to do graphical
work or base your class around the libraries that are available to
processing which include ones for web cameras, hardware access,
networking, sound and more but it&amp;#39;s not the same as an IDE or editor
for traditional Java development.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-23&#34;&gt;
Notes
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just about all of these tools have multiple themes and are fairly
customizable so don&amp;#39;t go by the screenshots above, on the homepages or
what they look like when you first install them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of the tools I liked installed right out of the box either by
using the package manager or downloading and extracting from an
archive. I can&amp;#39;t say yet if they install as easily on a Mac or Windows
box but since Linux is usually the unloved stepchild of sortware
packaging and distribution my guess is that if anything it&amp;#39;ll be
easier on those platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-24&#34;&gt;
Conclusions
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll always be an Emacs guy. Org-mode is too useful and I can get IDE
like behavior for pretty much any language I want to work in. In some
cases like Clojure, I haven&amp;#39;t seen an IDE that can match Emacs and
Cider, it&amp;#39;s premier Clojure development setup. I also haven&amp;#39;t a Git
interface nearly as slick and powerful as &lt;a href=&#34;https://magit.vc/&#34;&gt;Magit&lt;/a&gt; which works under
Emacs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For my teachers though, I&amp;#39;ll probably start with Geany or VSCode,
switch to Emacs for myself at some point in the program and make sure
to spend time on the command line along the way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I missed any editors or IDEs or have something to add on one of the
ones I mentioned, please share in the comments.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/java-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Two of the hardest topics to make meaningful to students in APCS-A are
inheritance and interfaces. It&amp;#39;s not that they&amp;#39;re super difficult
topics but rather that they&amp;#39;re not often needed, useful, or superior
to not using them on beginner assignments. More often than not the
motivation is a bit forced as are the assignments. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Inheritance is its own can of worms and to be honest, something I&amp;#39;ve
not found to be all that useful or necessary. The class abstraction
made sense to me for a number of projects but deep inheritance just
hasn&amp;#39;t come up much. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, today I thought I&amp;#39;d talk about interfaces.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When Java was first built a decision was made not to allow multiple
inheritance - the idea that a class can be derived from multiple
parents. Multiple inheritance is powerful but it can also be
complicated and confusing. By not including multiple inheritance Java
ended up easier to work with than say C++ but there were times where
you needed features that multiple inheritance provide. Specifically
there are times when you need some functionality that operates across
multiple unrelated classes. Without any other features, you&amp;#39;d have to
start &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; of your classes from a single based class and include that
functionality. Clearly not a good idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first useful example is probably &lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At first blush it might not seem all that useful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s suppose you are doing something like finding the first String
(alphabetically) from an array:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s easy enough but what if you had another class, &lt;code&gt;Shape&lt;/code&gt; where
you wanted to find the &amp;#34;smallest&amp;#34; based on area and a third class
&lt;code&gt;Person&lt;/code&gt; where you want to find the smallest by age? Without
interfaces you would need three independent search routines or set up
a crazy inheritance hierarchy where &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Person&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Shape&lt;/code&gt; all
come from the same parent. Instead, by having your two new classes
implement the &lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt; interface all three can use the same
search:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not entirely true. The above solution will give you compiler
warnings. You&amp;#39;ll have to decide if it makes sense to jump through the
hoops necessary to get rid of the warnings or if it&amp;#39;s sufficient to do
some vigorous had waving.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the benefit of interfaces. You can create functionality that
works across classes. In addition to writing things like our
 &lt;code&gt;findSmallest&lt;/code&gt; above, if our classes implement &lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt; we can sort
collections of our classes using the built in sort methods.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a benefit that our students can probably appreciate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anther place interfaces come up and make sense are with GUI
programming. It&amp;#39;s pretty easy to show the utility of using interfaces
with the assorted listeners. That said, Java GUI programming is
something of a bear so maybe that&amp;#39;s not the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Where else can you explore interfaces in APCS-A? Any program where you
have different entities that change in different ways over time. This
might be a simulation where time passes via a control loop or maybe a
game where time passes a turn at a time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, you might have a simulation with various resources that
implement an interface with an &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; routine:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe a food resource updates by raising or lowering the amount of
food it provides or perhaps an animal resource updates its location. You could
have an array of objects that implement this interface and just call
update on each one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You could do the same with a game. Maybe the human player&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; 
prompts for keyboard input while non player characters just calculate
their next state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Interfaces are not the easiest thing to teach. The mechanics are
straightforward but the motivation is frequently forced for
beginners. I was never 100% happy with how I did it and now that I&amp;#39;m
in a C++ shop it doesn&amp;#39;t come up but I hope this is helpful to some of
you out there.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>