<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tech on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (tech)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 11:56:23 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping Current Between Semesters</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/keeping-current-between-semesters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 11:56:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/keeping-current-between-semesters/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
People say that one of the impossible problems for CS teachers is
keeping current - they say the field is constantly changing, how can a
teacher keep up with all the new things going on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, on the one hand it isn&amp;#39;t true - most of the core of CS is the
same. We still teach roughly the same programming constructs, data
structures and algorithms. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it is true. When I was in college, OOP was just
starting to pick up steam and now an established and one might argue,
dominant paradigm. Functional programming has been around forever but
is only recently making inroads into the mainstream. Some fields have
radically changed. Just look at AI and related fields now that data is
so abundant. I remember looking over a Natural Language Processing
text in the mid 90s and it was all about programs with tons of if
statements. A later edition read more like a statistics text book.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then there are the changing technologies - the web and how we program
it, new languages, embedded systems are more accesible and much more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So the field both changes and stays the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the ways I try to stay on top of things is with my own personal
projects. We encourage our students to write side projects
to scratch itches so why shouldn&amp;#39;t we do the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This might be taking a course like when I did the Stanford online AI
and ML courses or it might be writing something like when I wanted to
figure out that &lt;a href=&#34;https://reactjs.org/&#34;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; thing that was all the rage a couple of years
ago but ended up diving more deeply into  &lt;a href=&#34;https://vuejs.org/&#34;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; as I felt it made
more sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re between semesters at Hunter I thought I&amp;#39;d scratch an
itch related to &lt;a href=&#34;https://classroom.github.com/classrooms&#34;&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. I love the tool but it has two pain
points. First, you end up accumulating a HUGE number of repositories
(one per student per assignment) and deleting them is a bear of a
task. The second is that while you can download all the submissions
for a given assignment, there&amp;#39;s no easy way to download all the
assignments for a given student. There are also some issues mapping
student names to GitHub accounts but I&amp;#39;ve pretty much worked that one
out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I figured I&amp;#39;d spend some time this December and January learning
some new technologies adn writing something to make those pain points
go away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what will I be learning about?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The GitHub API
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve worked with APIs before and even messed around with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt;. The
change is that their &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.github.com/v4/&#34;&gt;latest&lt;/a&gt; version uses GraphQL which brings me to my
first brand new technology:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
GraphQL
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://graphql.org/&#34;&gt;GraphQL&lt;/a&gt; is a query language developed by Facebook for APIs. In spite
of the name, it has nothing to do with databases. The idea is instead
of a bunch of random REST endpoints with every API call being
different you have one endpoint. You put together a query describing
what you want and the services responds with your content. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It looks pretty neat but we&amp;#39;ll see.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Reagent / Clojurescript
&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next thing I&amp;#39;ll be playing with is &lt;a href=&#34;https://clojurescript.org/&#34;&gt;Clojurescript&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://reagent-project.github.io/&#34;&gt;Reagent&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;ve
been playing on and off with Clojure for a while ahd Clojurescript
transpiles Clojure to Javascript instead of compiling for the
JVM. I&amp;#39;ve  already made a few &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-life&#34;&gt;small&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-breakout&#34;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zamansky/clojure-snake&#34;&gt;using&lt;/a&gt; it and like it much
better for the web than Javascript. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learnreagent.com/&#34;&gt;Reagent&lt;/a&gt; is essentially React for
Clojurescript.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Electron
&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought for a while about doing this as a command line tool since
that&amp;#39;s how I usually work but decided that if I do finish it something
GUI based might be useful to more people. I then considered a web
applicaiton but realized that wouldn&amp;#39;t do since there isn&amp;#39;t a way to
clone GitHub repos from a web application due to security issues. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then briefly considered doing a Clojure based GUI which would
basically be something like a Java Swing application but then decided
to explore &lt;a href=&#34;https://electronjs.org/&#34;&gt;Electron&lt;/a&gt;. An Electron appication is essentially a locally
run web application. You write it in a similar manner to a web app -
HTML/CSS/JS or in my case Clojurescript but then it&amp;#39;s run locally on a
platfomr based on the open source Chromium browser. Since it&amp;#39;s running
locally it has access to the local filesystem and resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve already started to play with things and already learned a
lot. Looking forward to coming out of this with a bunch of new
technologies and tools in the toolbelt and maybe an application that
will solve a couple of annoyances with what&amp;#39;s overall a great product.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>