<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lessons on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/lessons/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (Lessons)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 07:48:14 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/lessons/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I Speak Jive</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 07:48:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-speak-jive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
When I wrote about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/highedweb2019/&#34;&gt;HighWebEd&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/elfin_john&#34;&gt;John William&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;s talk on
Agile. He spoke about how the movie Airplane! was filmed in an Agile
manner and gave as an example the development of the &amp;#34;jive&amp;#34; scenes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zdCjbJ6NEfc&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zdCjbJ6NEfc&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Apparently the creative team had a script but it wasn&amp;#39;t working. The
first pair that read for the role, Norman Gibbs and Al White had their
owned take. Not only dir the team cast them on the spot and follow
their creative lead (hence Agile) but they also apparently apologized
to the two actors as the original attempt was so bad compared t what
Gibbs and White brought to the table.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, I would be negligent if I didn&amp;#39;t mention that the third
person to really make the jive sequence was Barbara Billingsley of
Leave it to Beaver fame.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, coming home, I had the Airplane! and the jive scenes in the back
of my mind. The other day at home, somehow or other we were chatting
about that great American masterpiece, The Muppet Show and of course,
the Swedish Chef.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OUU6Rt6bi1U&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OUU6Rt6bi1U&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brought me back the the &lt;a href=&#34;https://muppet.fandom.com/wiki/Encheferizer\&#34;&gt;Encheferizer&lt;/a&gt; (live version &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tuco.de/home/jschef.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So how is jive from Airplane! related to The Swedish Chef?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Filters!!!!!!!!&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A filter, in this context, is a program that takes data as input, in
this case a stream of text. Does some transformation to it and then
spits out the transformed text.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Way back, Unix systems had a program called &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jive_filter&#34;&gt;jive&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;#34;translated&amp;#34;
text into Jive along with other filters including cockney and valspeak which
converted text to like, um, Valley Girl speak dontcha know. It was,
like, totally tubular. Of course one filter was named &lt;strong&gt;chef&lt;/strong&gt;, known as
the encheferizer which translated into Swedish Chef talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over time, the list of filters grew. Some were silly, some fun, and,
yes, some were kind of offensive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
(side bar: as I write this bit of history, I just feel as though I&amp;#39;ve
been transported to Doug Peterson&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://dougpete.wordpress.com/2019/11/03/whatever-happened-to-183/&#34;&gt;Whatever happened to…&lt;/a&gt; posts and
feel as though I should write something like: Do you remember using
filters? Which ones did you use? etc.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, somewhere in here there&amp;#39;s the making of some nice class
projects but the challenge was how to do the translation. Some things
are easy. One filter was the Fudd filter which translated to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elmer_Fudd&#34;&gt;Elmer
Fudd&lt;/a&gt; speak. It&amp;#39;s easy enough to substitute &lt;strong&gt;w&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;strong&gt;l&lt;/strong&gt; in a word as
Elmer says &amp;#34;Hew wow&amp;#34; instead of &amp;#34;Hello&amp;#34; but it&amp;#39;s hard to know if you&amp;#39;ve
got enough translation rules so that your students text will change
enough to be entertaining.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, I found &lt;a href=&#34;- https://github.com/hyperrealm/talkfilters&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; repo. It&amp;#39;s an implementation of a whole
bunch of filters:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
austro (Think Ahhnolld), b1ff (a web newbie), brooklyn, butthead (as
in Beevis and), chef, cockney, drawl, dubya, fudd, funetak, jethro,
jive, kraut, newspeak, pansy, pirate, postmodern, redneck, valspeak, warez
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I couldn&amp;#39;t get the system to compile but was able to dive into the
source code to see the rules. They&amp;#39;re in the &lt;strong&gt;.l&lt;/strong&gt; files. All of those
files are source for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lex_%2528software%2529&#34;&gt;Lex&lt;/a&gt; parser generator but even if you aren&amp;#39;t
familiar with Lex you should be able to figure out most of the rules.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the translators rely mostly on simple letter
substitutions. Fudd is such a filter:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-lex&#34; data-lang=&#34;lex&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;r&amp;#34;         gtf_printf(&amp;#34;w&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;l&amp;#34;         gtf_printf(&amp;#34;w&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;qu&amp;#34;        gtf_printf(&amp;#34;qw&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;th &amp;#34;       gtf_printf(&amp;#34;f &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;th&amp;#34;        gtf_printf(&amp;#34;d&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;n.&amp;#34;        gtf_printf(&amp;#34;n, uh-hah-hah-hah. &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;R&amp;#34;         gtf_printf(&amp;#34;W&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;L&amp;#34;         gtf_printf(&amp;#34;W&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;Qu&amp;#34;        gtf_printf(&amp;#34;Qw&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;QU&amp;#34;        gtf_printf(&amp;#34;QW&amp;#34;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dubya, on the other hand goes more with word substitutions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-lex&#34; data-lang=&#34;lex&#34;&gt;[Tt]errorist		|
[Oo]sama		|
[Bb]in(-|{WB})[Ll]ad(e|i)n	{ switch(gtf_random(3))
				  {
				  case 0: gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;bad guy&amp;#34;); break;
				  case 1: gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;evildoer&amp;#34;); break;
				  case 2: gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;terrier&amp;#34;); break;
				  }
				}
[Uu]njustified/{NW}	     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;pre-emptive&amp;#34;);
[Cc]ontra/{NW}		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;freedom-fighter&amp;#34;);
[Un]nder		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;misunder&amp;#34;); BEGIN(INW);
[Mm]isunderstand	     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;misunderestimate&amp;#34;); BEGIN(INW);
[Mm]isunderstood             gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;misunderestimated&amp;#34;); BEGIN(INW);
[Kk]ill/{NW}		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;oblitifry&amp;#34;);
[Kk]illed/{NW}		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;oblitifried&amp;#34;);
[Dd]destroy/{NW}	     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;destructifry&amp;#34;);
[Dd]destroyed/{NW}	     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;destructifried&amp;#34;);
[Rr]esonat/{NW}		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;resignat&amp;#34;);
[Ee]ven(-|{WB})[Hh]anded/{NW} gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;foreign-handed&amp;#34;);
[Ee]mbitter		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;embetter&amp;#34;); BEGIN(INW);
[Ff]allability/{NW}	     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;fallacy&amp;#34;);
[An]tidote/{NW}		     gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;anecdote&amp;#34;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some, like chef, pirate, and aust do some of both:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-lex&#34; data-lang=&#34;lex&#34;&gt;[Tt]h		gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;z&amp;#34;);
w		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;v&amp;#34;);
ou		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;u&amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;de &amp;#34;		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;d &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;le &amp;#34;		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;l &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;me &amp;#34;		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;m &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;ne &amp;#34;		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;n &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;re &amp;#34;		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;r &amp;#34;);
&amp;#34;ve &amp;#34;		gtf_puts(&amp;#34;v &amp;#34;);
[Cc]		gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;s&amp;#34;);
[Pp]ie		gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;mozer&amp;#39;s pie&amp;#34;);
[Ss]teak        gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;shnitzel&amp;#34;);
[Gg]overnor	gtf_puts_case(&amp;#34;govenator&amp;#34;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some also deal with more complex situations such as only substituting
letters if they&amp;#39;re at the end of words and the like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is leading to a huge number lesson and project
possibilities from simple text replacements in an intro class to
something much more ambitious in a later class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was looking to vary some of the things we do in Hunter and I think
I&amp;#39;ll add some language filters to the mix.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not every lesson has to be magic</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 18:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/not-always-exciting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
If you check out Twitter, Facebook, Medium  and other blog sites you
might get the idea that you&amp;#39;re the worst teacher in the world. The
internet abounds with people sharing tweets and posts about wonderful
lessons they&amp;#39;ve just taught, witnessed or learned about in
professional development. Sure, the teacher forums rife with requests
for lesson ideas and resources but the shared material is always aces.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It makes sense, people in the community want to share things that
worked for them or things they think will work. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, for new teachers it can create an unhealthy illusion of what
really goes on in the classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that sharing of the good stuff is a bad thing but
the truth is that not every lesson is a masterpiece, not every teacher
is a super charismatic showman, and not all topics lend themselves to
creative teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing this now? Because I was planning lessons earlier
today and I&amp;#39;m at one of those places where I&amp;#39;m not going to be able to
deliver a whiz-bang lesson in my next class. One of my classes this
semester is for beginners so we&amp;#39;re building up language skills from
the ground up. Right now I want to do some loop applications but
there&amp;#39;s only so much we can do given what the students know. There are
reasons why I don&amp;#39;t want to do graphics with them right now. I also
haven&amp;#39;t introduced lists yet and don&amp;#39;t want to loop over strings yet
so I&amp;#39;m left with doing mathy stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ll look at Newton&amp;#39;s method for square roots. It&amp;#39;s
interesting for the math inclined and does let us explore issues with
floating point and accuracy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not going to be super exciting for everyone though and that&amp;#39;s okay. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could do lists first but I don&amp;#39;t want the kids to have to handle so
much new material so quickly. I&amp;#39;d rather keep the pace slower and work
with what they&amp;#39;ve just learned for a bit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could also do graphics but that adds a level of overhead I don&amp;#39;t
want to get into now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea is to look at the long game. A class runs a whole semester or
possibly a year. You&amp;#39;re going to have some special memorable lessons
and some mundane ones and that&amp;#39;s nothing to be ashamed of. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re still mostly going to see best practices shared online with only
a few brave souls sharing disaster classes and asking for help. That&amp;#39;s
just how the internet works. It&amp;#39;s not the worst thing in the
world. Just remember when you&amp;#39;re struggling to come up with a good
lesson or you&amp;#39;ve just taught a bad one that tomorrow&amp;#39;s will be
better. Judge yourself by your students long term development, not one
day at a time.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There&#39;s always something to learn (from your students)</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One thing I&amp;#39;ve learned from teaching is that there&amp;#39;s always something
new to learn. For the kids, yes, but I&amp;#39;m talking about for the
teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other day, I taught a lesson I&amp;#39;ve taught many times. Find the mode
of a data set. That&amp;#39;s the problem that they solve but the lesson is
really about run time complexity, hidden complexity and using data
structures in alternate ways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I blogged about this &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-Who_won_the_election-Quadratic_to_Linear_Time.md&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; so you can get an earlier take there
although the code isn&amp;#39;t formatted correctly due to blog conversions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As with the last time, the students  had already written code to find
the largest value in a list and also to find the frequency of an item
in a list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They had to write mode prior to the class. In the past, students would
generally come up with something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They&amp;#39;d use their existing knowledge and the &amp;#39;find the largest&amp;#39; idiom
to find the mode by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
find the frequency of the first item and assume it&amp;#39;s the mode so far
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
for each item in the list
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
find the frequency of that idem
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
if it occurs more than the mode so far then it becomes the new
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
mode so far
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a lot of good in this solution. The kids incrementally develop
a solution, they use and exctend code and concepts they already know
and understand and it&amp;#39;s clear and understandable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We would then run the code on larger and larger data sets and notice
that it gets slow pretty quickly. This leads to an informal discussion
of run time and the fact that there&amp;#39;s hidden complexity – the call to
&lt;code&gt;freq&lt;/code&gt; in the main loop introduces a linear component so we have a
loop within a loop and an N^2 routine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big takeaway is get a feel for run time and to be aware of hidden
complexity. We then move to a linear solution by using a list as
buckets. You can read more about that in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-Who_won_the_election-Quadratic_to_Linear_Time.md&#34;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What was interesting this time around was that most of the kids came
up with a solution more like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Instead of calculating the frequency inside the loop they made a list
of frequencies. &lt;code&gt;freq[0]&lt;/code&gt; had the frequency of &lt;code&gt;l[0]&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;freq[1]&lt;/code&gt; the
frequency of &lt;code&gt;l[1]&lt;/code&gt; etc. They then loop through that &lt;code&gt;freq&lt;/code&gt; list to
find the largest element and that&amp;#39;s the index of the mode value in the
original list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s functionally the same as the first solution but in some ways it&amp;#39;s
very different. They built the data set they needed ahead of time
instead of calculating the data on the fly and they used the concept
of parallel lists.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like the solution and it didn&amp;#39;t prevent us from getting to the run
time stuff but this did give me something to think about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why did this class led them largely to a different solution than the
classes I&amp;#39;ve taught in the class. There are a lot of things to ponder
since it&amp;#39;s a college class that meets twice a week with kids from a
range of backgrounds (CS and otherwise) vs a high school class that
meets 5 days a week and the kids all had the same in class experience
prior to this lesson. Did I do something differently before hand? Some
assignments? Something I modeled?  I&amp;#39;m not sure but it&amp;#39;s something I&amp;#39;m
going to ponder.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It will interesting to see if this was a one shot deal and my current
class will solve problems as I predict moving forward or if I&amp;#39;m going
to get to see a lot of new things.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>