<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blog on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/blog/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (blog)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 09:03:05 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Time For A New Theme</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/time-for-a-new-theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 09:03:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/time-for-a-new-theme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While setting up my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pinebook-update/&#34;&gt;Pinebook Pro&lt;/a&gt; I wanted to make sure I could write
blog posts. &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; installed and ran no problem but I switched to
Hugo in April 2020 back when it was version .49 or something like
that. Now it&amp;#39;s up to .73. It turns out there have been a few
changes. First, I set up my blog with two directories for posts. One
for the posts I wrote originally in Jekyll and one for the ones I
wrote for Hugo. I had to make a few changes to get that to work with
the new version.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also discovered that my archive page no longer works under the
current version of Hugo. As I poked around a little more, it turns out
that HTML embedding changed so I&amp;#39;m going to have to tweak all my Emacs
posts as well as posts where I embed tweets or other content.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that some or maybe many of my older posts will
be wonky until I can get around to fixing them. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rather than figuring out how to fix them under my current blog theme I
figured it was also a good time to explore a new Hugo theme so don&amp;#39;t
be surprised if the overall look here changes a few times over the
next few posts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hopefully I&amp;#39;ll be able to get everything working again sooner rather
than later.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>