<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>college on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/college/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (college)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/college/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hunter Daedalus Fall 2019 recruiting class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that high school seniors have all committed to their respective
colleges I though I&amp;#39;d share some information on Hunter&amp;#39;s incoming
Daedalus (honors CS) cohort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I joke about the first cohort saying that nobody applied to the
program. That&amp;#39;s kind of true. I jointed Hunter a little over three
years ago in late January. That was after high school seniors had
already applied to college and at that time the program didn&amp;#39;t
exist. We found the first cohort by looking at students who had
already applied to Hunter not expecting Daedalus to exist.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was 12 kids and we&amp;#39;ve lost a few since then. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second cohort consisted of 24 students. We started adding
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_E._Macaulay_Honors_College&#34;&gt;Macaulay&lt;/a&gt; students into the mix. Macaulay is a CUNY wide honors
scholarship program. Each campus has a cohort and it was part of an
effort to bring CUNY back to it&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;glory days&amp;#34; before open
enrollment. The Macaulay kids saw that Daedalus was the place to be
for CS in NYC and Hunter and wanted in. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Third year, we were up to 44 students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, in our fourth year we&amp;#39;re up to 50 which is a little over
capacity - at least until I can find and hire a partner in crime  (and
I am looking).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some other stats:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year:&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2016&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Size:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daedalus / Macaulay:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75% / 25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75%/ 20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;80% / 20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Approximate Applicants&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;~150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;~200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Over 320&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gender M/F %&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80/20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50/50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;75/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Taken APCS / Beginner&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50/50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;50/50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Number of high schools&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;# students from beyond NYC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also have stats on grades and test scores as well as the number of
offers an the percent of acceptances. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some thoughts on the stats:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I try to spend as much time as I can doing outreach. This is horribly
inefficient but it&amp;#39;s slowly getting the word out. I might spend most
of a day trekking out into the boroughs to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/&#34;&gt;talk to a class&lt;/a&gt; or a few
classes at some school knowing that there will probably be very few
fits for my program. I think I&amp;#39;m bringing important information to all
of the kids but it&amp;#39;s a low yield activity. Right now our biggest
feeder schools are Stuyvesant, Brooklyn Tech, and Bronx Science. Next
is Midwood. This makes sense as they&amp;#39;re all &lt;strong&gt;large&lt;/strong&gt; schools and they
all have established CS classes. They&amp;#39;ll probably continue to be the
biggest feeders but I&amp;#39;m delighted by the fact that I&amp;#39;m getting
students from 17 other schools including a couple from outside of
NYC. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m less happy with the gender distribution. Twenty five percent isn&amp;#39;t
bad compared to the national numbers but we should be doing
better. It&amp;#39;s a tough nut to crack. When I visit to schools I&amp;#39;m
normally sent to the CS classes so I&amp;#39;m already getting a gender skewed
audience. Not sure the best approach to work on this. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, I&amp;#39;m getting to enough of a general audience to have
roughly a 50/50 split of students with APCS-A or beyond or what I
would call a beginner. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I get to know this new group and find out why they applied to
Hunter Daedalus and ultimately decided to attend I&amp;#39;m hoping to be able
to better fine tune my recruiting approach and outreach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a bottom line I&amp;#39;m going to continue to work to make Hunter&amp;#39;s
Daedalus program the place to be for CS education in NY so that kids
can get a top flight experience without paying a quarter of a million
dollars.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting schools and talking tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Back in September I talked about embarking on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/&#34;&gt;Fall 2018 HS CS Tour&lt;/a&gt;.
Since then I&amp;#39;ve visited about a dozen schools. I&amp;#39;d like to thank my
friends who helped connect me to schools - particularly &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aankit&#34;&gt;Aankit Patel&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt&#34;&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though the original motivation for the visits was to get the word
out about Hunter CS and the awesome things we&amp;#39;re doing in the Hunter
CS Honors program I always tried to make my talks about something that
would be relevant for the entire audience and not just the few that
were great fits for my program. I think I&amp;#39;ve done a pretty good job at
that. All this said, doing these visits is incredibly draining. I&amp;#39;m
usually up at the crack of dawn and end up taking the subway or
sometimes subway and bus way out into the five boroughs. Actually four
this year since I wasn&amp;#39;t able to get a date to visit any Staten Island
schools. It takes a lot of time and effort and while I love
talking to students and there some ancillary things I enjoy about
getting out into the neighborhoods of the city I&amp;#39;m extremely happy
that I can now rest for a few weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reflecting on all of this I&amp;#39;m realizing how important these visits are
and not because they&amp;#39;re recruiting trips.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spoke about some of the specifics I talk about in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;
but arguably more important is that for many of them it&amp;#39;s the first
time for them to hear about the possibilities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While many students are excited about what they&amp;#39;re doing in their first
CS classes it turns out that few have any idea where it will
lead. They may have heard that computer science can lead to a high
paying job. They might know they can get a job at Google but they
don&amp;#39;t really know what that means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I saw this at Hunter when I started three years ago and now a lot of
hard work later students are much more in tune with the New York Tech
community and all that it means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students don&amp;#39;t realize that there are many programming careers beyond
Google and their are many CS careers beyond programming. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They don&amp;#39;t realize they can combine computer science with almost any
other field or interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They don&amp;#39;t know that the same algorithmic approach behind Amazon,
Netflix, and Spotify recommendations can be used by companies selling
cloths, cosmetics, or anything else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s just the tip of the iceberg. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now I&amp;#39;m not saying that teachers aren&amp;#39;t telling their students about
the possibilities but rather that sometimes it has to come from an
outsider. When I started at Stuy, before I had a reputation (good or
bad) I&amp;#39;d tell students things and they wouldn&amp;#39;t buy it. Later I&amp;#39;d have
a friend from the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; come in. Frequently they&amp;#39;d touch on
points I addressed in class and all of a sudden I was worth listening
to. Sometimes you need an outside voice to empower and authenticate the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying that I&amp;#39;m a super motivational speaker or anything like
that. I&amp;#39;m not. I&amp;#39;m an ok speaker with content worth listening to. I&amp;#39;m
just realizing more and more how important this small self imposed
corner of my job is. Not so much for Hunter but for the kids of NY. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jut this past week I&amp;#39;ve started to work to connect some of my current
students to &lt;a href=&#34;http://tealsk12.org&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; volunteers. If you read this blog you know I&amp;#39;m a
big fan of TEALS and have wanted to encourage my students to get
involved for a while. Once we get some of our Hunter CS majors into
schools around the city to help teach CS perhaps they can help spread
the message of the possibilities to even more students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve written before about why &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/&#34;&gt;Hunter College CS is so important&lt;/a&gt; for
NYC and I&amp;#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors
CS program -  a program in which students receive a scholarship along
with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS
education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/&#34;&gt;made a lot of
progress&lt;/a&gt; over the past two years and each year I roll out new
special activities and events for my honors students. Still, a major
challenges is getting the word out and building our reputation. Anyone
who takes a close look at what we&amp;#39;re doing can see we&amp;#39;re growing
something special but we still have to convince students and parents
who may not even realize that Hunter offers a CS degree to come to us
instead of going to more well known albeit much more expensive programs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To that end I try to visit as many high schools as I can during the
Fall semester to speak to high school seniors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Friday at Packer Collegiate.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Great to have &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt; come by and talk to juniors and seniors in the advanced CS about the tech sector and options for study including the amazing program at Hunter &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ubHNfyt8Y9&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ubHNfyt8Y9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; saber khan (@ed_saber) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber/status/1045768969519542272?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was invited by my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber&#34;&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; who runs the weekly twitter
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first started doing school visits I had a tough time figuring
out exactly what to say - I&amp;#39;m no salesman - I&amp;#39;m not good at it and I
don&amp;#39;t like doing it. Fortunately, I didn&amp;#39;t have to be a salesman. I
decided I&amp;#39;d talk to the students about questions they should be asking
themselves as they consider where to go after graduation. I talk about
school location, community, and culture. I also talk about majors - BA
vs BS, Major vs Minor, niche majors, and possible career paths. I also
talk about tech sectors - how NY might be different from Sill icon
Valley might be different from Seattle or Boston.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also tell them the truth about the undergraduate experience - how
you can get a great CS background at all sorts of schools. How
Algorithms is Algorithms and no matter where you go you&amp;#39;ll probably
use the same text and how while I have many former students at the
Googles and Facebooks of the world that  have gone to MIT and CMU I
also have plenty who end up at those companies or similar going to
Stony, Oberlin, Tufts, and yes, Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the talk I spend a few minutes talking about Hunter and
my honors program but it&amp;#39;s only a small part of the talk. I figure in
any given class there will be a few kids who could be a fit for my
program and I want the time spent to be worthwhile for the entire
class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes guidance people sit in when I talk to the students and
almost always they tell me how valuable it was for the students to
have someone like me come in and talk frankly about the college
application and acceptance process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s going to take time to build our reputation at Hunter but I think
that going around to students and talking honestly about college and
not giving the hard sell helps build trust and our reputation and over
time, people will realize the value we&amp;#39;re bringing to the table and
come to us. It&amp;#39;s already happening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, the only other challenge is to get more high schools to bring me
in. Next week I&amp;#39;m visiting NEST+M and Brooklyn Tech and I&amp;#39;ve got a few
more on the calendar in upcoming weeks but would love to get to a
bunch more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re at a NY area High School and you think there&amp;#39;s a fit -
hit me up - I&amp;#39;d love to visit and meet and talk with your kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter CS - a lot of progress in a short time</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I was back on campus for an early orientation session for
Hunter&amp;#39;s incoming Daedalus CS honors students. It was the first time
all of us got to meet face to face. The students I met with will be
my third cohort. I got to thinking how far we&amp;#39;ve come in under three
years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s had a strong but little known undergraduate
CS program for as long as I&amp;#39;ve known. Much like any program, we&amp;#39;ve got
our strengths and weaknesses but you go through our program and
academically you&amp;#39;ll be as well prepared as from anywhere else. We have some
challenges being a commuter school, a liberal arts school and a school
not commonly thought of for CS but the core has always been there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter has been making a concerted effort to up its computer science
game and my joining the team has been part of that. The Daedalus
program is an honors scholarship program. It&amp;#39;s similar to the well
known CUNY Macaulay program but it&amp;#39;s specific to Hunter and specific to
CS. Our kids get scholarships, laptops, special classes (with me),
activities and events and more. Our first cohort had 12. This past
year we had 23 but a funny thing happened right after we started. Hunter&amp;#39;s
Macaulay CS students heard about what was going on and wanted in. The
end result was that last years cohort had a total of 27 students
as we invited the incoming Hunter Macaulay CS students into the
fold. This year, we&amp;#39;re up to about 50 total and it looks to be a very
strong group. To be honest I&amp;#39;m a little
scared of growing this quickly. The kids will be great but it will be
a challenge building the community across multiple classes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m really pleased with the first two cohorts performance both in
class and out. They&amp;#39;re progressing well through the academic program
and are ahead of schedule in terms of internships and outside
activities but I&amp;#39;m even happier that they&amp;#39;ve been working to level up
Hunter CS as a whole. They started a once a week Dojo last year where
all Hunter CS students could hang out and work on tech projects and
have a speaker series on tap for this coming year. For my part, I&amp;#39;ve
got a couple of new ideas up my sleeve but I&amp;#39;m going to keep them
under wraps for now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Three years ago Hunter wasn&amp;#39;t so much on the map for CS inclined high
school students and while there&amp;#39;s much work to be done, many of our
incoming cohort members chose us over other programs that have
traditionally been considered CS strongholds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, our efforts to connect Hunter CS to the NY Tech community have begun to
raise our profile on the other end of the pipeline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s still a long rode ahead but I thought I&amp;#39;d give myself a day to
look back on how far we&amp;#39;ve come in a short time. Having a great public college option for CS
education is critical for NYC. This was one of the things I left Stuy to
accomplish and we&amp;#39;re well on our way.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>