<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hunter on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hunter/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (hunter)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 07:41:29 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hunter/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter&#39;s first Honors CS Cohort</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/first-daedalus-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 07:41:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/first-daedalus-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Almost four and a half years ago I left Stuyvesant and joined Hunter
College. One of the initiatives I was charged with was the creation of
a computer science honors program - the Daedalus scholars. Now, a
little over four years later, our first cohort is graduating.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m super proud of that first cohort and what we&amp;#39;ve collectively been
building. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I joined Hunter at the end of January 2016 - a month after college
applications had closed. This meant that we had to build our first
cohort after the fact. Nobody applied to Hunter to be a part of the
Daedalus scholars because we didn&amp;#39;t exist. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, by looking at the students who had already applied to Hunter we
found a few that were interested and qualified. We lost a few along
the way - a student who really wanted an engineering program, one who
had already conditionally been accepted to another school but took our
money for the semester (I really hate it when people exploit a system
like this but that&amp;#39;s another story), one who really didn&amp;#39;t know what
CS was and ended up not liking the subject, and one who really wanted
to leave the city. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During our first semester, some Macaulay students found out about our
program and wanted to join so we padded our numbers with a small
number of them. Overall we ended up with a small group of 12.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I&amp;#39;m proud of all of them for what they did at Hunter and
for what lies ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, four years later we get hundreds of applicants including a
growing number from outside the city and are taking in many more great
students. I don&amp;#39;t know the other colleges that our first cohort
members were accepted to but now we&amp;#39;re competing for students with
Stony Brook, NYU, RIT, and in some cases bigger &amp;#34;names.&amp;#34; My goal was
for us to become the best value CS and the best CS in NYC and we&amp;#39;re
well on our way. with the first cohort, we prototyped some activities
and events that have evolved into staples - tech mentoring, codefest,
interview prep and more. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first cohort led the way and I&amp;#39;m super proud of them. Now they&amp;#39;ll
become our first graduates and continue to be resource for both each
other and future Hunter CS students. This is now the start of another
endeavor - it took decades to create the StuyCS Mafia and now I get to
repeat the process with HunterCS  but this time, since I know what&amp;#39;s
to come I can enjoy the show as it unfolds.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter Codefest 2020</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codefest-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 13:41:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/codefest-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Two of the challenges faced by young computer science students are
finding the time to build independent projects for their portfolios
and getting feedback from and networking with tech professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enter Hunter Codefest 2020
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;
.flip {
    -webkit-transform: rotate(180deg);
    -moz-transform: rotate(180deg);
    -o-transform: rotate(180deg);
    -ms-transform: rotate(180deg);
    transform: rotate(180deg);
}
&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left flip&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/codefest.jpg&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;z_image_left flip&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/google.jpg&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter, like most colleges has a Fall semester that runs from late
August through the end of Decemeber and a Spring semester that starts
at the end of January and runs through late may. There&amp;#39;s generally
around a month between the two. Sometimes a student can take one of
the few courses offered during this &amp;#34;Winter semester&amp;#34; but more often
than not the time is wasted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Hunter, students can do a number of things during this break. Some get short term
mini internships, others take part in our tech bootcamps. Now, they
can all participate in Codefest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We launched in late December at the end of finals. Students are given
a theme and form groups. They then have a month to build a
project. It&amp;#39;s a great opportunity to learn how to work on a team and
explore tools that you wouldn&amp;#39;t normally use in a regular CS class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Friday was the payoff. We all gathered at GoogleNYC for a big
celebration. Each group was set up at a table with professional
Software Engineers. Mostly Googlers but wa also invited some outside
guests. They&amp;#39;d then spend time with discussing the project. After a
while, the Googlers would rotate to another project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rinse and repeat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/gil.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Current Googler and Hunter CS grad Gil advising our current students.&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Current Googler and Hunter CS grad Gil advising our current students.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/sarah.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;My former Stuy student and current Googler Sarah doing the same.&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;My former Stuy student and current Googler Sarah doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards we had some demos and then a big networking session where
our Hunter CS students got to spend more time getting to know and
getting advice from a host of Googlers and other software engineers
while enjoying refreshments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not everyone could make it due to class but we had a pretty strong
turnout.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;flip&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/everyone.jpg&#34; width=&#34;75%&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our student organizers did most of the heavy lifting and made the
whole event work from start to finish. Here are Leo, Angela, Shariar,
and Tracey. Our two other organizers, Miguel and Kun couldn&amp;#39;t make it
as Miguel was travelling and Kun had an interview for an internship.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/codefest2020/organizers.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Our organizers&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Our organizers&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Special thanks to Brendan and hist team of Googlers who helped make
this happen. I also want to say thanks to the dozen or so of my former
students currently at Google who stopped by to help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everyone was super impressed with what the students produced. It was
a great event and it&amp;#39;ll be even better next year.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hunter Daedalus Fall 2019 recruiting class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 08:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/daedalus-class-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that high school seniors have all committed to their respective
colleges I though I&amp;#39;d share some information on Hunter&amp;#39;s incoming
Daedalus (honors CS) cohort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I joke about the first cohort saying that nobody applied to the
program. That&amp;#39;s kind of true. I jointed Hunter a little over three
years ago in late January. That was after high school seniors had
already applied to college and at that time the program didn&amp;#39;t
exist. We found the first cohort by looking at students who had
already applied to Hunter not expecting Daedalus to exist.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was 12 kids and we&amp;#39;ve lost a few since then. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second cohort consisted of 24 students. We started adding
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_E._Macaulay_Honors_College&#34;&gt;Macaulay&lt;/a&gt; students into the mix. Macaulay is a CUNY wide honors
scholarship program. Each campus has a cohort and it was part of an
effort to bring CUNY back to it&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;glory days&amp;#34; before open
enrollment. The Macaulay kids saw that Daedalus was the place to be
for CS in NYC and Hunter and wanted in. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Third year, we were up to 44 students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, in our fourth year we&amp;#39;re up to 50 which is a little over
capacity - at least until I can find and hire a partner in crime  (and
I am looking).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some other stats:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year:&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2016&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Size:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daedalus / Macaulay:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75% / 25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75%/ 20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;80% / 20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Approximate Applicants&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;~150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;~200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Over 320&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gender M/F %&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80/20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50/50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;75/25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Taken APCS / Beginner&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50/50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;50/50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Number of high schools&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;# students from beyond NYC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also have stats on grades and test scores as well as the number of
offers an the percent of acceptances. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some thoughts on the stats:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I try to spend as much time as I can doing outreach. This is horribly
inefficient but it&amp;#39;s slowly getting the word out. I might spend most
of a day trekking out into the boroughs to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/&#34;&gt;talk to a class&lt;/a&gt; or a few
classes at some school knowing that there will probably be very few
fits for my program. I think I&amp;#39;m bringing important information to all
of the kids but it&amp;#39;s a low yield activity. Right now our biggest
feeder schools are Stuyvesant, Brooklyn Tech, and Bronx Science. Next
is Midwood. This makes sense as they&amp;#39;re all &lt;strong&gt;large&lt;/strong&gt; schools and they
all have established CS classes. They&amp;#39;ll probably continue to be the
biggest feeders but I&amp;#39;m delighted by the fact that I&amp;#39;m getting
students from 17 other schools including a couple from outside of
NYC. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m less happy with the gender distribution. Twenty five percent isn&amp;#39;t
bad compared to the national numbers but we should be doing
better. It&amp;#39;s a tough nut to crack. When I visit to schools I&amp;#39;m
normally sent to the CS classes so I&amp;#39;m already getting a gender skewed
audience. Not sure the best approach to work on this. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, I&amp;#39;m getting to enough of a general audience to have
roughly a 50/50 split of students with APCS-A or beyond or what I
would call a beginner. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I get to know this new group and find out why they applied to
Hunter Daedalus and ultimately decided to attend I&amp;#39;m hoping to be able
to better fine tune my recruiting approach and outreach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a bottom line I&amp;#39;m going to continue to work to make Hunter&amp;#39;s
Daedalus program the place to be for CS education in NY so that kids
can get a top flight experience without paying a quarter of a million
dollars.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College Winter Codefest 2019</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 17:34:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/code-fest-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s great to see how much Hunter CS has developed since starting here
there years ago. The latest endeavor is Winter Codefest. During the
fall I was approached by one of my students who had asked an older
Hunter CS student about their portfolio and found that the senior&amp;#39;s
portfolio was lacking. This student said we should do something to
help encourage younger students to build that portfolio. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The result was Winter Codefest. A team of organizers was formed and
they came up with the plan. Have students register teams right after
Fall finals and have teams work on independent projects over the
course of January before the Spring semester started. We&amp;#39;d then have an
event where everyone would show off their work. We decided to limit
participants to my Daedalus scholars this time around but planned from
the get go to make it Hunter wide in the future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended up with about 24 participants spanning all three Daedalus
cohorts with most of the participants in the second year group. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Due to the scheduling we couldn&amp;#39;t hold the end of competition event
until today. A bunch of us gathered along with some of our friends
from the tech community to review the projects, network, and generally
talk tech. All in all the event was a real success. All the
participants learned new  technologies and now have one more show
piece to talk about in interviews.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year was unquestionably a success and it&amp;#39;s going to be a bigger
one next year. The CS department is working on creating 1 and 2 credit
projects courses that will be offered during the winter session. This
will enable students to take the courses to develop a Winterfest
project with the support of a class around it. We&amp;#39;re also going to
make the event available to all Hunter CS students. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s really exciting to be part of developing programs like Hunter
College CS, Programs that can be super transformative for young New
Yorkers. It&amp;#39;s even more exciting when your students take active
leadership roles and help make our programs even more special.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges of teaching at a commuter school</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 08:43:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/commuter-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the bigger challenges faced at commuter schools is building a
feeling of community. Students aren&amp;#39;t on campus every day and come
from far afield and even when they are on campus, we really don&amp;#39;t have
a CS &amp;#34;hang out&amp;#34; space. The space issue should be resolved soon - we&amp;#39;re
scheduled to get a CS student lounge next semester.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m finding this to be even more of a challenge this year with my
honors students. The first two cohorts were a single class in
size. Even though some dormed and some commuted, they were all
together in my class twice a week. This year, we&amp;#39;ve close to doubled
in size and about half of my students came in with a good deal of
prior CS knowledge. The result is that I have two different classes of
honors students and we are never all together unless it&amp;#39;s for a
special event.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, we&amp;#39;ve got one of my favorites coming up. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In two weeks, I&amp;#39;ll be taking about half my students up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;Catskills
Conf&lt;/a&gt;. An event that I describe as light tech conference with a focus
on creativity and diversity meets summer camp. I&amp;#39;ve written about the
event in in each of the past three years (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015/%0A&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskillsconf-2016/%0A&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskills-2017/%0A&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;) and also
about the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/knitting-tech-conference/%0A&#34;&gt;knitting for charity&lt;/a&gt; event that Devorah runs during the
conference weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event and if you&amp;#39;re anywhere near the Hudson Valley
region you should &lt;a href=&#34;http://catskillsconf.com&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, it&amp;#39;s a great first conference for the students. It only has
one track so no choices and the talks look really interesting this
year. Some of the ones I&amp;#39;m looking forward to are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Designing for Access first
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Behind the Tech: Emoji
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Leaning into uncertainty
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The full schedule is &lt;a href=&#34;https://catskillsconf.com/schedule/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But also mixed in are activities like blacksmithing
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/blacksmith.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and a live bird of prey show
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/BOP.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are also hikes that show off the beauty of Fall in the Hudson
Valley
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature1.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature2.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/nature3.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rather than having the kids spread out in random hotel rooms we&amp;#39;re all
in a camp style bunkhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/bunkhouse.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The weekend is spent  living together along with technologists and
other creative types from NYC, the Hudson Valley and everywhere else. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my favorite parts is at the end of each evening when we all
hang out by the campfire. Hunter CS students, company founders,
software engineers, designers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/commuter-school/campfire.jpg&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;250px&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a great event overall and a great event to build community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said before, if you&amp;#39;re in the area, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 in review - Hunter Undergraduate CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I usually don&amp;#39;t do year in review posts. At Stuy, not much changed
year after year so I never felt it worth summarizing the past and
projecting the future. At Hunter, now that I&amp;#39;m a couple of years in,
projects are really picking up steam so I think it&amp;#39;s worth talking
about them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my two major missions at Hunter was to build a CS Honors
program and raise the profile of Hunter&amp;#39;s undergraduate CS program in
general. Hunter had a strong CS program before I joined the team it&amp;#39;s
just that few people knew about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My goal is to see Hunter become the &amp;#34;go to&amp;#34; institution for
undergraduate CS in New York City before my time is done.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is an extremely important mission.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are other strong CS options besides Hunter but compare the costs:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Institution&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Annual Tuition&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NYU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$50,464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NYY Tandon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$48,750&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Columbia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$54,504&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hunter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$6,530&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunter is about one tenth the cost.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
True, if you&amp;#39;re wealthy this isn&amp;#39;t a problem and if you&amp;#39;re at the
bottom of the economic ladder you might get a full ride but if you
fall into that category where you earn more than the financial aid
people think is &amp;#34;poor&amp;#34; but are clearly not rich you&amp;#39;re left in a bad place. This seems
particularly true for New Yorkers as our income seems higher than that
of people from other parts of the country but our cost of living is
higher as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My wife and I are both career public educators. No one would confuse a
family of two working teachers as upper class but we were granted no
financial aid for our kids. The alternatives without a great public
option are to have saved for our entire lives and now liquidate those
savings or go into tremendous debt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes the mission critical. Add to that the accessibility
issue - elite private institutions only have to concern themselves
with whatever slice of the population they choose to accept. We are
charged with providing a top flight education to all - be they the
high achievers, the late bloomers, the struggling students or anyone
else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what&amp;#39;s happened in the past year?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, the Daedalus honors program is developing nicely. In our first
year we had a cohort of 12. This past year 27. I haven&amp;#39;t seen the
applicant pool yet - Hunter applications are open until the end of
January, but I&amp;#39;m hoping to bring in an even larger cohort this year. I
spent a good amount of time this fall visiting high schools to talk
about Hunter CS and CS options in general. Not as many as I&amp;#39;d like but
more than during year one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had classes, trips, and special events but more important was that
the cohort is starting to form a community and the students want it to
be a community that includes ALL of Hunter CS, not just the honors
students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They&amp;#39;ve started a once a week Dojo where students can work on projects
and interact and we&amp;#39;re starting an evening speaker series in
the Spring.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall there&amp;#39;s a vibe of excitement and an energy around Hunter CS
that I&amp;#39;ve been told hasn&amp;#39;t been there before.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my class, I&amp;#39;ve been introducing a number of real world practices
that are usually not covered in undergraduate CS and we&amp;#39;re starting to
talk about bringing those practices into the non-honors sections.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we&amp;#39;ve started to partner with the New York Tech
community. We&amp;#39;re bringing together the Hunter students and the tech
professionals to raise awareness outside of Hunter of what our
students can do and to best prepare our students for their next
steps. These partnerships, in addition to internship possibilities
have led to us planning some great things this coming semester
incuding:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
workshops such as how to work on an open source project or how to do
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
a code review.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having industry mentors at our local Dojo sessions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mixer events to educate our students as to the variety of pathways
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
they can follow when they graduate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past year set the stage but there will be some challenges moving
forward.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest one is continued outreach to high schools. Getting to the
students and their parents to let them know that we have a great
program. It&amp;#39;s also about convincing them to come to Hunter. Back in
the day CUNY was &amp;#34;the poor man&amp;#39;s Harvard&amp;#34; but open enrollment in the
1970s killed that reputation. CUNY has been making it&amp;#39;s way back and
Hunter has many excellent programs but reputations are decades in the
making and at Hunter CS we&amp;#39;re just starting to get the word out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other big challenge will be with time. Right now, for the most
part, I&amp;#39;m a team of one. I have tremendous support from my colleagues
but they all have their own full time obligations and the overall
growth in Hunter CS has already put a strain on personnel and
resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of the challenges, I&amp;#39;m not complaining. This has been an
exciting year for Hunter CS and an exciting year for me to be a part
of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;


&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s been a while since my last post and a while since I started at
Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time to share a bit about what I&#39;ve been up to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College&#39;s
computer science program. It&#39;s been around for years and it&#39;s been
that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters
degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the
area&#39;s MS in CS programs. It came down to Hunter College and Courant
Institute at NYU. I was going to go with Hunter since the programs
seemed comparable and Hunter was far more affordable but I had to go
with NYU due to class schedules. Too many of the Hunter offerings were
to early in the day and I had my full time teaching job to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter isn&#39;t currently offering their Masters program but their
Bachelor of Arts program is alive and well, it&#39;s just that people
don&#39;t know about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part of my job is to change that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, not really, part of my job is to add my piece to the puzzle. The
rest will take care of itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My piece? It&#39;s all about creating a tech culture, tying into the NY
Tech ecosystem, and filling in the gaps that are shared by just about
every college computer science program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do we do it?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The long term plan is that we&#39;re starting a new CS Honors program. In
the fall, I&#39;ll be teaching and mentoring a group of entering
undergrads. We&#39;ll have workshops, trips, activities. You name it. I&#39;ll
also be teaching them modified versions of our courses with the hope
of bringing some of my modifications back to the rest of the student
body. Things like integrating real tools and professional techniques
into what is already a solid academic program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the mean time, I&#39;m getting to know Hunter&#39;s current CS students and
working to energize the existing community.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We already had an amazing event hosted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://yext.com&#34;&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt;. We had a panel and
mixer with representatives from about a dozen companies talking to the
kids about the possibilities ahead of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ve also set up a couple of workshops in house.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m also starting to talk to friends at companies across the city to
plan out both curriculum and programs to set up our kids to
succeed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is that within five years, I want people to realize that
Hunter CS is the place to be for CS Education in NYC. Not everyone can
afford the 40K and up private college tuition and there&#39;s no reason to
when you can get a great CS education with ties to the tech community
at CUNY prices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to help, drop me a note. We&#39;re looking to start something
very special and you have a chance to be a part of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>