<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HS on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hs/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (HS)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/hs/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting schools and talking tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 15:49:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-tour-revisited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Back in September I talked about embarking on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/&#34;&gt;Fall 2018 HS CS Tour&lt;/a&gt;.
Since then I&amp;#39;ve visited about a dozen schools. I&amp;#39;d like to thank my
friends who helped connect me to schools - particularly &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aankit&#34;&gt;Aankit Patel&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/diane_levitt&#34;&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though the original motivation for the visits was to get the word
out about Hunter CS and the awesome things we&amp;#39;re doing in the Hunter
CS Honors program I always tried to make my talks about something that
would be relevant for the entire audience and not just the few that
were great fits for my program. I think I&amp;#39;ve done a pretty good job at
that. All this said, doing these visits is incredibly draining. I&amp;#39;m
usually up at the crack of dawn and end up taking the subway or
sometimes subway and bus way out into the five boroughs. Actually four
this year since I wasn&amp;#39;t able to get a date to visit any Staten Island
schools. It takes a lot of time and effort and while I love
talking to students and there some ancillary things I enjoy about
getting out into the neighborhoods of the city I&amp;#39;m extremely happy
that I can now rest for a few weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reflecting on all of this I&amp;#39;m realizing how important these visits are
and not because they&amp;#39;re recruiting trips.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spoke about some of the specifics I talk about in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;
but arguably more important is that for many of them it&amp;#39;s the first
time for them to hear about the possibilities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While many students are excited about what they&amp;#39;re doing in their first
CS classes it turns out that few have any idea where it will
lead. They may have heard that computer science can lead to a high
paying job. They might know they can get a job at Google but they
don&amp;#39;t really know what that means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I saw this at Hunter when I started three years ago and now a lot of
hard work later students are much more in tune with the New York Tech
community and all that it means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students don&amp;#39;t realize that there are many programming careers beyond
Google and their are many CS careers beyond programming. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They don&amp;#39;t realize they can combine computer science with almost any
other field or interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They don&amp;#39;t know that the same algorithmic approach behind Amazon,
Netflix, and Spotify recommendations can be used by companies selling
cloths, cosmetics, or anything else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that&amp;#39;s just the tip of the iceberg. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now I&amp;#39;m not saying that teachers aren&amp;#39;t telling their students about
the possibilities but rather that sometimes it has to come from an
outsider. When I started at Stuy, before I had a reputation (good or
bad) I&amp;#39;d tell students things and they wouldn&amp;#39;t buy it. Later I&amp;#39;d have
a friend from the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; come in. Frequently they&amp;#39;d touch on
points I addressed in class and all of a sudden I was worth listening
to. Sometimes you need an outside voice to empower and authenticate the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying that I&amp;#39;m a super motivational speaker or anything like
that. I&amp;#39;m not. I&amp;#39;m an ok speaker with content worth listening to. I&amp;#39;m
just realizing more and more how important this small self imposed
corner of my job is. Not so much for Hunter but for the kids of NY. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jut this past week I&amp;#39;ve started to work to connect some of my current
students to &lt;a href=&#34;http://tealsk12.org&#34;&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; volunteers. If you read this blog you know I&amp;#39;m a
big fan of TEALS and have wanted to encourage my students to get
involved for a while. Once we get some of our Hunter CS majors into
schools around the city to help teach CS perhaps they can help spread
the message of the possibilities to even more students.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2018 HS CS Tour</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 16:57:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/fall-2018-hs-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve written before about why &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/&#34;&gt;Hunter College CS is so important&lt;/a&gt; for
NYC and I&amp;#39;ve been working hard to develop our Daedalus Scholars honors
CS program -  a program in which students receive a scholarship along
with all sorts of special opportunities to add on to their in class CS
education. The program and Hunter CS as a whole have &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/&#34;&gt;made a lot of
progress&lt;/a&gt; over the past two years and each year I roll out new
special activities and events for my honors students. Still, a major
challenges is getting the word out and building our reputation. Anyone
who takes a close look at what we&amp;#39;re doing can see we&amp;#39;re growing
something special but we still have to convince students and parents
who may not even realize that Hunter offers a CS degree to come to us
instead of going to more well known albeit much more expensive programs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To that end I try to visit as many high schools as I can during the
Fall semester to speak to high school seniors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Friday at Packer Collegiate.
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Great to have &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/zamansky?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt; come by and talk to juniors and seniors in the advanced CS about the tech sector and options for study including the amazing program at Hunter &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ubHNfyt8Y9&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ubHNfyt8Y9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; saber khan (@ed_saber) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber/status/1045768969519542272?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34;
charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was invited by my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ed_saber&#34;&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; who runs the weekly twitter
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first started doing school visits I had a tough time figuring
out exactly what to say - I&amp;#39;m no salesman - I&amp;#39;m not good at it and I
don&amp;#39;t like doing it. Fortunately, I didn&amp;#39;t have to be a salesman. I
decided I&amp;#39;d talk to the students about questions they should be asking
themselves as they consider where to go after graduation. I talk about
school location, community, and culture. I also talk about majors - BA
vs BS, Major vs Minor, niche majors, and possible career paths. I also
talk about tech sectors - how NY might be different from Sill icon
Valley might be different from Seattle or Boston.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also tell them the truth about the undergraduate experience - how
you can get a great CS background at all sorts of schools. How
Algorithms is Algorithms and no matter where you go you&amp;#39;ll probably
use the same text and how while I have many former students at the
Googles and Facebooks of the world that  have gone to MIT and CMU I
also have plenty who end up at those companies or similar going to
Stony, Oberlin, Tufts, and yes, Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the talk I spend a few minutes talking about Hunter and
my honors program but it&amp;#39;s only a small part of the talk. I figure in
any given class there will be a few kids who could be a fit for my
program and I want the time spent to be worthwhile for the entire
class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes guidance people sit in when I talk to the students and
almost always they tell me how valuable it was for the students to
have someone like me come in and talk frankly about the college
application and acceptance process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s going to take time to build our reputation at Hunter but I think
that going around to students and talking honestly about college and
not giving the hard sell helps build trust and our reputation and over
time, people will realize the value we&amp;#39;re bringing to the table and
come to us. It&amp;#39;s already happening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, the only other challenge is to get more high schools to bring me
in. Next week I&amp;#39;m visiting NEST+M and Brooklyn Tech and I&amp;#39;ve got a few
more on the calendar in upcoming weeks but would love to get to a
bunch more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re at a NY area High School and you think there&amp;#39;s a fit -
hit me up - I&amp;#39;d love to visit and meet and talk with your kids.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>