<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>data structures on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/data-structures/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (data structures)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 13:53:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/data-structures/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Heaps</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/heaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 13:53:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/heaps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Continuing with the theme of alternate representations we just 
started &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heap_(data_structure)&#34;&gt;heaps&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_heap&#34;&gt;binary heaps&lt;/a&gt;. 
binary min and max heaps.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Heaps are one of my favorite topics in CS2. If you&amp;#39;re not familiar
with them, a binary min heap is a complete binary tree that enforces
the heap property. By being complete we mean that every level except
possibly the last one is full - that is 2 children. The last level is
as filled left to right. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The heap property for a min heap is that the key value stored in any
node is less than the values in it&amp;#39;s children. Heaps are frequently
used as priority queues. There are plenty of great web sites and
videos that talk all about heaps - creating them, standard operations,
run time etc. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I love about them though is that they tie together
arrays and trees. Up until now, we&amp;#39;ve been using pointers to represent
trees. Our binary trees are represented by a class with a pointer to a
root node. Each node has pointers to left and right
children. Technically you could represent a heap in this way but with
a heap you have to be able to not only navigate easily from parent to
child but also from child to parent. This would make things a bit
unwieldy with additional parent pointers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Instead consider the following tree:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/heap/heap1.png&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve numbered each of the nodes with the root - node 0 holding a key
value of 10. We can easily store this tree in an array:#heaps.org#
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/heap/heap1-array.png&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We have an easy relationship between parent and child. Given any node &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;,
its children are located at &lt;code&gt;2n+1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;2n+2&lt;/code&gt;. Likewise we can use
integer division  &lt;code&gt;(n-1)/2&lt;/code&gt; to find a node&amp;#39;s parent. Easy peasy. This
is both easy and efficient and of course we can also go from an array
to a tree and in fact, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heapsort&#34;&gt;heapsort&lt;/a&gt; algorithm takes an arrray and
rearranges the elements into a heap and then uses heap operations to
sort the array all in place and in O(nlgn) time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here we have another cool representation. We can of course represent a
tree by explicitly creating classes for nodes with all the required
pointers but here we are implicitly creating a tree by using a mapping
to relate nodes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We could of course do this for any binary tree:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/heap/heap2.png&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/heap/heap2-array.png&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; Nodes 11 and 12 in the tree above should be 13 and 14. I messed up the
graphviz dot source for the diagram and am too lazy to
correct. Likewise there should be two extre cells in the array and the
32 and 50 should be in cells 13 and 14 respectively. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is where the completeness comes in. The fact that a heap is
complete and the last level is filled in left to right means that
there aren&amp;#39;t any unused cells in the array. If we just had any old
binary tree like the one above, we&amp;#39;re going to waste space. It could
still at times be a useful representation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like talking to my students about these types of data structures and
representations. Without considering cases like this you can get
programmers who adhere to the saying that &amp;#34;If your only tool is a
hammer then every problem looks like a nail.&amp;#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alternate Representations</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alternate-representations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 12:54:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/alternate-representations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There was a comment on my last post about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/arbitrary-trees/&#34;&gt;arbitary trees&lt;/a&gt; on Reddit
talking about how this type of data structure was a hold over from the
old days when computer resources were more limited. Nowadays having a
list of children makes more sense. The comment was of course correct
but I still think it&amp;#39;s worth teaching representations like the one I
spoke of in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/arbitrary-trees/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking at interesting and different ways of representing data and
modeling solutions is one of the things that separates programmers or
coders from computer scientists and software engineers. I&amp;#39;m not
talking about commonly accepted definitions or advanced classwork or
theory and mathy stuff. I&amp;#39;m talking about how you approach a problem. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me, the coder or programmer is someone who has learned rudimentary
coding prowess but learned via rote example. This is typical of a code
school graduate or many self taught programmers. This is not to say
that people who learned this way are not computer scientists at heart
nor that they don&amp;#39;t have the ability to think deeply about problems
but rather that their training was superficial - usually to get them
to market quickly. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know many people who started on their own following a book or mooc
or code school and grew beyond those basics but we&amp;#39;ve also seen many
&amp;#34;coders&amp;#34; who brute force using the same techniques regardless of
appropriateness. I can&amp;#39;t tell you how many times I&amp;#39;ve seen an SQL
database used inappropriately as a flat file store or forcing
relationships when not optimal in something like MongoDB. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We don&amp;#39;t want our students to merely parrot the solution that we went
over in class. We want them to consider the problem at hand and all
the tools in their tool belt and come up with what makes sense. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like the arbitrary tree example as it uses the same internal
structure as a binary tree does: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a binary search tree pointer1 is left and pointer 2 is right. For
an arbitrary tree they represent first child and next sibling. The
same structure can also be used for a doubly linked list with previous
and next or a skip list. It&amp;#39;s all about creatively using the tools at
hand. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a number of lessons during which we can stretch our students
thinking in terms of data representations in our early classes. One is
when we can augment a data structure to avoid special cases. I wrote
about this when solving a maze or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-26-change-the-data/&#34;&gt;knight&amp;#39;s tour&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those problems are also great place to talk about implicit data
structures. When we do our maze solver we talk about state space
search. The idea that there&amp;#39;s this huge graph where each node is the
a potential state of the maze and the edges represent how we can move
from state to state:#alternate-representations.org#
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/mazestates.png&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The above graph can be considered an implicit data structure - it
never actually exists as a whole in our program. Our solver usually
uses a two dimensional array to represent a specific state of our
maze - that is, one node of the graph. We change the array as we make
and return from recursive calls. That recursion creates and destroys
nodes in our graph. At any point in time, each layer of stack in the
recursion holds one node in our graph with the top of the stack being
our current state but we never actually create or internally represent
the full graph. It&amp;#39;s an ephemeral implicit data structure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, one very early opportunity to discuss these types of ideas
come when you use an array as a set of buckets where the index is the
value and the entry is the count. It&amp;#39;s pretty simple but a very
different way of using an array or list when all you&amp;#39;ve seen is using
it to store actual items. I like doing this in the context of a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-who_won_the_election-quadratic_to_linear_time/&#34;&gt;frequency&lt;/a&gt; lesson.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it&amp;#39;s sometimes worthwhile to look at solutions that may
no longer be optimal - they can be great triggers of both student
thought and discussion.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrary Trees</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/arbitrary-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 18:45:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/arbitrary-trees/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been 10 days from my last post. Not really a big break for me
historically but certainly a big one given how much I&amp;#39;ve been posting
this year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Been under the weather for the past couple of weeks dealing with
COVID-19. Haven&amp;#39;t had super bad symptoms and as symptoms have been
getting fewer and less severe I&amp;#39;m hoping I&amp;#39;m close to a full recovery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, I&amp;#39;m feeling good enough for a quick post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my data structures class we&amp;#39;ve been working on binary trees. Most
of the unit is focused on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_search_tree&#34;&gt;Binary Search Trees&lt;/a&gt;. They used to be a big
part of the B part of the old APCS-AB and are still a mainstay of
college CS2 classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As usual, we covered all the basics. Creation, insertion, search,
traversal, and deletion. We discovered the run times and how a tree
structure can yield lgn behavior but can also degenerate to linear. We
also give a preview of more advanced data structures like red/back and
2-3 trees that address these issues (not to mention things like BTrees
and Splay trees).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One side topic I always like talking about during this unit though are
arbitrary trees. That is, trees where each node can have an arbitrary
number of children. Students usually start by creating nodes with an
array of children and then sometimes a linked list of children but I
like discussing something simpler. A tree where in each node you hold
two pointers - a pointer to the first child and a pointer to the next
sibling. I like this because internally it&amp;#39;s the same as a binary
search tree where you also have two pointers in each node a left and a
right. Same &amp;#34;physical&amp;#34; representation but two very different
variations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/arbtree.png&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The image on the left is the actual arbitrary tree and the one on the
right shows the internal representation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of applications, the file system is a
great example of an arbitrary tree. Another one that I like even more
is the DOM representation of a web page. That&amp;#39;s nice because there are
Javascript functions to get the next sibling.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I put a short video together for my class. Here it is in case anyone
is interested. It&amp;#39;s code agnostic so would be suitable for an APCS-A
class that also covers data structures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&amp;#34;560&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;315&amp;#34;
src=&amp;#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K1lR3ssgxLc&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K1lR3ssgxLc&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#34; frameborder=&amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
allow=&amp;#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope;
picture-in-picture&amp;#34; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 3 - word chains</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/word-chains/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 05:45:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/word-chains/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
At this point, we&amp;#39;ve done a fair amount of playing with text so it&amp;#39;s
time for a fun little project. We&amp;#39;re going to generate some text &amp;#34;in
the style&amp;#34; of a source text. The technique we&amp;#39;re going to use is
usually called a Markov Chain text generator. Basically a model where
the next state or word is based entirely on the current state. I don&amp;#39;t
dwell on the math under the hood but in case you&amp;#39;re interested, here
are a few links: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://setosa.io/ev/markov-chains/&#34;&gt;Explained Visually&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.math.ucdavis.edu/~daddel/linear_algebra_appl/Applications/MarkovChain/MarkovChain_9_18/MarkovChain_9_18.html&#34;&gt;UC Davis Math&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can motivate this lesson in a number of ways. One is to start by
showing some generated text - for this, a flowery, poetic text like
the Book of Psalms works well. You can generate text a bunch of times
until you get a good result. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the start of the Book of Psalms:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;Blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the
ungodly, nor standeth in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in
the seat of the scornful.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and here&amp;#39;s some generated text:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;Blessed is the people that delight in war. Princes shall come out of
Zion,  the perfection of beauty god hath shined our god shall come and
shall declare thy mighty acts. I will speak of the glory of the lord
surely i will not lie unto David.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I added the punctuation as our generator strips it all and converts
the text to lower case.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The generated text looks reasonable in some ways but is clearly wrong
in others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This leads to the conversation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we look at the original text, it starts with &amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34; but if we
look at our bag of words we also can see that &amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34; appears 49
times. What&amp;#39;s interesting for generating text are the words the follow
&amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34; and the number of times they follow it. Here they are
(sorted for convenience):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Word&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;How many times it follows the word &amp;#34;blessed&amp;#34;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;are&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;art&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;be&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;blessed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;depart&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;his&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;that&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;thee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;thy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;upon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wealth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So we&amp;#39;ll have a lot of things like &amp;#34;blessed be the&amp;#34; &amp;#34;blessed be he&amp;#34;
etc. but only one occurrence of &amp;#34;blessed upon….&amp;#34; To generate text, we
can build a dictionary where the keys are the words and the values are
all the words that follow the key. We can build this with a variation
on our bag of words builder:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that we need a counting loop rather than just iterating over the
list since we need both the current item and the one after it in each
iteration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The (partial) value for the wordlists for the Book of Psalms would be:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point, generating text is easy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Start with a word
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Add the word to yoru story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Look  it up in your wordlists dictionary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
select a random word from that words dictionary entry (it&amp;#39;s list).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That becomes the word for the next iteration
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Repeat until you have enough words.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This won&amp;#39;t add any punctuation and it will crash when it gets to the
last word in the original text (as it can&amp;#39;t find any &amp;#34;next words&amp;#34; but
basically it will work. Here&amp;#39;s the code:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;code&gt;random.choice()&lt;/code&gt; randomly selects a word from a list. This is
perfect for us since words that follow our key more frequently will
have more entries in the list and thus appear more often. I decided to
build a list of words and then use the &lt;code&gt;&amp;#34; &amp;#34;.join()&lt;/code&gt; to turn it all
into a space separated string.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is pretty fun but the students will note that it really doesn&amp;#39;t
work that well. This can lead to increasing our sample. Instead of
using a single word as our key and having chain links based on two
words (key, random choice from value), we can use three word
links. Use a two word tuple for the key and the same list of words as
the value.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, a partial dictionary based on this idea from Macbeth Act
1 Scene 1 could be:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-python&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This takes a bit more work to build and also a bit more work to
generate text but it&amp;#39;s eminently doable and the result is
better. What about three word keys? Four? These aren&amp;#39;t hard to write
and ambitious students can write a generic dicitonary builder and
story generator routine so as to be able to use any key lenght.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Students will find that the longer the key, the better the resultant
story. They&amp;#39;ll also notice that at some point, all you&amp;#39;ll ever
generate is the original back again. This is a great time to talk
about over-training.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This can be a fun unit and / or assignment. I used source materials
that I like but any text will work.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 2 - bag of words</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bag-of-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 08:15:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bag-of-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Following up on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-textx/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;#39;re going to continue to talk about
playing with text. This time, building and working with a bag of words
from a text. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A bag of words is a simple language processing model where you just
consider individual words in a text. What they are and how many times
they occur. This is a pretty simple model but you can still have a
good bit of fun with your students with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if you take a text like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This land is your land
this land is my land
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once you clean the a data as per the previous post you get the
following bag:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;word&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;land&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;my&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;this&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;your&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not too interesting but it gets more interesting on a larger text. We
used:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Act 1 Scene 1 from Macbeth (for testing - it&amp;#39;s only 13 lines)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cyrano de Bergerac (because it&amp;#39;s my favorite play)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moby Dick (chapter 1)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moby Dick (full text)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Book of Psalms
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Assuming a cleaned string with all the text, building the bag is
pretty easy:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;cleaned_text &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;a string with all the cleaned text&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;bag&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;{}
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; cleaned_text&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;split():
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;  bag&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;setdefault(word,&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;  bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;code&gt;setdefault&lt;/code&gt; in line three says that if &lt;code&gt;word&lt;/code&gt; isn&amp;#39;t a key in the
dictionary then insert it with a value of 0, otherwise, if &lt;code&gt;word&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt;
already a key in the dictionary do nothing. This saves us from
constructs like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; bag:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;      bag[word]&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;      bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we have our bag we can do some explorations. Take out all the
values using &lt;code&gt;bag.values()&lt;/code&gt; and sort them. Ask &amp;#34;what words are going
to occur most frequently?&amp;#34; It&amp;#39;s easy to guess that it will be words
like &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;of&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; etc.. Words that don&amp;#39;t really tell us anything
about the text. It&amp;#39;s a fun puzzle to figure out where the
&amp;#34;interesting&amp;#34; words start and even the question of what might make a
word in a text &amp;#34;interesting.&amp;#34; Words like &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt;, *and&amp;#34;, etc. are known
as &lt;a href=&#34;http://xpo6.com/list-of-english-stop-words/&#34;&gt;stop words&lt;/a&gt;. Depending on the application, you might want ot remove
them. Then again, you might not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Usually we take a bit of time just to play with the bag, looking at
the types of words in various count ranges. Sometimes we&amp;#39;ll make bags
for different chapters of books and compare them. This is also when I
cover Python list comprehensions which make experimenting on bags of
words much cleaner. Say, for instance you want to find all the words
that occur between 50 and 100 times. Without list comprehensions you
might write:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;  result &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; []
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; bag:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;          result&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;append(word) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# or (word,count) or whatever&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While with the comprehension it&amp;#39;s:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;  result &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; [ word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; bag &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; bag[word] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;]
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides basic exploring, what else can you do? You can make word
vectors, that is a list or vector where an element is 1 if the word is
present and 0 otherwise. Then you can do simple document
comparisons. You can kick this up a notch if you calculate word
frequencies based on the bag counts and use these. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can also do basic sentiment analysis. Download a list of
&amp;#34;positive&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;negative&amp;#34; words and then check bags against them. You
can check to see how many negative or positive words are in a bag or
you can work with frequencies. You can also use other categories. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While we were discussing this at our PD, some teachers thought that
their classes might ahve a hard time doing all of this  from scratch
but thought that they could provide either the cleaning code or the
bag building code and have the students build experiments off of the
base. I thought it was a great idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of our session we all agreed to think about how we might
build a lesson or unit out of this bag of words idea. I&amp;#39;ll leave you
all with some web sites that use these ideas in what I think are
interesting ways:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://davidamackenzie.com/tmbg_lyrics/&#34;&gt;They Might Be Giants Lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.sap.com/2014/01/07/measuring-word-use-frequency-in-rap-song-lyrics/&#34;&gt;Word use in rap lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://genius.com/Sameoldshawn-rap-stats-breaking-down-the-words-in-rap-lyrics-over-time-annotated&#34;&gt;Another analysis of rap lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://towardsdatascience.com/text-analysis-of-successful-song-lyrics-e41a4ccb26f5&#34;&gt;Analysis of succesful song lyrics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A* is born</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/a-star-is-born/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/a-star-is-born/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Over on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;CS Educator StachExchange&lt;/a&gt;, which is in private beta for a
few more days, I saw a post asking about how to introduce the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A*_search_algorithm&#34;&gt;A*
search algorithm&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I taught A* as part of the APCS class at Stuy so I thought I&amp;#39;d talk
about what I did here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some time around mid year, we get to intermediate recursion. This is
about the time, give or take, when we talk about the nlogn sorts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also build a recursive maze solver. It&amp;#39;s a nice algorithm and a
nice little program. It&amp;#39;s around 15 lines of code to perform a
recursive depth first search:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/astar/dfs.gif&#34; alt=&#34;/img/astar/dfs.gif&#34; title=&#34;/img/astar/dfs.gif&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; height=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The basic algorithm is:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a nice lesson because in addition to all the recursion stuff, we
also get to talk about state space, state space search, backtracking,
efficiency concerns and much more. After we finish the maze solver, we also talk about
other problems that can be similarly examined using state-space search
like the knights tour and N-queens problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A month or so later, when we&amp;#39;re learning about stacks and queues as
data structures, we revisit the maze solver. This time we solve the
problem in a more general way. We talk about using a data structure to
hold the set of nodes that we&amp;#39;re aware of and that we want to visit
next.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-java&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we write the solution, we see that using a queue for this
data structure yields a breadth first search:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/astar/bfs.gif&#34; alt=&#34;/img/astar/bfs.gif&#34; title=&#34;/img/astar/bfs.gif&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; height=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
while using a stack yields depth first.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of this leads to a discussion as to how deciding on which
locations to look at next can greatly influence the steps to the
exit. From here it&amp;#39;s easy to see that you can use a heuristic to order
the nodes in our data structure so that we explore &amp;#34;better&amp;#34;
possibilities first. The data structure becomes a priority queue and
we finally get to both &amp;#34;best first&amp;#34; and A* search:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/astar/astar.gif&#34; alt=&#34;/img/astar/astar.gif&#34; title=&#34;/img/astar/astar.gif&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; height=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a nice sequence of lessons, albeit lessons spread out over
months. The end result is that the students see both the need and
motivation for something like A* and they see that it&amp;#39;s not hard to
implement. One basic routine where you can plug in one of three data
structures - stack, queue, or priority queue to get very different
results.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>